Recommended by the World Wildlife Fund
Tokuma Shoten and Hakuhodo present
Another village destroyed.
Lets go. Soon, this place will also
be consumed by the Sea of Decay.
1,000 years after the collapse
of industrial civilization,
the Sea of Decay, a swamp
exuding toxic vapors,
covered an earth strewn with rusting
ruins, threatening human survival.
NAUSICAÄ OF THE VALLEY OF THE WIND
Executive Producers
Yasuyoshi TOKUMA Michitaka KONDO
Original story and screenplay by
Hayao MIYAZAKI
Based on the serial graphic novel
"Nausicaä of the Valley of the Wind"
Music by
Joe HISAISHI
Producer
Isao TAKAHATA
Director
Hayao MIYAZAKI
An Ohm's tracks...
Still fresh.
An Ohm shell!
How amazing!
I've never seen such
a perfect shell before!
What a lovely sound...
It even chipped my ceramic sword!
The villagers will be pleased.
They'll have plenty of material to
make into tools now.
What an eye!
I wonder if I can carry it...
It came free!
So light.
Mushigo Palm spores...
So beautiful.
But this is a forest of death,
your lungs would rot
in five minutes without a mask.
What was that?
What can it be?
My heart is pounding in my chest!
Those are gunshots!
Someone is in trouble.
Oh, I'm sorry!
Over there!
What a thick cloud of toxins!
An Ohm!
That must have been its shell.
You'll never escape that way.
This way!
They answered!
They're coming!
Who's that?
What a magnificent Ohm!
Go upwind!
Thank you!
Return to the forest, Ohm.
This is not your world.
Be a good boy now.
It's blinded by rage!
I've got to do something!
The flares stunned it!
An insect charm...
Awaken, Ohm.
Return to the forest from
which you came.
It's awake!
The Ohm's returning to the forest!
She tamed that Ohm with nothing more
than flares and an insect charm!
Lord Yupa!
Nausicaa!
I hardly recognized you.
It's been almost a year and half.
Father will be glad to see you.
I must thank you for saving me.
You've become quite the wind-rider!
I've still got much to learn...
Oh, of course!
I completely forgot about him.
A fox-squirrel?
I've never seen one before.
When a winged insect snatched him up,
I mistook him for a human baby.
I had no choice but to fire my gun.
That's what enraged the Ohm.
He'd fainted, so he was
spared the forest poisons.
Better not touch him!
Even young, they're savage.
Come on...
Here.
Hey.
I'm not dangerous.
There's nothing to be afraid of.
See? Nothing to be afraid of.
See?
You were just frightened.
Oh Lord Yupa, may I have him?
Why certainly...
Thank you!
Kai and Kui!
Remember me?
What a mysterious gift she has...
You must be tired,
you've traveled so far.
Is everyone well?
What's wrong?
My father...
He can no longer fly.
Jihl...
The forest poisons?
Yes.
He says it's the fate for all
living by the Sea of Decay.
I should have come sooner.
Oh, no.
Thank you for coming at all.
Lord Yupa, there's something
I want to show you...
My secret room.
It's a secret because
I don't want to scare the Valley...
I'll tell them you're coming!
Come soon!
Lord Yupa
Would you carry this?
It's too heavy to fly with.
She certainly reads the wind well.
Not far now.
Oh...
Lord Yupa!
Welcome!
Are you feeling well?
The waters and winds
are clear and calm.
Lord Yupa!
Hello children, you're looking well!
We've missed you!
Princess, Lord Yupa has arrived.
Almost done...
Lord Yupa!
Old Mito, I see you're
hard at work as usual.
Tonight I'll hear the
tales of your travels!
OK. Start it up.
Seems to be working.
Yes.
This is excellent material!
Tomorrow, we'll send a
group of men to get the rest.
Come, Toeto. Don't be shy.
Lord Yupa...
This is Toeto's baby, born this year.
Oh? Let's have a look, shall we?
A fine baby indeed!
Reminds me of Nausicaa
when she was a baby.
Please be her godfather,
we would be honored.
Name her so that a fair wind
may favor her.
I will indeed.
I'll find her a fine name.
Thank you!
May she grow up
as strong as our Princess.
She's as strong as they come!
But we won't want her
playing around in the Sea of Decay.
But that's where
I found the Ohm shell, Mito.
Put yourself in my shoes.
I'm responsible for this castle-
-and she's made me sick with worry.
Let her play in the Sea of Decay
if she finds us Ohm shells.
Indeed, her presence
there saved my skin!
Saved by the girl?
This is a fine valley.
Being here calms my spirits.
How was your journey?
It was terrible.
The Sea of Decay consumed
two more nations to the south.
It's spreading all the time,
further and further every day.
And yet war and hunger
are everywhere.
Nothing but bad omens.
Why can't everybody live as peacefully
as you do here in this valley?
The ocean winds protect our valley.
The Sea of Decay
can't reach us here.
What do you say? Yupa?
Isn't it time you
settled in this valley?
Look at my condition...
It would bring everyone
peace of mind if you stayed.
He could never settle.
Yupa's a man who is fated
to search forever.
My fate, is it?
Obaba, what is he searching for?
Oh, my child. Don't you
know, Nausicaa?
Look there, see the
tapestry on the wall.
I can no longer see it,
though I remember it well.
There is a figure in the left corner
clothed in blue robes
descending onto a golden field
to mend the bond between Man and Earth
and guide the people to the pure land at last.
Lord Yupa, I always thought
that was only a legend.
You mustn't tease me, Obaba.
It is no legend, Yupa.
I only wish to solve
the Sea of Decay's mysteries.
Are we humans but a tribe
destined to be swallowed-
-and ruined by the Sea of Decay?
That is what I wish to know.
If only I could help Lord Yupa...
Princess, Princess!
What is it. Mito?
A strange scent on the wind,
somethings not right.
At this hour?
I'll be right there.
How is it?
It's one fine storm,
but somethings amiss.
Over there!
Look!
It's a ship!
Why would a ship be way out here?
What is it?
Lord Yupa!
It's a ship!
A ship!
It's coming closer!
It's huge!
It's a Tolmekian ship!
Somethings not right...
It's an emergency landing!
Help me up, Gol!
Princess, you mustn't!
It's too dangerous!
I'll just guide them to the shore!
It's coming about!
Off you go!
Teto!
How dare they!
They must have landed in the forest
and enraged some insects!
Turn away!
You'll crash!
Turn your ship!
Turn!
It crashed!
The Princess!
Get to the cliffs!
Let's go!
Everyone to the rescue!
Even the boys!
It's that girl, she's alive!
Where am I...
The Valley of the Wind.
Save your strength.
My name is...
Lastel of Pejite.
My cargo...
Burn the cargo...
The cargo...
Please, burn it.
It must be destroyed...
Your cargo, I understand.
Don't worry, it's all in flames.
Thank the heavens...
Princess!
That's... The Princess of Pejite!
What's she doing on a Tolmekian ship?
An insect!
An Ushiabu is alive!
Oh, no, it's calling its friends!
It can't fly!
Bring guns!
No! If you shoot,
it'll call more to its aid!
I'll kill it now with one shot!
Guns won't kill an Ushiabu!
Then what do we do!?
Wait!
Mito, bring me my glider!
Yes, Princess!
Return to the forest.
You're strong, you can fly.
That's a good boy.
Princess!
Thanks!
Thank God!
No telling how we'd suffer for
even a single insects death!
An Ohm...
I found one!
Over here!
Right here!
So those spores were
stuck to that ship.
Thank goodness they haven't
released any toxins yet.
Keep working hard!
I know, we can't miss
even a single one.
What on earth is this thing?
The fire didn't destroy it.
Leave this mystery
for later, folks.
Go and help burn the spores,
and be sure to get them all!
Be careful, now.
Why would she bring this
bundle of trouble here?
Mito, look here...
It's pulsing, beating like a heart!
Almost like it's alive.
Lord Yupa, what is this?
On my journey
I heard ominous rumors
of a monster from the
old world that had slept
beneath Pejite, had been unearthed.
A monster from the old world?
Giant Warriors...
The Giant Warriors!
They say they were destroyed
in the Seven Days of Fire!
This... can't be!
The Giant Warriors were all
said to have turned to stone,
But a single one slept in
the earth for 1,000 years.
In... in a way, the thing
looks almost human.
Tolmekia is a savage military state,
far to our west.
And remember the Pejite
captive who perished...
Keep up the good work
What's that on the horizon?
Tolmekian ships!
Everyone head to the castle!
To the castle!
Hurry!
Gather in the castle!
The castle!
Father!
Obaba, you should hide yourself!
I think I'll stay right where I am,
my King.
Princess!
How could you!
Nausicaa...
Stay where you are!
Move, and this sword
carved of insect shell
will pierce your ceramic armor
with ease!
That's Lord Yupa...
The great swordsman...
I ask you Tolmekian warriors
to stop this violence.
Just last night, these villagers toiled
desperately to save one of your ships.
And we have just now gently
laid your dead to rest.
Is this how you Tolmekians treat
such a nation? However weak?
If you would make war,
you must have reasons!
And you should first send a messenger
to declare them.
Nausicaa...
Be calm, Nausicaa.
If you fight now,
they will slaughter the villagers.
We must survive,
and wait for our chance.
You...
Little wench!
Put it down, Kurotowa!
But...
Look at this mess!
She's slaughtered them all.
Your rebuke stings.
Are you Yupamiralda,
the greatest swordsman of this region?
We have not come for slaughter.
We wish simply to talk.
Lay down your sword.
The Princess!
Princess!
Listen well!
Her Highness Kushana, Division
Commander of the Tolmekian
Frontier Forces will speak.
We have come to unify
the frontier nations,
and build peace throughout region.
You live on the brink of extinction,
beside the Sea of Decay.
Accept our rule,
and join our enterprise,
And we shall burn away the
Sea of Decay and resurrect the earth!
Burn away the Sea of Decay?
Is that even possible?
We have revived the
miraculous skills and power
that once allowed humans
to rule this earth!
For those who submit to us,
I promise a life free from fear of
the toxins and insects of that swamp!
Wait!
You must not harm the Sea of Decay!
What's that, you old hag?
Take her away!
Let her speak...
In the 1,000 years
of the Sea of Decay,
countless times have humans
sought to burn it away.
Yet... each time herds
of Ohms, blind with rage,
have swarmed the earth,
like a tidal wave.
Destroying nations,
swallowing cities.
The Ohms' rage would not quiet
until they starved to death.
In time, the spores
took root in the Ohms' rotting flesh,
.and engulfed our vast
earth in this Sea of Decay.
You must not touch
the Sea of Decay!
Enough!
No more of your ravings!
Ah! What will you do?
Kill me, too?
Silence!
Kill me if you will!
Easy work to murder
an old blind woman,
Just as you murdered our King Jihl!
What! Not Jihl!
How cruel!
He was helpless!
Shut them up!
Show no mercy to impudence!
Wait, everyone!
Please listen to me!
I don't want anymore people to die..
Please...
Princess...
You, too, Obaba.
We must submit to these people,
for the time being.
Step on it!
Hurry up!
It really is a lovely valley...
I see nothing of value here.
We have orders to send the
Giant Warrior back at once.
An order we can't possibly fulfill!
Even our biggest ship would
collapse from its weight
But you can't be serious
about building a nation here...
And what if I am?
You expect me to hand over that
monster as some war toy to those fools?
You have a point.
I am but a simple soldier.
Such a decision is beyond my position.
You're a sly fox is what you are.
While I'm in Pejite, your priority
is to revive that Giant Warrior.
Yes!
Can this gun ship fly?
Yes, we found it here in
good shape.
Now do as I have said,
I was not asking you.
But you highness, taking the
Princess to Pejite,
five hostages,
the gun ship and food...
You may choose the hostages.
Just prepare everything
for the morning.
Thanks for going as a hostage, Mito.
We're fine, but look...
They're taking everything in sight!
Don't worry, I will slip away
and return when I can.
We must prevent that
monster's resurrection while I'm gone!
Yes.
Nausicaa?
Teto, where has she gone too?
Nausicaa! What on earth is this?
These plants are gathered from
the Sea of Decay.
I've grown them
from spores I collected.
Don't worry. They're not toxic.
Not toxic?
The air here is pure indeed, but...
Why... with these deadly poisonous
plants blooming?
The castle windmill draws pure
water from deep within the earth.
The sand, too, comes from
the very bottom of the well.
With pure water and soil,
the plants from the Sea of Decay
are not poisonous.
The pollution lies in the earth itself.
Even the earth of our valley is
affected.
Why...
Who has made such a
terrible mess of the world?
Did you discover this all yourself?
Yes.
To cure my father's illness,
and that of many others.
But... It's too late now.
I'm closing it down.
I just shut off the water supply, and
they'll soon wither away and die.
Nausicaa...
My strength scares me, Yupa.
I don't know what my rage
will make me do.
I don't want to kill anyone!
Princess!
We gathered these for you Princess!
Chiko nuts.
They're for your journey
All of you...
There's so many!
You've worked so hard...
Thank you all so much.
They're very precious.
It's not fair, Princess!
Please don't go!
All aboard!
We're taking off!
There, now...
You mustn't cry.
Don't worry
I'll be home in no time.
Really?
Why, have I ever lied to you?
No
Right?
Yeah
Promise?
Yes
Go along now, it's dangerous here.
OK!
Remember your promise!
Take care of the Princess!
Aren't we in Pejite yet?
My back is killing me.
Boy oh boy, did the Princess
ever pick a bunch of losers.
Hey, isn't this strange?
Why do they fly so close together?
It's like they're afraid of an attack
or something...
The toxins swirl below the clouds...
Don't move!
A gun ship!
Were taking enemy fire!
They've hit ship number two!
What did I tell you!
Wow, that could have been us!
Defensive formation!
That's a Pejite gun ship!
Pejite!
Damn! They got ship
number three as well!
What's the Korvet doing?
Their ships just crumble apart...
Oh no, he's hit our tail!
The Barge tether snapped!
Hurry, Teto..
Oh, no! We're going down!
Princess!
Stop! Please! No more killing!
No more!
Princess...
Hurry, Mito!
Princess, we're doomed!
Maybe I can fly it.
Are you crazy?
Hurry, Mito!
What? Right!
Start the engine!
Blast open the door!
Come with us!
Hurry!
Get inside.
Mito, are you ready?
Ready or not!
Full throttle as soon as we take off!
Roger that!
Ready...
GO!
Put on your toxin masks!
Let's drop below the clouds
to find the Barge.
You're still warm...
Don't give up, Teto.
What is this place!
I've never seen such dense toxins!
Keep an eye on the right tail...
It's got to be nearby...
It's still aloft.
Hey! You're right!
There it is!
It's the Princess!
Princess!
Don't give up, everyone,
I'll throw you a rope!
Our tow hook is broken!
You can't hook us in mid-air!
I don't want to crash and
become insect food!
We'll leap to our deaths first!
Don't panic!
Just ditch your cargo!
Good bye, farewell!
This is the end!
Listen to me!
Toss your cargo!
Kill the rear engine.
What?
The engine noise is too loud.
Hurry!
Yes, Princess!
What?
Princess...
What are you...
Your mask, Princess!
You'll die!
Put your mask on!
I promise you'll be safe,
but you must trust me.
And dump your cargo!
We'll do what ever you say
Please! Just put your mask back on!
The Princess is smiling?
We're going to be OK
Hurry! Lose the cargo
Princess, we're in a nose-dive!
Re-start engines!
I accidentally inhaled
some of the poisons...
Hurry, hurry
Princess!
Is everyone safe?
Don't move!
Traitor!
Thank you for saving me.
Why did you save her, Princess?
You're a fool, princess.
You thought I'd grovel
in gratitude?
You know nothing of the Sea of Decay.
It isn't like the human world.
There's no telling what terrors
a single gunshot will bring.
That battle hurled
ships into this forest,
The insects are furious right now.
Look up...
The Yamma are sentries,
They'll quickly bring other insects
to launch an attack.
We must escape now!
Throw me your extra rope.
Mito, fix the hook.
Don't move!
I give the orders around here!
What are you so afraid of?
You're just like
a lost fox-squirrel
How dare you!
Don't be afraid,
We just want you to go back
to your own country.
You...
They're here!
Quiet! We must not anger them
This is an Ohm's nest!
We're surrounded...
They're checking if we can
be trusted...
Forgive us. Ohm,
for disturbing your nest.
Please understand,
we're not your enemies
Princess!
He's still alive?
Wait, Ohm!
What's happening?
Their eyes have turned blood-red!
What will you do with the glider?
When the waters quiet again,
take off and wait for me on the surface.
If I'm not back in one hour,
return to the Valley.
But...
Princess!
She's gone...
Hand it over!
All right, everyone
We'll do as the Princess said.
Princess...
Damn!
Who are you?
You think only of killing,
My flares and charms
are of no use now.
It's quicksand!
Damn!
It's been two hours already.
More and more insects
keep appearing...
Princess!
Nausicaa
Come here
Father...
Mother's here, too.
No, I don't want to go!
Stay away!
There's nothing here.
I said, there's nothing!
No, don't come out.
It's a baby Ohm.
She's being used by the insects!
Give it to me, Nausicaa
No! It's not doing anything bad!
Insects and humans cannot
live in the same world, child.
Please, don't kill it!
Please!
Teto...
What a strange place
Hey!
I finally found it
How are you feeling?
Where are we?
First, let me thank you.
I'm Asbel of Pejite
Thank you for saving me
I'm Nausicaa of
the Valley of the Wind.
Where are we?
It's no wonder you're surprised,
We're beneath the Sea of Decay.
Beneath the Sea of Decay?
Look, we fell from up there.
Along with the sand.
We're not wearing masks!
That's right.
The air here is pure.
Couldn't believe it myself,
finding this place
under the Sea of Decay.
What is it?
Nausicaa, don't wander off too far!
What a wonderful tree
Even though it's dead,
water still flows through it
Just like the sand
at the bottom of our well
Grains of petrified wood
sifting down from above
Nausicaa...
Are you crying?
Yes, I'm just so happy
Lastel was my twin sister.
I should have been with her..
I'm sorry I didn't tell you sooner.
No.
I'm sorry.
I nearly killed the person
who eased my sisters pain.
So, it's in the Valley of the Wind.
This nut tastes awful!
It's a chiko nut.
They're really good for you.
It doesn't taste great,
but I could eat a whole boot-full!
Why the Sea of Decay was born...?
You think the strangest thoughts.
The trees of the Sea of Decay
grew to cleanse
a world polluted by humans.
They absorb toxins from the earth,
generate pure crystals,
die and turn to sand.
That's what created
these underground caverns...
The insects protect this forest
because its saving the earth.
In that case, we're doomed.
We can't possibly survive,
living in terror of toxins and
insects for thousands of years!
At least we can find a way
to keep it from spreading.
You sound just like Kushana
No! We don't plan to use
the Giant Warriors!
You'll see when you
meet my friends tomorrow.
Let's go to sleep,
We have far to go tomorrow.
All's well, sir.
Everything on schedule?
The torso is solidifying well, sir.
You're one cute monster,
you know that?
Makes a poor soldier think
of dusting off old ambitions.
It's grinning...
You should have slept beneath
the earth till the end of time.
Counselor!
Her Highness' planes were
attacked by Pejite survivors.
All crashed, except the Korvet.
What about Her Highness?
Her ship exploded in flight, sir.
Counselor?
- The villagers don't know yet?
- No.
I see... we'll move ahead
as scheduled.
You stay here and keep working.
Either fortune's finally smiling
on this lowly soldier
Or it's a trap set to destroy me.
Mito and the others have returned,
They're waiting for you at Acid Lake,
Lord Yupa.
In shame we return without
the princess...
No, no, I'm pleased you're safe.
Releasing me?
You must drown the Giant Warrior
deep in Acid Lake,
and return to your own country.
Few of your soldiers remain here.
We could easily force you out,
but why sacrifice more people?
Fire and water are powerless against it,
and it's only a matter of time
before it starts to walk.
Don't you see?
It's far too late to turn back...
My orders to invade Pejite
were motivated by fear
that another country had
harnessed its strength.
Once its presence here is known,
the great powers will
send their armies.
You have but one choice left.
Revive the Giant Warrior,
defy both great powers,
and learn to live with that thing.
Look...
An insect did that?
Yes, and whoever becomes my husband
will see much worse than that!
Burn the Sea of Decay,
kill the insects,
and restore the human world!
Why do you hesitate!
Steal the Giant from us, just as
we stole it from Pejite.
We shall not give
the Giant Warrior life!
Emergency!
What's the password?
I'm in a hurry!
Wind...
Valley!
OK
Some spores survived!
What!?
They're spreading toxins all over,
and the Valley's going crazy!
Hand 'em over!
Hurry up!
Hurry, or the Valley's doomed!
We need our tools back!
The tools that burn spores
can also be used as weapons.
We have no choice but to
release everything but their guns
The Korvet is taking off
Get through this time,
And summon all our troops
from Pejite to this valley
Good grief, what a mess
this has become.
Hurry!
Find the Princess
Look after the valley,
and be careful until we return.
Lets get back to the valley
It's no use! The spores
are already spreading!
And on this side, too!
Move!
What are you doing!
Oh, no. Here too...
Obaba, what shall we do?
We've got no choice but to burn it
This forest is doomed.
If we hesitate, the Sea of Decay
will consume our Valley!
Isn't there anything to be done?
This forest has guarded
this Valley for three centuries!
Damn! If only those Tolmekians
had never come...
This is getting out of hand.
Let's go help them.
Different?
I think it looks the same as ever.
The insects have all gone.
Why is my heart pounding so hard?
We're almost there!
My people are just
over that mountain
Pejite looks strange
What is that haze?
Asbel, your mask!
Insects! All dead!
Head for Pejite
Be careful, the Tolmekian
army must be there
Even an Ohm...
It attacked the Great Dome.
Pejite's finished...
I knew they wiped out the Tolmekians,
but this is...
Wiped out?
What do you mean, Asbel?
It's a Brig!
My friends' ship!
They're landing, let's go!
Asbel!
You're alive!
What's happened here?
We could never rebuild it.
You've seen the city.
Don't worry, if the Sea of Decay
swallows it, we'll burn it away.
But how? The
Giant Warrior isn't here.
I know, it's in the Valley of the Wind.
How did you...
We haven't exactly been idle,
We've already launched our
second phase attack
We'll wipe out the Tolmekians
in the valley tonight!
What!?
What are you going to do?
Who's this, Asbel?
Nausicaa... from
the Valley of the Wind.
I owe her my life.
The Valley of the Wind...
Tell me, what will happen to
the Valley?
You must know, Asbel!
Tell me!
They'll provoke an insect attack.
So you made them
attack Pejite, too!
You're... horrible...
We simply have to recover the
Giant Warrior before they revive it!
We're doing it to save the world!
And in doing so you'll murder
everyone in the Valley!
Stop it! Call it off! Please!
It's too late...
Once they've started,
no one can stop them.
We've lost most of our
people to the Tolmekians,
this is the only choice
we have left.
Let go! Let me fly!
It's horrible now, yes, but the Giant
Warrior will purge the Sea of Decay,
and rebuild the human world!
Liar! You're just like the Tolmekians!
No! They want to use it for destruction!
You drink water from the wells, too!
Do you know what purifies that water?
The trees in the Sea of Decay
cleanse all the lakes
and rivers that
humans have polluted!
And you want to destroy that?
Why did you dig up
that Giant Warrior!
What choice did we have?
Subject ourselves to Tolmekian rule?
No, never!
Tell them, Asbel, how
the Sea of Decay came to be!
How the insects protect this world!
Please, Asbel!
Tell them!
What are you doing!
Don't move!
Release her!
Calm down, Asbel.
I'm serious.
Let her go.
Nausicaa, go and warn the Valley!
Asbel!
Let me go!
Fools!
There's no stopping
the fighting once it starts!
But he warned us to be careful...
Quit dawdling and use the tanks
to rescue our men!
Counselor!
They've killed our last man!
Are they coming our way?
I don't know.
The whole village is gathering!
Burn down a forest and the whole
village goes berserk!
Just as it was with Pejite.
They've captured our tank!
Hurry! Get it moving!
Don't panic!
Incoming fire!
Forward!
Hurry up!
Maybe it's this one?
It's moving!
Which way?
Forward, move forward!
I know that!
Damn! Mobilize all the tanks!
She survived...
So much for my dreams.
Your Highness!
We'll hold 'em off here!
Lead everyone to safety
by the Acid Lake!
All right.
It's just until the Princess
returns with the gun ship.
Hurry everyone!
Stop gawking and help me.
My back hurts.
The tanks are coming!
Hurry!
I know what to do!
Are you sure?
Yes sir, it's a Pejite Brig!
I saw it peeking through the clouds.
OK!
Watch out, she's a wild one.
Quickly!
Nausicaa, we're here to help
you escape.
Go and warn your Valley!
Your glider may get you
there in time.
It's waiting for you.
Asbel told me everything.
I'll take your place.
Put this on.
You're...
Lastel's mother.
Thank you.
I'm so very sorry
Everything my people have done is wrong!
Hurry!
What about her?
She'll be all right, don't worry.
Be careful
We've treated you so badly.
Could you ever forgive us?
Over here, Nausicaa!
Hurry!
Thank you, everyone!
Sorry it took so long...
Can you launch from here?
I can try
A Korvet!
Take cover in the clouds!
Stop firing!
Idiots! Nothing but wind
and lightning in there.
It's useless! I've lost all control!
The ship is breaking apart!
We have to leave
the clouds and fight!
They were expecting us...
What are they up to?
They're forcing us into the clouds
so they can board us!
Here they come!
This is your last chance!
No, I'll stay with you.
I can't abandon all those people
and the girl who took my place.
Only you can save your people!
Please, go, for our sakes!
The ship is ours.
Take no prisoners. Destroy them all.
Nausicaa! Go now!
Asbel!
Princess!
Mito!
Mito! Lord Yupa!
Princess
Hurry, the Valley is in trouble!
I'll engage the hook now...
Lord Yupa, that red lever!
This is their last stronghold.
The door won't hold much longer.
Any time now...
Show them some Pejite pride.
What is that?
A bird?
A ship, a gun ship from the Valley!
What!
You...
That's Lord Yupa! Kill him,
and you'll be famous!
Surrender, your Korvet
won't be back for you.
This guy's tough!
Princess, you're crazy!
The engine'll blow!
C'mon, just make it to the Valley...
Go faster!
Dear God. God of the Wind
please protect my people.
They won't budge.
They're waiting for her return.
Return?
They believe that girl will
return with their gun ship.
A single gun ship isn't a threat.
Now is our chance to attack!
Do you know what that ship is?
It's from before
the Seven Days of Fire.
The one, they say,
that went as far as the stars...
It's too strong for our guns,
but we could burn it.
I too, wish to wait for the girl.
If she really does return from
deep in the Sea of Decay...
I'd like a chance
to really talk to her.
Made up your minds?
If you'll aid our attack,
I'll let you go free.
You want to end up like Pejite?
You're a Princess, too,
but you're nothing
like our Princess.
Look at my hands.
This is what caused King Jihl
so much pain.
In 6 more months
they will be like stone.
But our Princess said,
that she liked these hands.
That they were the beautiful hands
of a hard worker.
You want to live
with the Sea of Decay?
Even as it's toxins ravage your body?
You use fire.
We use it a bit, too.
But too much fire
and nothing will grow.
Fire can turn the forest
into ashes in a single day.
While water and wind can sustain
a forest for 1,000 years!
We enjoy the water and the wind.
The sight of our forest
will grieve the Princess dearly.
Counselor, we await your orders!
Shut up, you.
Yes sir!
Who knows what happened...
but she sure looks cute.
Ready your troops, Kurotowa!
Huh? You want to advance?
Feed the soldiers.
We attack in 1 hour.
Food, huh?
Finally, a real meal.
Someone's coming!
It's Gol and the others!
What is it?
There's no wind...
No wind?
You're right, the wind has stopped!
Obaba, what is it?
Obaba!
Someone...
Someone take me outside...
The wind's never stopped
like this before!
Obaba, my ears hurt.
The air...
The very air is thick with rage...
We're close!
We're clear of the Sea of Decay!
Three minutes to Acid Lake!
Idle the engines, and
drop beneath the clouds.
What's that glow?
Ohms!
The Sea of Decay is spreading!
They're headed for the Valley!
How did they stampede the Ohms...
Someone's baiting them...
Mito! Turn towards Sirius
Yes!
It's there!
Mito, a flare!
Ready
Fire!
What is that?
How cruel...
They're baiting them
with a tortured baby Ohm!
I'll shoot 'em down!
No, Mito!
Don't shoot!
Why not! Why shouldn't I?
Kill the baby,
and the stampede will never end!
What can we do!
They'll destroy the Valley!
Calm down, Mito.
We've got to return their baby to them.
At least try.
What are you doing, Princess!
You go ahead and warn them!
Princess!
You're not even armed!
That's not one of our flares...
How far?
20 leagues.
The other side of the lake.
Is it a gun ship?
Probably.
That's a distress signal.
It's definitely the gun ship.
Well, it's been an hour. Let's go.
Why not wait?
The bloodshed is inevitable.
Infantry advance!
You would be safer inside.
I'm fine here.
The gun ship!
Fire!
Hold your fire!
Stop it! Stop!
Princess!
Stand-by
Don't fire
Your Highness
Where's the girl?!
The Princess!
She's not here.
The Ohm, a stampede!
It's coming this way!
What!
The Ohm!
The Princess stayed behind
to stop them.
This is no time for battle!
Everyone run, find the
highest place you can! Now!
Obaba, I see a red glow!
It's spreading.
It's coming this way!
You hold on tight,
there's no stopping them now.
Don't panic!
There's still time!
If I have to die,
I want to die in the Valley.
No! You mustn't give up,
not while the Princess still has faith!
Listen, hold them off
as long as you can.
I'll return soon with
the Giant Warrior!
Your Highness, not that...
It's not even close to ready yet!
If not now, when!
Go!
Don't shoot! Listen to me!
Damn! She flies like a bird!
She's not an enemy...
I think she wants to say something.
Anyone who interferes is an enemy.
We'd better drop the bait in
the Valley soon, or die ourselves.
Here she comes!
Let her come in close, then fire!
Now! Fire!
No!
That's Lastel!
Move!
Ohm...
Don't be angry.
Don't be frightened.
I'm not your foe
I'm sorry they hurt you...
I'm sorry.
I can't ask your forgiveness.
It's too cruel!
Don't move!
You'll bleed to death!
Be good, little one, just keep still!
They've found us!
They're coming!
Stop! Not with those wounds!
The lake is acid...
You...
Good baby.
I'm fine.
They're coming for you now.
They're turning away!
Ohm! Don't!
The Valley's that way!
They've forgotten us in their rage...
If I don't calm them, the Valley...
Fools! Drawing them
with their own fire!
We're safe...
We'd better get away from here.
Check the engine!
No. No!
We can discuss this.
You will take us to them.
And we will give their baby back.
What's the point? It's too late now.
They'll never stop!
Drop us in front of them, then.
Take us!
But you'll die, too!
Obaba, will we all die?
If that is to be our fate,
then we must accept it.
They don't even waver!
Lets retreat!
Idiot! There's nowhere to go.
Don't retreat!
Hold your ground!
For Her Highness!
Highness...
Your Highness!
Get them!
They've actually revived it...
It's falling apart.
It's much too soon.
Burn them!
What's wrong?
Are you not descended from
Earth's most evil tribe?
Incredible...
No wonder the world caught fire!
Your Highness Kushana, hurray!
Destroy them!
What's wrong with you?
Hurry up and fire!
We're done for!
The Giant Warrior is dead.
It's for the best.
The Ohm's rage is
the fury of the Earth itself.
There's no reason to live
if our lives depend on a monster.
Princess!
The Princess!
Not there
It's madness
Oh, Princess!
The Ohms are changing color!
Their rage has vanished!
They stopped.
The Ohms stopped everyone!
Princess!
The Princess is dead.
She calmed them with her own life.
She has saved our Valley.
Look...
What is that light?
Teto...
Wonderful...
Thank you. Ohm
Thank you
It's a miracle!
A miracle!
Such friendship, and sympathy!
The Ohms have truly
opened their hearts.
Children, watch well and tell me
what I cannot see.
The Princess is wearing
strange blue clothes...
It's like she's walking
through golden fields.
Clothed in blue robes
descending onto a golden field
Obaba...
The ancient legend was true!
Look!
The glider!
The wind!
The wind has returned!
Featured Voices
NAUSICAÄ
Alison Lohman  ·  Sumi Shimamoto
LORD YUPA
Patrick Stewart  ·  Gorô Naya
KUSHANA
Uma Thurman  ·  Yoshiko Sakakibara
ASBEL
Shia LaBeouf  ·  Yôji Matsuda
MITO
Edward James Olmos  ·  Ichirô Nagai
OBABA
Tress MacNeille  ·  Hisako Kyôda
GOL
Frank Welker  ·  Kôhei Miyauchi
MAYOR of PEJITE
Mark Hamill  ·  Mugihito
KUROTOWA
Chris Sarandon  ·  Iemasa Kayumi
MUZO
James Arnold Taylor  ·  Mahito Tsujimura
GIKKURI
Jeff Bennett  ·  Jôji Yanami
Additional Voices
Mark Silverman · Emily Bauer · Jodi Benson · Ashley Rose
Minoru Yada · Mîna Tominaga · Akiko Tsuboi · Takako Ôta
And
Tony Jay as the Narrator
English translation by
Linda Hoaglund · Judith Aley · Nao Amisaki · Steve Alpert
Production
Top Craft
The End
www.moviesubtitles.org