Once upon a time, in a faraway land,
a young prince lived
in a shining castle.
Although he had everything
his heart desired,
the prince was spoiled,
selfish and unkind.
But then, one winter's night,
an old beggar woman came
to the castle
and offered him a single rose
in return for shelter from the bitter cold.
Repulsed by her haggard appearance,
the prince sneered at the gift
and turned the old woman away.
But she warned him
not to be deceived by appearances,
for beauty is found within.
And when he dismissed her again,
the old woman's ugliness melted away
to reveal a beautiful enchantress.
The prince tried to apologize,
but it was too late,
for she had seen
that there was no love in his heart.
And as punishment,
she transformed him
into a hideous beast
and placed a powerful spell
on the castle and all who lived there.
Ashamed of his monstrous form,
the Beast concealed himself
inside his castle
with a magic mirror as his only window
to the outside world.
The rose she had offered
was truly an enchanted rose,
which would bloom until his 21st year.
If he could learn to love another
and earn her love in return
by the time the last petal fell,
then the spell would be broken.
If not, he would be doomed
to remain a beast for all time.
As the years passed,
he fell into despair and lost all hope,
for who could ever learn
to love a beast?
Little town, it's a quiet village
Every day like the one before
Little town, full of little people
Waking up to say...
There goes the baker
with his tray, like always
The same old bread and rolls to sell
Every morning just the same
Since the morning that we came
To this poor provincial town
- Good morning, Belle.
- Morning, monsieur.
- Where you off to?
- The bookshop.
I just finished the most wonderful story
-about a beanstalk and an ogre and...
- That's nice.
Marie, the baguettes! Hurry up!
Look, there she goes
The girl is strange, no question
Dazed and distracted, can't you tell?
Never part of any crowd
'Cause her head's up on some cloud
No denying she's a funny girl
that Belle
- Bonjour
- Good day
How is your family?
- Bonjour
- Good day
How is your wife?
I need six eggs
That's too expensive
There must be more
than this provincial life
- Belle.
- Good morning.
I've come to return the book I borrowed.
Finished already?
I couldn't put it down.
Have you got anything new?
Not since yesterday.
That's all right. I'll borrow this one.
That one? But you've read it twice.
Well, it's my favorite.
Far-off places, daring sword fights,
magic spells, a prince in disguise.
If you like it all that much, it's yours.
- But, sir...
- I insist.
Well, thank you. Thank you very much.
Look, there she goes
That girl is so peculiar
I wonder if she's feeling well
With a dreamy, far-off look
And her nose stuck in a book
What a puzzle to the rest of us is Belle
Isn't this amazing?
It's my favorite part
Because you'll see
Here's where she meets
Prince Charming
But she won't discover that it's him
Till chapter three
Hey, hey! Hey, hey, hey!
Now it's no wonder
that her name means beauty
Her looks have got no parallel
But behind that fair facade
I'm afraid she's rather odd
Very different from the rest of us
She's nothing like the rest of us
Yes, different from the rest of us
is Belle
Wow! You didn't miss a shot, Gaston.
You're the greatest hunter
in the whole world!
- I know.
- No beast alive
stands a chance against you.
- And no girl, for that matter.
- It's true, LeFou.
And I've got my sights set on that one.
- The inventor's daughter?
- She's the one.
- The lucky girl I'm going to marry.
- But she...
- The most beautiful girl in town.
- I know, but...
That makes her the best.
- And don't I deserve the best?
- Well, of course. I mean, you do.
Right from the moment
when I met her, saw her
I said she's gorgeous, and I fell
Here in town there's only she
Who is beautiful as me
So I'm making plans
to woo and marry Belle
Look, there he goes
Isn't he dreamy?
Monsieur Gaston
Oh, he's so cute
Be still, my heart
I'm hardly breathing
He's such a tall, dark, strong
and handsome brute
- Bonjour
- Good day
- You call this bacon?
- What lovely grapes
- Some cheese
- Ten yards
- Excuse me
- I'll get the knife
- Please let me through
- This bread, it's stale
- Those fish, they smell
- Madame's mistaken
There must be more
than this provincial life
Just watch, I'm going
to make Belle my wife
Look, there she goes
a girl who's strange but special
A most peculiar mademoiselle
It's a pity and a sin
She doesn't quite fit in
'Cause she really is a funny girl
A beauty but a funny girl
She really is a funny girl
That Belle
- Hello, Belle.
- Bonjour, Gaston.
Gaston, may I have my book, please?
How can you read this?
There's no pictures.
Well, some people
use their imagination.
Belle, it's about time you got
your head out of those books
and paid attention
to more important things.
Like me.
The whole town's talking about it.
It's not right for a woman to read.
Soon she starts getting ideas
and thinking.
Gaston, you are positively primeval.
Why, thank you, Belle.
What do you say you and me
take a walk over to the tavern
-and take a look at my trophies?
- Maybe some other time.
- What's wrong with her?
- She's crazy.
He's gorgeous.
Please, Gaston, I can't.
I have to get home to help my father.
Good bye.
That crazy old loon.
He needs all the help he can get.
Don't talk about my father that way.
Yeah! Don't talk
about her father that way.
My father is not crazy. He's a genius.
- Papa?
- How on earth did that happen?
- Doggone it!
- Are you all right, Papa?
I'm... I'm about ready
to give up on this hunk of junk.
- You always say that.
- I mean it this time!
I'll never get this
boneheaded contraption to work!
Yes, you will. And you'll win first prize
at the fair tomorrow.
And become a world-famous inventor.
You really believe that?
I always have.
Well, what are we waiting for?
I'll have this thing fixed in no time.
Hand me that...
The dog-legged clincher there.
So, did you have a good time
in town today?
I got a new book.
Papa, do you think I'm odd?
My daughter? Odd?
Where would you get an idea like that?
I don't know.
It's just that I'm not sure I fit in here.
There's no one I can really talk to.
What about that Gaston?
He's a handsome fella.
He's handsome, all right,
and rude and conceited and...
Papa, he's not for me.
Well, don't you worry.
'Cause this invention's gonna be
the start of a new life for us.
I think that's done it.
Now, let's give it a try.
- It works!
- It does?
- It does!
- You did it.
You really did it!
Hitch up Philippe, girl. I'm off to the fair!
Goodbye, Papa. Good luck.
Goodbye, Belle.
Take care while I'm gone.
We should be there by now.
Maybe we missed a turn.
I guess I should've taken...
Wait a minute.
No. Let's go this way.
Come on, Philippe, it's a shortcut.
We'll be there in no time.
This can't be right.
Where have you taken us, Philippe?
We better turn around.
Whoa. Whoa, boy.
Whoa, now, whoa, Philippe.
Look out! No!
Whoa!
Whoa, boy!
Back up, back up, back up!
Good boy. Good boy.
That's good, that's... Back up!
Steady, steady, now. Steady.
Steady. No, Philippe!
Philippe?
Help! ls... ls someone there?
Help!
Hello?
Hello!
Poor fellow must have lost his way
in the woods.
Keep quiet. Maybe he'll go away.
Is someone there?
Not a word, Lumiere. Not one word.
I don't mean to intrude,
but I've lost my horse
and I need a place to stay for the night.
Cogsworth, have a heart.
Of course, monsieur,
you are welcome here.
Who said that?
Over here.
- Where?
- Hello.
Incredible!
Well, now you've done it, Lumiere.
Splendid. Just peachy.
- How is this accomplished?
- Put me down at once.
Stop that! Stop that, I say!
Sir, close that at once!
- Do you mind?
- I beg your pardon.
It's... It's just
that I've never seen a clock that
You are soaked to the bone, monsieur.
Come. Warm yourself by the fire.
- Thank you.
- No, no, no!
You know what the master will do
if he finds him here.
I demand that you stop right there.
No, no. Not the master's chair.
I'm not seeing this. I'm not seeing this.
Well, hello there, boy.
- What service.
- All right.
This has gone far enough.
I'm in charge here...
How would you like a nice spot of tea,
sir? It'll warm you up in no time.
No. No tea. No tea!
His mustache tickles, Mama.
Hello.
There's a stranger here.
Master, allow me to explain.
The gentleman was lost in the woods.
He was cold and wet, so...
Master, I'd like to take this moment
to say
I was against this from the start.
It was all his fault.
I tried to stop them.
Would they listen to me? No, no...
Who are you?
What are you doing here?
I... I... I was lost in the woods and...
You are not welcome here!
I... I'm... I'm sorry.
- What are you staring at?
- Nothing.
So, you've come to stare
at the Beast, have you?
Please, I meant no harm!
I just needed a place to stay.
- I'll give you a place to stay!
- No, no, please! No! No!
Oh, boy. Belle's gonna get
the surprise of her life, huh, Gaston?
Yep, this is her lucky day.
I'd like to thank you all
for coming to my wedding.
First, I better go in there
and propose to the girl.
And you, LeFou, now,
when Belle and I come out that door...
I know. I know. I strike up the band!
- Not yet.
- Sorry.
Gaston, what a pleasant surprise.
Isn't it, though?
I'm just full of surprises.
You know, Belle,
there's not a girl in town
who wouldn't love to be in your shoes.
This is the day...
This is the day your dreams come true.
What do you know
about my dreams, Gaston?
Plenty! Here. Picture this.
A rustic hunting lodge,
my latest kill roasting on the fire
and my little wife massaging my feet
while the little ones play on the floor
with the dogs.
- We'll have six or seven.
- Dogs?
No, Belle.
- Strapping boys like me.
- Imagine that.
Do you know who that little wife will be?
- Let me think.
- You, Belle.
Gaston, I'm... I'm speechless.
I really don't know what to say.
- Say you'll marry me.
- I'm very sorry, Gaston, but...
But I just don't deserve you!
So, how'd it go?
I'll have Belle for my wife.
Make no mistake about that.
Touchy.
Is he gone?
Can you imagine?
He asked me to marry him.
Me, the wife of that boorish, brainless...
Madame Gaston
Can't you just see it?
His little Wife
No, sir, not me, I guarantee it
I want much more
than this provincial life
I want adventure
in the great wide somewhere
I want it more than I can tell
And for once it might be grand
To have someone understand
I want so much more
than they've got planned
Philippe! What are you doing here?
Where's... Where's Papa?
Where is he, Philippe?
What happened?
We have to find him.
You have to take me to him.
What is this place?
Philippe, please, steady.
Steady.
Papa!
Couldn't keep quiet, could we?
Just had to invite him to stay,
didn't we?
Serve him tea, sit in the master's chair.
Pet the pooch.
I was trying to be hospitable.
Hello?
Is anyone here?
Papa? Papa?
Are you here?
Mama, there's a girl in the castle.
Now, Chip, I'll not have you
making up such wild stories.
Really, Mama. I saw her.
- Not another word. Into the tub.
- But... What?
A girl. I saw a girl in the castle.
See, I told you.
Irresponsible, devil-may-care,
waxy-eared, slack-jawed...
Papa?
Did you see that?
- It's a girl!
- I know it's a girl.
Don't you see? She's the one.
The girl we have been waiting for.
- She has come to break the spell.
- Wait a minute. Wait a minute.
Papa?
Hello? ls someone here?
Wait! I'm looking for my father. I...
That's funny.
I'm sure there was someone.
Is anyone here?
- Belle?
- Papa!
How did you find me?
Your hands are like ice.
We have to get you out of there.
Belle, I want you to leave this place.
Who's done this to you?
No time to explain. You must go. Now!
- I won't leave you.
- What are you doing here?
Run, Belle!
- Who's there? Who are you?
- The master of this castle.
I've come for my father.
Please let him out.
Can't you see he's sick?
Then he shouldn't
have trespassed here!
But he could die.
Please, I'll do anything.
There's nothing you can do.
He's my prisoner.
There must be some way I can...
Wait!
- Take me instead.
- You?
You would take his place?
Belle, no!
You don't know what you're doing!
If I did, would you let him go?
Yes. But you must promise
to stay here forever.
Come into the light.
No, Belle! I won't let you do this!
- You have my word.
- Done.
No, Belle, listen to me.
I'm old. I've lived my life.
Wait.
- Belle!
- Wait.
No! Please spare my daughter. Please!
She's no longer your concern.
Take him to the village.
Let me out. Please let me out!
Let me out! Please! Please!
- Master?
- What?
Since the girl is going to be with us
for quite some time,
I was thinking that you might want
to offer her a more comfortable room.
Then again, maybe not.
You didn't even let me say goodbye.
I'll never see him again.
I didn't get to say goodbye.
I'll show you to your room.
My room? But I thought...
You wanna...
You wanna stay in the tower?
- No.
- Then follow me.
Say something to her.
I hope you like it here.
The castle is your home now,
so you can go anywhere you like,
except the west wing.
- What's in the west...
- It's forbidden!
Now, if you need anything,
my servants will attend you.
Dinner. Invite her to dinner.
You will join me for dinner.
That's not a request!
Who does she think she is?
That girl has tangled
with the wrong man.
- No one says no to Gaston.
- Darn right.
Dismissed. Rejected.
Publicly humiliated.
Why, it's more than I can bear.
- More beer?
- What for? Nothing helps.
- I'm disgraced.
- Who, you? Never.
Gaston, you've got
to pull yourself together.
Gosh, it disturbs me
to see you, Gaston
Looking so down in the dumps
Every guy here 'd
love to be you, Gaston
Even when taking your lumps
There's no man in town
as admired as you
You're everyone's favorite guy
Everyone's awed
and inspired by you
And it's not very hard
To see why
No one's slick as Gaston
No one's quick as Gaston
No one's neck's
as incredibly thick as Gaston
For there's no man in town
half as manly
Perfect, a pure paragon
You can ask any
Tom, Dick or Stanley
And they'll tell you
whose team they prefer to be on
No one's been like Gaston
A kingpin like Gaston
No one's got a swell cleft
in his chin like Gaston
As a specimen, yes, I'm intimidating
My, what a guy, that Gaston
Give five hurrahs
Give 12 hip-hips
Gaston is the best
and the rest is all drips
No one fights like Gaston
Douses lights like Gaston
In a wrestling match
nobody bites like Gaston
For there's no one
as burly and brawny
As you see, I've got biceps to spare
- Not a bit of him scraggly or scrawny
- That's right
And every last inch of me's
covered with hair
- No one hits like Gaston
- Matches wits like Gaston
In a spitting match
nobody spits like Gaston
I'm especially good at expectorating
Ten points for Gaston
When I was a lad
I ate four dozen eggs
Every morning to help me get large
And now that I'm grown
I eat five dozen eggs
So I'm roughly the size of a barge
No one shoots like Gaston
Makes those beauts like Gaston
Then goes tromping around
wearing boots like Gaston
I use antlers in all of my decorating
My, what a guy
Gaston
- Help! Someone help me!
- Maurice?
Please! Please, I need your help.
He's got her...
He's got her locked in the dungeon.
- Who?
- Belle. We must go.
Not... Not a minute to lose.
Whoa! Slow down, Maurice.
- Who's got Belle locked in a dungeon?
- A beast!
A horrible, monstrous beast!
- Is it a big beast?
- Huge.
- With a long, ugly snout?
- Hideously ugly.
- And sharp, cruel fangs?
- Yes, yes! Will you help me?
All right, old man. We'll help you out.
You will?
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Crazy old Maurice.
He's always good for a laugh.
Crazy old Maurice?
Crazy old Maurice.
LeFou, I'm afraid I've been thinking
A dangerous pastime
I know
But that wacky old coot
is Belle's father
And his sanity's only so-so
Now, the wheels in my head
have been turning
Since I looked at that loony old man
See, I promised myself
I'd be married to Belle
And right now, I'm evolving a plan
- If I...
- Yes?
- Then we...
- No, would she?
- Guess.
- Now I get it!
- Let's go!
No one plots like Gaston
Takes cheap shots like Gaston
Plans to persecute harmless crackpots
like Gaston
So, his marriage
we soon will be celebrating
My, what a guy
Gaston
Will no one help me?
- Who is it?
- Mrs. Potts, dear.
I thought you might like a spot of tea.
But you're... You're a...
- Careful.
- This is impossible.
I know it is, but here we are.
I told you she was pretty, Mama,
didn't I?
All right, Chip, now, that'll do.
Slowly now. Don't spill.
Thank you.
Wanna see me do a trick?
- Chip!
- Sorry
That was a very brave thing
you did, my dear.
We all think so.
But I've lost my father,
my dreams, everything.
Cheer up, child.
It'll turn out all right in the end.
You'll see.
Listen to me jabbering on
while there's a supper
to get on the table.
Chip?
Bye.
Well, now,
what shall we dress you in for dinner?
Let's see what I got in my drawers.
How embarrassing!
Here we are.
You'll look ravishing in this one.
That's very kind of you,
but I'm not going to dinner.
But you must.
Dinner is served.
What's taking so long?
I told her to come down.
- Why isn't she here yet?
- Try to be patient, sir.
The girl has lost her father
and her freedom all in one day.
Master, have you thought
that perhaps this girl could be the one
to break the spell?
Of course I have! I'm not a fool.
Good! So, you fall in love with her,
she falls in love with you, and poof!
The spell is broken.
We'll be human again by midnight.
It's not that easy, Lumiere.
These things take time.
But the rose has already begun to wilt.
It's no use.
She's so beautiful and I'm...
Well, look at me!
You must help her to see past all that.
I don't know how.
Well, you can start
by making yourself more presentable.
Straighten up.
Try to act like a gentleman.
Yes. When she comes in,
give her a dashing, debonair smile.
Come, come, show me the smile.
- But don't frighten the poor girl.
- Impress her with your rapier wit.
But be gentle.
- Shower her with compliments.
- But be sincere.
And above all,
-you must control your temper!
- You must control your temper!
Here she is!
Good evening.
- Well, where is she?
- Who?
The girl, yes. The girl.
Well, actually, she's in the process of...
Circumstances being what they are...
She's not coming.
What?
Oh, dear. Your Grace! Your Eminence!
Let's not be hasty!
I thought I told you
to come down to dinner!
I'm not hungry.
You'll come out or I'll... I'll...
I'll break down the door!
Master, I could be wrong,
but that may not be the best way
to win the girl's affections.
Please attempt to be a gentleman.
But she is being so difficult.
Gently, gently.
- Will you come down to dinner?
- No!
Suave, genteel.
It would give me great pleasure
if you would join me for dinner.
And we say "please."
- Please.
- No, thank you.
- You can't stay in there forever!
- Yes, I can.
Fine! Then go ahead and starve!
If she doesn't eat with me,
then she doesn't eat at all!
Oh, dear.
That didn't go very well at all, did it?
Lumiere, stand watch at the door
and inform me at once
if there is the slightest change.
You can count on me, mon capitaine.
Well, we might as well go downstairs
and start cleaning up.
I ask nicely, but she refuses.
What does she want me to do, beg?
Show me the girl.
But the master's really not so bad,
once you get to know him.
Why don't you give him a chance?
I don't want to get to know him.
I don't want to have anything
to do with him.
I'm just fooling myself.
She'll never see me as anything
but a monster.
It's hopeless.
- Oh, no.
- Oh, yes.
- Oh, yes, yes, yes.
I've been burned by you before.
Zut alors! She has emerged!
Come on, Chip. Into the cupboard
with your brothers and sisters.
But I'm not sleepy.
- Yes, you are.
- No, I'm not.
I work and I slave all day long,
and for what?
A culinary masterpiece gone to waste!
Stop your grousing.
It's been a long night for all of us.
Well, if you ask me,
she was just being stubborn.
After all, he did say "please."
But if the master doesn't learn
to control that temper,
-he'll never break the...
- Splendid to see you
out and about, mademoiselle.
I am Cogsworth, head of the household.
- This is Lumiere.
- Enchanté, chérie.
If there's, stop that,
anything we, please,
can do to make your stay
more comfortable...
- I am a little hungry.
- You are?
Hear that? She's hungry.
Stoke the fire.
Break out the silver. Wake the china.
Remember what the master said.
Pish tosh. I'm not about
to let the poor child go hungry.
All right, fine. Glass of water,
crust of bread and then...
Cogsworth, I am surprised at you.
She's not a prisoner. She's our guest.
We must make her feel welcome here.
Right this way, mademoiselle.
Well, keep it down.
If the master finds out about this,
it will be our necks.
Of course, of course.
But what is dinner
without a little music?
Music?
It is with deepest pride
and greatest pleasure
that we welcome you tonight.
And now, we invite you to relax.
Let us pull up a chair,
as the dining room proudly presents
your dinner.
Be our guest, be our guest
Put our service to the test
Tie your napkin
'round your neck, chérie
And we provide the rest
Soup du jour, hot hors d'oeuvres
Why, we only live to serve
Try the gray stuff, it's delicious
Don't believe me?
Ask the dishes
They can sing, they can dance
After all, miss, this is France
And a dinner here
is never second best
Go on, unfold your menu
Take a glance
and then you'll be our guest
Oui, our guest
Be our guest
Beef ragout, cheese souffle
Pie and pudding, en flambé
We'll prepare and serve with flair
A culinary cabaret
You're alone and you're scared
But the banquet's all prepared
No one's gloomy or complaining
While the flatware's entertaining
We tell jokes, I do tricks
With my fellow candlesticks
Und it's all in perfect taste
That you can bet
Come on and lift your glass
You've won your own free pass
To be our guest
If you're stressed
it's fine dining we suggest
Be our guest, be our guest
Be our guest
Life is so unnerving
For a servant who's not serving
He's not whole
without a soul to wait upon
Get off!
Those good old days
When we were useful
Suddenly, those good old days
are gone
Ten years we've been rusting
Needing so much more than dusting
Needing exercise
A chance to use our skills
Most days
we just lay around the castle
Flabby, fat and lazy
You walked in and oops-a-daisy
It's a guest, it's a guest
Sakes alive, well, I'll be blessed
Wine's been poured
and thank the Lord
I've had the napkins freshly pressed
With dessert, she'll want tea
And, my dear, that's fine with me
While the cups do their soft-shoeing
I'll be bubbling, I'll be brewing
I'll get warm, piping hot
Heaven sakes, is that a spot?
Clean it up
We want the company impressed
We've got a lot to do
Is it one lump or two?
For you, our guest
- She's our guest
Be our guest
Be our guest, be our guest
Our command is your request
Let's go, people. Fun's over.
Over here. Line up.
It's 10 years
since we've had anybody here
And we 're obsessed
With your meal, with your ease
Yes, indeed, we aim to please
While the candlelight's still glowing
Let us help you, we'll keep going
Course by course
One by one
Till you shout, "Enough, I'm done!”
Then we'll sing you off to sleep
as you digest
Tonight, you'll prop your feet up
But for now, let's eat up
Be our guest
Please be our
Guest
- Bravo! That was wonderful.
- Thank you.
Thank you, mademoiselle.
Good show, wasn't it? Everyone!
My goodness, look at the time.
Now it's off to bed, off to bed.
I couldn't possibly go to bed now.
It's my first time in an enchanted castle.
Enchanted!
Who said anything
about the castle being enchanted?
It was you, wasn't it?
I figured it out for myself.
I'd like to look around, if that's all right.
- Would you like a tour?
- Wait a second. Wait a second.
I'm not sure that's such a good idea.
We can't let her go poking around
in certain places,
if you know what I mean.
Perhaps you'd like to take me.
I'm sure you know everything there is
to know about the castle.
Well. Actually, I...
Yes, I do.
As you can see,
the pseudo-facade was stripped away
to reveal the minimalist Rococo design.
Note the unusual
inverted vaulted ceilings.
This is yet another example
of the late-neoclassic Baroque period.
And, as I always say,
if it's not Baroque, don't fix it.
Where was I?
As you were!
Now, then, if I may draw your attention
to the flying buttresses above the...
Mademoiselle?
- What's up there?
- Where? There? Nothing.
Absolutely nothing of interest at all
in the west wing.
Dusty, dull, very boring.
So, that's the west wing!
Nice going.
I wonder what he's hiding up there.
- Hiding? The master is hiding nothing.
- Then it wouldn't be forbidden.
Perhaps mademoiselle would like
to see something else?
We have exquisite tapestries
dating all the way back to...
- Maybe later.
- The gardens.
Or... Or the... The library, perhaps?
You have a library?
- Yes. Indeed.
- With books.
- Scads of books.
- Mountains of books.
- Forests of books.
- Cascades.
- Cloudbursts.
- Swamps of books.
More books than you'll ever be able
to read in a lifetime.
Books on every subject ever studied
by every author
who ever set pen to paper.
- Why did you come here?
- I'm... I'm sorry.
- I warned you never to come here!
- I didn't mean any harm.
Do you realize
what you could have done?
Please! Stop!
- Get out!
- No!
Get out!
Where are you going?
Promise or no promise,
I can't stay here another minute.
No, wait, please! Please, wait!
No!
Here, now. Don't do that.
Just hold still.
That hurts!
If you'd hold still,
it wouldn't hurt as much!
Well, if you hadn't have run away,
this wouldn't have happened.
If you hadn't frightened me,
I wouldn't have run away.
Well, you shouldn't have been
in the west wing!
Well, you should learn
to control your temper.
Now, hold still. This might sting a little.
By the way,
thank you for saving my life.
You're welcome.
I don't usually leave the asylum
in the middle of the night,
but he said
you'd make it worth my while.
- I'm listening.
- It's like this.
I've got my heart set on marrying Belle,
but she needs a little persuasion.
Turned him down flat.
Everyone knows her father's a lunatic.
He was in here tonight
raving about a beast in a castle.
Maurice is harmless.
The point is, Belle would do anything
to keep him from being locked up.
Yeah, even marry him.
So, you want me to throw her father
into the asylum,
unless she agrees to marry you.
That is despicable.
I love it.
If no one will help me,
then I'll go back alone.
Yes, is that everything?
I don't care what it takes.
I'll find that castle and somehow, I...
I'll get her out of there.
- Belle! Maurice!
- Oh, well.
Guess it's not gonna work, after all.
They have to come back sometime.
And when they do,
we'll be ready for them.
LeFou, don't move from that spot
until Belle and her father come home.
But... But I...
Nuts.
I've never felt this way about anyone.
I want to do something for her.
But what?
Well, there's the usual things.
Flowers, chocolates,
promises you don't intend to keep.
No, no.
It has to be something very special.
Something that sparks her interest.
Wait a minute.
Belle?
There's something I want to show you.
But first, you have to close your eyes.
It's a surprise.
- Can I open them?
- No, no. Not yet.
Wait here.
- Now can I open them?
- All right. Now.
I can't believe it.
I've never seen so many books
in all my life.
- You... You like it?
- It's wonderful.
Then it's yours.
Thank you so much.
- Would you look at that!
- I knew it would work.
What? What works?
- It's very encouraging.
- Isn't this exciting?
- I didn't see anything.
- Come along, Chip.
There's chores to be done
in the kitchen.
But what are they talking about?
What's going on? Come on, Mom.
There's something sweet
and almost kind
But he was mean
and he was coarse and unrefined
And now he's dear and so unsure
I wonder why
I didn't see it there before
She glanced this way
I thought I saw
And when we touched
she didn't shudder at my paw
No, it can't be
I 'll just ignore
But then she's never looked at me
that way before
New and a bit alarming
Who'd have ever thought
That this could be
True
That he's no Prince Charming
But there's something in him
That I simply didn't see
- Well, who'd have thought
- Well, bless my soul
- Well, who'd have known
- Well, who, indeed
And who'd have guessed
they'd come together on their own
- It's so peculiar. Wait and see
- We'll wait and see
A few days more
There may be something there
that wasn't there before
You know, perhaps there is something
there that wasn't there before
What?
There may be something there
that wasn't there before
What's there, Mama?
I'll tell you when you're older.
Right, then,
you all know why we're here.
We have exactly 12 hours,
36 minutes and 15 seconds
to create the most magical,
spontaneous, romantic atmosphere
known to man or beast.
Right. Need I remind you
that if the last petal falls from this rose
the spell will never be broken?
Very well.
You all know your assignments.
Half of you to the west wing,
half of you to the east wing,
the rest of you, come with me.
Lighten up, Cogsworth,
and let nature take its course.
It's obvious there's a spark
between them.
Yes, but there's no harm
in fanning the flames, you know, a little.
Besides, they must fall in love tonight
if we ever expect to be human again.
- Human again.
Yes, think what that means.
I'll be cooking again
Be good-looking again
With a mademoiselle on each arm
When I'm human again
Only human again
Poised and polished
and gleaming with charm
I'll be courting again
Chic and sporting again
Which should cause
several husbands alarm
I'll hop down off this shelf
and, tout de suite, be myself
I can't wait to be human again
When we're human again
Only human again
When we 're knickknacks
and what-nots no more
When we're human again
Good and human again
Oh, chéri, won't it all be top-drawer?
I'll wear lipstick and rouge
And I won't be so huge
Why, I'll easily fit through that door
I'll exude savoir-faire
I'll wear gowns, I'll have hair
It's my prayer to be human again
When we're human again
Only human again
When the world once more
starts making sense
I'll unwind for a change
Really? That would be strange
Can I help it if I'm tense?
In a shack by the sea
I'll sit back sipping tea
Let my early retirement commence
Far from fools made of wax
I'll get down to brass tacks and relax
When I'm human again
So, sweep that dust from the floor
Let's let some light in the room
I can feel, I can tell
Someone might break the spell
Any day now
Shine up the brass on the door
Alert the dustbin and broom
If it all goes as planned
Our time may be at hand
Any day now
Open the shutters
and let in some air
Put these here
and put those over there
Sweep up the years
of sadness and tears
And throw them away
We'll be human again
Only human again
When the girl finally sets us all free
Cheeks a-blooming again
We're assuming again
We'll resume our long lost
joie de vivre
We'll be playing again
Holidaying again
And we're praying it's ASAP
We will push, we will shove
They will both fall in love
And we'll finally be human again
"For never was a story of more woe
"Than this of Juliet and her Romeo"
- Could you read it again?
- Here, why don't you read it to me?
All right.
- I can't.
- You mean, you never learned?
I learned. A little.
It's just been so long.
Well, here, I'll help you.
- Let's start here.
- Here.
- Okay. "Twoh..."
- "Two."
"Two." I knew that. "Two households..."
We'll be dancing again
We'll be twirling again
We'll be whirling around
with such ease
When we're human again
Only human again
We'll go Waltzing
those old one-two-threes
We'll be floating again
We'll be gliding again
Stepping, striding
as fine as you please
Like a real human does
I'll be all that I was
On that glorious morn
when we're finally reborn
And we're all of us human
Again
Tonight is the night.
- I'm not sure I can do this.
- You don't have time to be timid.
You must be bold, daring.
Bold. Daring.
There will be music,
romantic candlelight
provided by myself.
And when the moment is right,
you confess your love.
Yes, I...
I... I... No, I can't.
- You care for the girl, don't you?
- More than anything.
Well, then, you must tell her.
Voila! You look so, so...
Stupid.
Not quite the word I was looking for.
Perhaps a little more off the top.
Your lady awaits.
Tale as old as time
True as it can be
Barely even friends
Then somebody bends
Unexpectedly
Just a little change
Small to say the least
Both a little scared
Neither one prepared
Beauty and the Beast
Ever just the same
Ever a surprise
Ever as before
Ever just as sure
As the sun will rise
Tale as old as time
Tune as old as song
Bittersweet and strange
Finding you can change
Learning you were wrong
Certain as the sun
Rising in the east
Tale as old as time
Song as old as rhyme
Beauty and the Beast
Tale as old as time
Song as old as rhyme
Beauty and the Beast
Off to the cupboard with you now, Chip.
It's past your bedtime.
Good night, love.
Belle?
Are you happy here with me?
Yes.
What is it?
If only I could see my father again,
just for a moment.
I miss him so much.
There is a way.
This mirror will show you anything.
Anything you wish to see.
I'd like to see my father, please.
Papa. Oh, no.
He's sick. He may be dying,
and he's all alone.
Then you must go to him.
What did you say?
I release you.
You're no longer my prisoner.
- You mean I'm free?
- Yes.
Thank you.
Hold on, Papa. I'm on my way.
Take it with you
so you'll always have a way
to look back and remember me.
Thank you for understanding
how much he needs me.
Well, Your Highness, I must say
everything is going just swimmingly.
I knew you had it in you.
I let her go.
Yes, yes...
You what?
- How could you do that?
- I had to.
Yes, but... But why?
Because I love her.
He did what?
- Yes, I'm afraid it's true.
- She's going away?
But he was so close.
After all this time,
he's finally learned to love.
That's it then.
That should break the spell.
But it's not enough.
She has to love him in return.
Now it's too late.
Papa?
They're back.
Belle.
It's all right, Papa. I'm home.
I thought I'd never see you again.
- I missed you so much!
- But the Beast...
- Did you... How did you escape?
- I didn't escape, Papa.
- He... He let me go.
- That horrible beast?
But he's different now, Papa.
He's changed somehow.
- Hi I
- A stowaway.
Why, hello there, little fella.
Didn't think I'd see you again.
Belle, why'd you go away?
Don't you like us any more?
Chip, of course I do. It's just that
- May I help you?
- I've come to collect your father.
- My father?
- Don't worry, mademoiselle.
We'll take good care of him.
- My father's not crazy!
- He was raving like a lunatic!
- We all heard him, didn't we?
- Yes!
- No, I won't let you!
- Belle?
Maurice, tell us again, old man.
Just how big was the beast?
He was... I mean, he was...
He was enormous!
I'd... I'd say at least eight,
no, more like 10 feet!
Well, you don't get much crazier
than that.
It's true, I tell you.
- Get him out of here!
- Let go of me!
No! You can't do this!
Poor Belle.
It's a shame about your father.
You know he's not crazy, Gaston.
I might be able to clear up
this little misunderstanding if...
- If what?
- If you marry me.
- What?
- One little word, Belle.
- That's all it takes.
- Never!
Have it your way.
Belle? Let go of me!
My father's not crazy
and I can prove it.
Show me the Beast.
- Is it dangerous?
- No, no, he'd never hurt anyone.
Please, I know he looks vicious,
but he's really kind and gentle.
- He's my friend.
- If I didn't know better,
I'd think you had feelings
for this monster.
He's no monster, Gaston. You are!
She's as crazy as the old man.
The Beast will make off
with your children.
- He'll come after them in the night.
- No.
We're not safe till his head
is mounted on my wall!
I say we kill the Beast!
We're not safe until he's dead
He'll come stalking us at night
Set to sacrifice our children
To his monstrous appetite
He'll wreak havoc on our village
If we let him wander free
So, it's time to take some action, boys
It's time to follow me
Through the mist, through the woods
through the darkness and the shadows
It's a nightmare
but it's one exciting ride
Say a prayer, then we're there
at the drawbridge of a castle
And there's something
truly terrible inside
It's a beast
He's got fangs, razor-sharp ones
Massive paws, killer claws
for the feast
Hear him roar, see him foam
But we're not coming home
Till he's dead, good and dead
Kill the Beast!
No, I won't let you do this.
If you're not with us, you're against us.
Bring the old man!
Get your hands off me!
We can't have them running off
to warn the creature.
- Let us out!
- We'll rid the village of this beast!
- Who's with me?
- I am!
Light your torch, mount your horse
Screw your courage
to the sticking place
We're counting on Gaston
to lead the way
Through a mist, to a wood
where within a haunted castle
Something's lurking
that you don't see every day
It's a beast
One as tall as a mountain
We won't rest
till he's good and deceased
Sally forth, tally-ho
Grab your sword and your bow
Praise the Lord and here we go
We'll lay siege to the castle
and bring back his head!
I have to warn the Beast.
This is all my fault.
- Papa, what are we going to do?
- Now, now. We'll think of something.
We don't like
what we don't understand
In fact, it scares us
And this monster
is mysterious at least
Bring your guns, bring your knives
Save your children and your wives
We'll save our village and our lives
We'll kill the Beast
I knew it. I knew it was foolish
to get our hopes up.
Maybe it would have been better
if she'd never come at all.
- Could it be...
- Is it she?
Sacrebleu! Invaders!
- Encroachers.
- And they have the mirror.
Warn the master.
If it's a fight they want,
we'll be ready for them.
Who's with me?
Take whatever booty you can find.
But remember, the Beast is mine!
Hearts ablaze, banners high
We go marching into battle
Unafraid, although the danger
just increased
Raise the flag, sing the song
Here we come, we're 50 strong
And 50 Frenchmen can't be wrong
Let's kill the Beast
- Pardon me, Master.
- Leave me in peace.
But, sir, the castle is under attack.
Kill the Beast! Kill the Beast!
- This isn't working.
- Lumiere, we must do something!
Wait! I know!
Kill the Beast! Kill the Beast!
What shall we do, Master?
It doesn't matter now.
Just let them come.
Kill the Beast! Kill the Beast!
Kill the Beast!
Now!
Yes!
Here we go!
What the devil?
Belle, look out!
You guys gotta try this thing.
Up here, you scurvy scum.
Now!
And stay out.
Get up.
What's the matter, Beast?
Too kind and gentle to fight back?
No!
- Belle.
- No, Gaston, don't.
Let's go, Philippe.
Come on out and fight!
Were you in love with her, Beast?
Did you honestly think she'd want you
when she had someone like me?
It's over, Beast! Belle is mine!
Let me go. Let me go.
Please, don't hurt me.
I'll do anything. Anything!
Get out.
Beast!
Belle.
Belle?
You came back.
You...
Of course I came back.
I couldn't let them...
This is all my fault.
If only I'd gotten here sooner.
Maybe it's better... It's better this way.
Don't talk like that.
You'll be all right.
We're together now.
Everything's going to be fine, you'll see.
At least I got to see you
one last time.
No. No.
Please. Please. Please don't leave me.
I love you.
Belle, it's me.
It is you.
Lumiere.
Cogsworth.
Mrs. Potts!
- Look at us.
- Mama. Mama.
- Oh, my goodness.
- It is a miracle.
I 'amour.
Well, Lumiere, old friend.
Shall we let bygones be bygones?
Of course, mon ami.
I told you she would break the spell.
I beg your pardon, old friend,
but I believe I told you.
No, you didn't. I told you.
You most certainly did not,
you pompous,
paraffin-headed pea-brain!
En garde, you overgrown pocket watch!
- Take that.
- Stop shoving.
Are they gonna live
happily ever after, Mama?
Of course, my dear.
Of course.
Do I still have to sleep in the cupboard?
Certain as the sun
Rising in the east
Tale as old as time
Song as old as rhyme
Beauty and the Beast
Tale as old as time
Song as old as rhyme
Beauty and the Beast
www.moviesubtitles.org