[gulls cry]
- [gull cries]
- [dolphins yap]
# I'll tell you a tale
of the bottomless blue
# And it's, hey
to the starboard, heave-ho
# Look out, lad
a mermaid be waiting for you
# In mysterious fathoms below
Isn't this great?
The salty sea air,
- the wind blowing in your face.
- [barks]
- A perfect day to be at sea.
- Oh, yes, delightful. [retches]
A fine strong wind
and a following sea.
King Triton must be
in a friendly type mood.
- King Triton?
- Ruler of the Merpeople, lad.
Thought every good sailor
knew about him.
Merpeople.
Eric, pay no attention
to this nautical nonsense.
But it ain't nonsense. It's the truth.
I'm tellin' ya! Down in the depths
of the ocean they live! Oh!
Aah!
# In mysterious fathoms below #
[sighs]
[fanfare of trumpets]
[coughs] His Royal Highness,
King Triton!
[applause, cheering]
And presenting the distinguished
court composer,
Horatio Felonious Ignacious
Crustaceous Sebastian!
[fanfare of kazoos]
[applause]
- [both whinny]
- Whoa!
I'm really looking forward
to this performance, Sebastian.
[chuckles] Your Majesty!
This will be the finest concert
I have ever conducted.
Your daughters,
they will be spectacular!
- [whinnies]
- Yes.
- Especially my little Ariel.
- Yes, yes.
She has the most beautiful voice. Hmm?
If only she'd show up
for rehearsals once in a while.
- [orchestra tunes up]
- [applause]
# Ah, we are the daughters of Triton
# Great father who loves us
and named us well
# Aquata
# Andrina
# Arista, Attina
# Adella, Alana
# And then there is the
youngest in her musical debut
# Our seventh little sister
We're presenting her to you
# To sing a song Sebastian wrote
# Her voice is like a bell
- # She's our sister Ari...
- [all gasp]
- [gasps]
- Ariel!
[male voice] Ariel, wait for me.
Flounder, hurry up.
[pants] You know I can't swim that fast.
There it is.
[Ariel] Isn't it fantastic?
Yeah, sure. It's great.
Now let's get outta here.
Oh! You're not getting
cold fins now, are you?
Who, me? No way.
It's just... It, uh...
It looks damp in there. Yeah.
And I think I may be
coming down with something.
Yeah, I got this cough. [coughs]
[whispers] All right. I'm going inside.
You can just stay here
and watch for sharks.
OK.
[whispering] Yeah, you go.
I'll stay and...
What? Sharks? Ariel!
[grunts]
Ariel, I can't... I mean...
- Ariel, help!
- [laughs]
- Oh, Flounder.
- [whispers] Ariel.
Do you really think there
might be sharks around here?
Flounder, don't be such a guppy.
I'm not a guppy. [grunts]
This is great.
I mean, I really love this.
Excitement, adventure, danger
lurking around every corner...
[screams] Ariel!
[grunts] Oh, are you OK?
Yeah, sure. No problem. I'm OK.
Shh!
Oh, my gosh. Oh, my gosh!
Have you ever seen anything so
wonderful in your entire life?
Wow! Cool! But, uh, what is it?
I don't know, but I bet Scuttle will.
What was that?
Did you hear something?
Mmm? I wonder what this one is.
- Ariel?
- Flounder, will you relax?
Nothing is going to happen.
- [growls]
- Shark!
Shark! We're gonna die!
[Flounder screams]
Oh, no!
[grunts]
[Flounder screams]
- [growls]
- [Flounder whimpers]
You big bully! [blows raspberry]
[gasps]
[Ariel chuckles]
Flounder, you really are a guppy.
I am not.
# Hmm-hmm, fourteen hundred
and ninety-two
# Dah-de-dum
Dee-do-do
# Rum-dim-dim
Dee-do-dee-do #
- [Ariel] Scuttle!
- Whoa!
Mermaid off the port bow!
[shouts] Ariel, how you doin', kid?
- Whoa, what a swim.
- Scuttle, look what we found.
We were in this sunken ship,
and it was really creepy...
Human stuff, huh? Hey, let me see.
Oh! Oh! Look at this.
Wow. This is special.
This is very, very unusual.
- What? What is it?
- It's a dinglehopper.
Humans use these little babies...
to straighten their hair out.
See? Just a little twirl here
and a yank there and violee...
Ya got an aesthetically pleasing
configuration of hair
that humans go nuts over.
A dinglehopper.
- What about that one?
- Ah!
This I haven't seen in years.
This is wonderful!
- A banded, bulbous snarfblatt.
- [both] Oh!
The snarfblatt dates to prehistorical
times when humans used to sit around
and stare at each other all day.
Got very boring.
So, they invented this
snarfblatt to make fine music.
Allow me.
- [Scuttle coughs]
- Music!
- It's stuck!
- Oh, the concert!
Oh, my gosh! My father's gonna kill me!
The concert was today?
You could make
a little planter out of it.
I'm sorry! I've gotta go!
Thank you, Scuttle!
Any time, sweetie!
Any time.
Yes, hurry home, Princess.
We wouldn't want to miss old Daddy's
celebration, now, would we?
Ha! Celebration, indeed. Oh, bah!
In my day, we had fantastical feasts,
- when I lived in the palace.
- [whimpers]
[gulps]
And now look at me.
Wasted away to practically nothing.
Banished and exiled
and practically starving,
while he and his flimsy
fish folk celebrate.
Well, I'll give 'em something
to celebrate soon enough.
Flotsam! Jetsam!
I want you to keep an extra close watch
on this pretty little daughter of his.
She may be the key to Triton's undoing.
I just don't know what we're
going to do with you, young lady.
Daddy, I'm sorry. I just forgot.
As a result of your careless behavior...
Careless and reckless behavior!
...the entire celebration was, uh...
Well, it was ruined! That's all!
Completely destroyed!
This concert was to be
the pinnacle of my distinguished career.
Now, thanks to you, I am the
laughingstock of the entire kingdom!
But it wasn't her fault...
Uh, well, first, uh,
the shark chased us.
Yeah, yeah. And we tried to...
but we couldn't, and he...
[growls] And... And we... Whoa!
[sighs] And then we were safe.
But then this seagull came,
and it was, "This is this..."
Seagull?
- [gasps]
- What? Oh!
You went up to the surface again,
didn't you?
- Didn't you?
- Nothing happened.
Oh, Ariel, how many times
must we go through this?
You could have been seen by one of those
barbarians, by one of those humans!
- They're not barbarians.
- They are dangerous.
Do you think I want to see my youngest
daughter snared by a fish-eater's hook?
I'm 16 years old.
I'm not a child anymore.
Don't you take that tone of voice
with me, young lady!
As long as you live under my ocean,
you'll obey my rules!
- If you would just listen...
- Not another word!
And I am never... never to hear of you
going to the surface again!
Is that clear?
Hmph! Teenagers.
They think they know everything.
You give them an inch,
they swim all over you.
Do you think I was too hard on her?
Definitely not.
Why, if Ariel was my daughter,
I'd show her who was boss.
None of this flitting to the surface
and other such nonsense.
No, sir. I'd keep her
under tight control.
- You're right, Sebastian.
- Of course.
Ariel needs constant supervision.
Someone to watch over her,
to keep her out of trouble.
All the time.
And you are just the crab to do it.
[Sebastian] How do I get myself
into these situations?
I should be writing symphonies,
not tagging along after
some headstrong teenager.
Hmm? What is that girl up to?
[Sebastian pants]
[gasps]
Huh?
Ariel, are you OK?
[Ariel] If only I could
make him understand.
I just don't see things the way he does.
I don't see how a world
that makes such wonderful things
could be bad.
# Look at this stuff, isn't it neat
# Wouldn't ya think
my collection's complete
# Wouldn't ya think I'm the girl
# The girl who has everything
# Look at this trove, treasures untold
# How many wonders
can one cavern hold?
# Lookin' around here you'd think
# Sure, she's got everything
# I've got gadgets and gizmos aplenty
# I've got whozits and whatzits galore
# You want thingamabobs? I got 20
# But who cares
No big deal
# I want more
# I wanna be where the people are
# I wanna see
Wanna see 'em dancin'
# Walkin' around on those...
What do ya call 'em?
Oh, feet.
- [giggles]
- [grunts]
# Flippin' your fins
you don't get too far
# Legs are required for jumpin', dancin'
# Strollin' along down a...
What's that word again?
# Street
# Up where they walk
Up where they run
# Up where they stay all day in the sun
# Wanderin' free
Wish I could be
# Part of that world
# What would I give if I could live
- # Out of these waters?
- [gasps]
# What would I pay to spend a day
# Warm on the sand?
# Betcha on land they understand
# Bet they don't reprimand
their daughters
# Bright young women sick of swimmin'
# Ready to stand
# And ready to know
what the people know
# Ask 'em my questions
and get some answers
# What's a fire and why does it...
What's the word?
# Burn?
# When's it my turn? Wouldn't I love
# Love to explore that shore up above?
# Out of the sea
# Wish I could be
# Part of that
# World #
- [accordion]
- Sebastian!
Ariel, what are you...
How could you... What is all this?
It's, uh... It's just my collection.
Oh, I see.
Your collection, hmm.
If your father knew about this place...
You're not gonna tell him, are you?
Oh, please, Sebastian,
he would never understand.
Ariel, you're under
a lot of pressure down here.
I'll take you home
- and get you something warm to drink.
- [rumbling]
- [Ariel] What do you suppose...
- Ariel?
Ariel?
[rumbling continues]
[Ariel gasps]
- [giggles]
- Ariel, what are you...
Jumpin' jellyfish!
Ariel? Ariel! Please! Come back!
[men laugh and chatter]
[accordion]
[laughter]
[barks]
[sniffs]
[gasps]
[man whistles] Max! Here, boy!
[Max barks]
Hey, come on, mutt.
What ya doin', huh, Max?
Come on, Max. [laughs]
Good boy. Good boy.
Hey there, sweetie! Quite a show, eh?
Scuttle, be quiet. They'll hear you.
Ooh, I got ya. I got ya.
We're bein' intrepidaceous.
We're out to discover!
I've never seen a human
this close before.
Oh. He's very handsome, isn't he?
I don't know. He looks kind of
hairy and slobbery to me.
Not that one.
The one playing the snarfblatt.
Silence, silence.
It is now my honor and privilege
to present our esteemed Prince Eric
with a very special, very expensive,
very large birthday present.
Ah, Grimsby, ya old beanpole,
you shouldn't have.
- [applause]
- I know.
[Grimsby] Happy birthday, Eric.
[gasping]
[growls]
Uh, gee, Grim... Ha! [clears throat]
It's, uh... It's really somethin'.
Yes, I commissioned it myself.
Of course, I had hoped
it would be a wedding present.
Come on, Grim. Don't start.
You're not still sore because I didn't
fall for the princess of Glowerhaven?
Oh, my! Oh, Eric, it isn't me alone.
The entire kingdom wants to see you
happily settled with the right girl.
Oh, she's out there somewhere. I just...
I just haven't found her yet.
[Grimsby] Perhaps you haven't
been looking hard enough.
Believe me, Grim,
when I find her, I'll know.
Without a doubt, it'll just...
bam... hit me, like lightning.
[thunder]
[man] Hurricane a-comin'!
Stand fast! Secure the riggin'!
[shouting]
[barks]
Whoa! The wind's all of a sudden
on the move here! Yo!
Ariel!
[bell clangs]
[Eric] Look out!
- [clanging]
- [screaming]
- Grim! Hang on!
- [coughs]
[Max barks]
Max!
- [barks]
- Jump, Max!
Come on, boy! Jump! You can do it, Max!
[Max yelps]
Eric!
[Max barks]
Is he... dead?
It's hard to say.
Oh, I... I can't make out a heartbeat.
No, look! He's breathing.
He's so beautiful.
# What would I give
to live where you are?
# What would I pay
to stay here beside you?
# What would I do
to see you smiling at me?
# Where would we walk
Where would we run
# If we could stay all day in the sun?
# Just you and me and I could be
# Part of your world #
[Max barks]
[Grimsby] Eric? Eric!
You really delight in
these sadistic strains
on my blood pressure, don't you?
- [Max barks]
- A girl... rescued me.
She... She was singing.
She had the most beautiful voice.
Ah, Eric, I think you've swallowed
a bit too much seawater.
Off we go. Come along, Max.
We just gonna forget
this whole thing ever happened.
The sea king will never know.
You won't tell him. I won't tell him.
I will stay in one piece.
# I don't know when
I don't know how
# But I know something's
starting right now
# Watch and you'll see
# Some day I'll be
# Part of your
# World #
[Max barks]
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no.
I can't stand it. It's too easy.
The child is in love with a human.
And not just any human. A prince!
[chuckles] Her daddy will love that.
King Triton's headstrong, lovesick girl
would make a charming addition
to my little garden.
[cackles]
[female voice]
Ariel dear, time to come out.
You've been in there all morning.
[hums tune]
What is with her lately?
[continues humming]
- Oh. Morning, Daddy.
- Well! [chuckles]
[continues humming]
- Oh, she's got it bad.
- What? What has she got?
Isn't it obvious, Daddy?
Ariel's in love.
Ariel? In love?
OK. So far, so good.
I don't think the king knows.
But it will not be easy keeping
something like this a secret for long.
[sighs] He loves me.
Mmm. He loves me not.
He loves me! [laughs] I knew it!
Ariel, stop talking crazy!
I gotta see him again... tonight.
- Scuttle knows where he lives.
- Ariel, please!
Will you get your head out of the clouds
and back in the water where it belongs?
I'll swim to his castle, then Flounder
will splash around to get his attention.
- And then we'll go...
- Down here is your home!
Ariel, listen to me.
The human world... It's a mess.
Life under the sea is better
than anything they got up there.
# The seaweed is always greener
in somebody else's lake
# You dream about going up there
# But that is a big mistake
# Just look at the world around you
# Right here on the ocean floor
# Such wonderful things around you
# What more is you lookin' for?
# Under the sea
Under the sea
# Darling, it's better
down where it's wetter
# Take it from me
# Up on the shore they work all day
# Out in the sun they slave away
# While we devoting full time
to floating under the sea
[steel drums]
# Down here all the fish is happy
# As off through the waves
they roll, yeah
# The fish on the land ain't happy
# They sad 'cause they in the bowl
# But fish in the bowl is lucky
# They in for a worser fate
# One day when the boss get hungry
# Guess who's gonna be on the plate
Oh, no!
# Under the sea
Under the sea
# Nobody beat us, fry us
and eat us in fricassee
# We what the land folks loves to cook
# Under the sea we off the hook
# We got no troubles
Life is the bubbles
- # Under the sea
# Since life is sweet here
we got it beat here
- # Naturally
# Even the sturgeon and the ray
# They get the urge and start to play
# We got the spirit,
you got to hear it, under the sea
# The newt play the flute
The carp play the harp
# The plaice play the bass
and they soundin' sharp
# The bass play the brass
The chub play the tub
# The fluke is the duke of soul
# The ray, he can play
The ling's on the strings
# The trout's rocking out
The blackfish, she sings
# The smelt and the sprat
They know where it's at
# And, oh that blowfish blow
[Sebastian laughs]
- # Yeah, under the sea
- # Under the sea
# When the sardine begin the beguine
- # It's music to me
- # Music it is to me
# What do they got? A lot of sand
# We got a hot crustacean band
# Each little clam here
know how to jam here under the sea
# Each little slug here
cutting a rug here under the sea
# Each little snail here
know how to wail here
# That's why it's hotter under the water
# Yeah, we in luck here
down in the muck here
# Under the sea #
Ariel?
Oh, somebody's got to
nail that girl's fins to the floor.
[Seahorse] Sebastian!
[pants] Sebastian, I've been
looking all over for you.
I've got an urgent message
from the sea king.
The sea king?
He wants to see you right away.
Something about Ariel.
[gasps] He knows.
[laughs] Hey, let's see now.
Oh, who could the lucky merman be?
[clears throat] Come in, Sebastian.
[inhales sharply] I mustn't overreact.
I must remain calm.
[squeaky voice] Yes? [clears throat]
- Yes, Your Majesty?
- Sebastian.
I'm concerned about Ariel.
Have you noticed she's been
acting peculiar lately?
- Oh! Uh, peculiar?
- You know, mooning about.
Daydreaming, singing to herself.
You haven't noticed, hmm?
Oh, well, I...
- Sebastian?
- Hmm?
I know you've been
keeping something from me.
[gulps] Keeping something?
About Ariel?
- Ariel?
- In love, hmm?
[whimpers] I tried to stop her, sir!
She wouldn't listen!
I told her to stay away from humans!
They are bad!
- They are trouble!
- Humans? What about humans?
Humans? [chuckles nervously]
Who said anything about humans? [yelps]
Flounder, why can't you just
tell me what this is all about?
You'll see. It's a surprise.
Oh, Flounder.
Flounder, you're the best!
It looks just like him.
It even has his eyes.
[giggles] Why, Eric, run away with you?
Oh, this is all so... so sudden.
[laughs]
[gasps]
Daddy?
I consider myself a reasonable merman.
I set certain rules,
and I expect those rules to be obeyed.
But, Dad, I...
Is it true you rescued
a human from drowning?
I had to...
Contact between the human world
and the mer world is strictly forbidden.
Ariel, you know that!
Everyone knows that.
- He would have died.
- One less human to worry about.
- You don't even know him.
- Know him?
I don't have to know him!
They're all the same.
Spineless, savage,
harpooning fish-eaters
incapable of any feeling...
Daddy, I love him! [gasps]
No! Have you lost
your senses completely?
He's a human. You're a mermaid.
I don't care.
So help me, Ariel,
I am going to get through to you.
And if this is the only way, so be it!
Daddy! No!
No! Please!
Daddy, stop! Daddy, stop it!
Daddy, no!
[Ariel sobs]
Ariel, I...
[sobs] Just go away.
Poor child. Poor, sweet child.
She has a very serious problem.
If only there were
something we could do.
But there is something.
Who... Who are you?
Don't be scared.
We represent someone who can help you.
Someone who can make
all your dreams come true.
[both] Just imagine...
You and your prince...
Together forever.
I don't understand.
Ursula has great powers.
[gasps] The sea witch?
Why, that's... I couldn't possibly.
No! Get out of here. Leave me alone!
Suit yourself.
It was only a suggestion.
Wait.
[both] Yes?
- [sniffles] Poor Ariel.
- I didn't mean to tell.
It was an accident. [mutters]
Ariel? Where are you going?
Ariel, what are you doing here
with this riffraff?
I'm going to see Ursula.
[gasps] Ariel, no! No!
She's a demon. She's a monster.
Why don't you go tell my father?
You're good at that.
But... But, I... Come on!
This way.
[creatures moan]
[gasps, grunts]
[pants]
[Ursula] Come in. Come in, my child.
We mustn't lurk in doorways. It's rude.
One might question
your upbringing. [chuckles]
Now, then, you're here
because you have a thing for
this human, this prince fellow.
Not that I blame you.
He is quite a catch, isn't he?
Well, angelfish,
the solution to your problem is simple.
The only way to get what you want
is to become a human yourself.
[gasps] Can you do that?
My dear, sweet child. That's what I do.
It's what I live for.
To help unfortunate merfolk,
like yourself,
poor souls with no one else to turn to.
# I admit that in the past
I've been a nasty
# They weren't kidding when
they called me, well, a witch
# But you'll find that nowadays
I've mended all my ways
# Repented, seen the light
and made a switch
True? Yes.
# And I fortunately know a little magic
# It's a talent that
I always have possessed
# And here lately, please don't
laugh, I use it on behalf
# Of the miserable, lonely and depressed
Pathetic.
# Poor unfortunate souls
# In pain, in need
# This one longing to be thinner
# That one wants to get the girl
# And do I help them? Yes, indeed
# Those poor, unfortunate souls
So sad, so true
# They come flocking to my cauldron
# Crying spells, Ursula, please
# And I help them
Yes, I do
# Now it's happened once or twice
# Someone couldn't pay the price
# And I'm afraid I had to
rake 'em across the coals
# Yes, I've had the odd complaint
# But on the whole I've been a saint
# To those poor unfortunate souls #
Now, here's the deal.
I will make you a potion that will
turn you into a human for three days.
Got that? Three days.
Now, listen, this is important.
Before the sun sets on the third day,
you've got to get dear old princie
to fall in love with you.
That is, he's got to kiss you.
Not just any kiss,
the kiss of true love.
If he does kiss you before
the sun sets on the third day,
you'll remain human permanently.
But if he doesn't, you'll turn
back into a mermaid...
and... you belong to me!
No, Ariel! [muffled]
Have we got a deal?
If I become human,
I'll never be with
my father or sisters again.
That's right!
But you'll have your man.
[chuckles] Life's full of
tough choices, isn't it?
[cackles]
Oh! And there is one more thing.
We haven't discussed
the subject of payment.
You can't get something for nothing.
- But I don't have any...
- I'm not asking much.
Just a token really, a trifle.
You'll never even miss it.
What I want from you is... your voice.
- My voice?
- You've got it, sweetcakes.
No more talking, singing. Zip!
But without my voice, how can I...
You'll have your looks,
your pretty face.
And don't underestimate the
importance of body language!
Ha!
# The men up there
don't like a lot of blabber
# They think a girl
who gossips is a bore
# Yes, on land it's much preferred
for ladies not to say a word
# And, after all, dear
What is idle prattle for?
Come on!
# They're not all that
impressed with conversation
# True gentlemen avoid it when they can
# But they dote and swoon and fawn
# On a lady who's withdrawn
# It's she who holds her tongue
who gets her man
# Come on, you poor unfortunate soul
# Go ahead, make your choice
# I'm a very busy woman
and I haven't got all day
# It won't cost much, just your voice
# Ya poor, unfortunate soul
# It's sad, but true
# If you want to cross a bridge,
my sweet you've got to pay the toll
# Take a gulp and take a breath
and go ahead and sign the scroll
# Flotsam, Jetsam
Now I've got her, boys
# The boss is on a roll
# This poor, unfortunate
# Soul
# Beluga, sevruga
# Come, winds of the Caspian Sea
# Larynxis, glossitis
Et max laryngitis
# La voce to me
Now, sing!
[vocalizes]
Keep singing!
[vocalizing continues]
[cackles]
[pipe plays]
[barks]
That voice.
I can't get it out of my head.
I've looked everywhere, Max.
Where could she be?
Well, look at what
the catfish dragged in.
[laughs] Look at ya. Look at ya.
There's somethin' different.
Don't tell me.
I got it. It's your hairdo, right?
You've been usin' the dinglehopper?
No? No, huh? Well, let me see.
New seashells?
No new seashells.
I gotta admit I can't
put my foot on it right now.
If I stand here long enough...
She's got legs, you idiot!
She traded her voice to the sea
witch and got legs. Geez, man!
I knew that.
Ariel's been turned into a human.
She's gotta make the prince fall in love
with her, and he's gotta kiss her.
[Sebastian]
And she's only got three days!
Just look at her!
On legs! On human legs!
My nerves are shot!
This is a catastrophe!
What would her father say?
I'll tell you what her father'd say.
He'd say he's gonna kill himself a crab!
That's what he'd say!
I'm gonna march meself
straight home right now
and tell him just like I should
have done the minute...
And don't you shake your head
at me, young lady.
Maybe there's still time.
If we could get that witch
to give you back your voice,
you could go home with all
the normal fish and just be...
Just be...
Just be miserable
for the rest of your life.
All right, all right.
I'll try to help ya find that prince.
Boy, what a soft shell
I'm turning out to be.
Now, Ariel, I'm telling ya.
If you wanna be a human, the first thing
to do is dress like one. Let me see.
[sniffs]
- [barks]
- Max? What?
Huh? What? Max!
[wolf whistles] Ya look great, kid.
- Ya look sensational.
- [barks]
[gasps]
- [pants]
- [Sebastian mutters]
[barks]
[Eric] Max!
Max!
- Quiet, Max.
- [barks]
What's gotten into you, fella? Oh.
- Oh, I see.
- [barks]
[Eric] Are you OK, miss?
I'm sorry if this knucklehead
scared you.
He's harmless really, uh...
You seem very familiar to me.
Have we met?
[Max barks]
We have met. I knew it.
You're the one,
the one I've been looking for.
What's your name?
What's wrong? What is it?
You can't speak? Oh!
Oh, then you couldn't be
who I thought.
- [sighs]
What is it? You're hurt?
No, no. You need help?
Whoa, whoa, careful! Careful, easy.
Gee, you must have
really been through something.
Don't worry. Don't worry. I'll help you.
Come on. Come on. You'll be OK.
[barks]
[woman] Washed up from a shipwreck.
Oh, the poor thing.
We'll have you feeling better
in no time.
- [woman hums]
- [gasps]
I'll just... I'll just
get this washed for you.
[gasps, splutters]
Well, you must have at least
heard about this girl.
- No!
- Gertrude says...
When has Gertrude ever
gotten anything right?
[burps]
- Really.
- Madam, please...
She shows up in rags and doesn't speak.
Not my idea of a princess.
If Eric's looking for a girl,
I know a couple of highly
available ones right here.
[gasps]
[knife glistens]
Oh, Eric, be reasonable.
Nice young ladies just don't
swim around rescuing people
in the middle of the ocean
and then flitter off into oblivion...
I'm tellin' ya, Grim. She was real.
I'm gonna find that girl,
and I'm gonna marry her.
[woman laughs] Come on, honey.
Don't be shy.
Oh, Eric, isn't she a vision?
Uh, you look wonderful.
Come, come, come. You must be
famished. Let me help you, my dear.
There we go. That's better.
Now, quite comfy, hmm? Ha, ha.
It's not often that we have
such a lovely dinner guest, eh, Eric?
[match strikes]
Uh, do you like it?
It is rather a fine one.
- [laughs]
- [woman] Oh, my.
[clears throat] Sorry, Grim.
Why, Eric, that's the first time
I've seen you smile in weeks.
Ah, very amusing. [sniffs]
Carlotta, my dear, what's for dinner?
Oh, you're gonna love it!
Chef's been fixing
his specialty: stuffed crab.
[gasps]
# Nouvelle cuisine
# Les Champs-Elyses
# Maurice Chevalier
[chuckles]
# Les poissons, les poissons
# How I love les poissons
# Love to chop and to serve little fish
# First I cut off their heads
Then I pull out their bones
# Ah, mais oui a c'est toujours delish
# Les poissons, les poissons
[laughs in rhythm]
# With the cleaver I hack them in two
# I pull out what's inside
and I serve it up fried
# 'Cause I love little fishes
Don't you?
# Here's something for
tempting the palate
# Prepared in the classic technique
# First you pound the fish flat
with the mallet
# Then you slash through the skin,
give the belly a slice
# Then you rub some salt in
# 'Cause that makes it taste nice
- Oh.
- Zut alors! I have missed one.
# Sacrebleu! What is this?
# How on earth could I miss
# Such a sweet, little succulent crab?
# Quel dommage! What a loss
# Here we go, in the sauce
# Now some flour I think just a dab
# Now I'll stuff you with bread
# It don't hurt 'cause you're dead
and you're certainly lucky you are
# 'Cause it's gonna be hot
in my big silver pot
# Toodle-oo, mon poisson, au revoir #
- [thudding]
- Eh?
What is this? Ow!
Yeow! Oh, ow, ow, oh!
[screaming]
[crashing]
I think I'd better go see
what Louis is up to.
Come out, you little pipsqueak,
and fight like a man!
- Louis!
- Ow.
- What are you doing?
- Well, I was just, uh...
- I'm sorry, madame.
- [huffs]
You know, Eric, perhaps
our young guest might enjoy
seeing some of the sights
of the kingdom.
Something in the way of a tour.
[chuckles] I'm sorry, Grim.
What was that?
You can't spend all your time
moping about. You need to get out.
- Do something. Have a life.
- Shh!
- Get your mind off...
- Easy, Grim, easy.
It's not a bad idea,
if she's interested.
Well, what do ya say?
Would you like to join me on
a tour of my kingdom tomorrow?
Wonderful! Now, let's eat before
this crab wanders off my plate.
- [Max barks]
- [whistles] Come here, boy.
- [barks]
- [Eric growls]
This has got to be, without a doubt,
the single most humiliating
day of my life.
I hope that you appreciate what I go
through for you, young lady.
Now, we got to make a plan
to get that boy to kiss you.
Tomorrow when he takes you for that
ride, you gotta look your best.
You gotta bat your eyes, like this.
You gotta pucker up your lips,
like this.
Hmm.
You are hopeless, child. You know that?
Completely hopeless. [yawns]
Any sign of them?
No, Your Majesty.
We searched everywhere.
We've found no trace of
your daughter or Sebastian.
Keep looking. Leave no shell unturned,
no coral unexplored.
Let no one in this kingdom sleep
until she's safe at home.
Yes, sire.
[Triton] Oh, what have I done?
What have I done?
Has he kissed her yet?
- Not yet.
- Oh!
[chatter]
[clucking]
Oh, Judy!
Yo! Flounder! Any kissing?
No, not yet.
Well, they'd better get crackin'!
[whinnies]
[Flounder] Move over.
Move your big feathers.
I can't see a thing.
[Scuttle] Nothing is happening.
Only one day left, and that boy
ain't puckered up once.
OK. All right, this calls for
a little vocal romantic stimulation.
- Stand back!
- [chirping]
[clears throat] Wa, wa, wa, wa-wa!
Wow. Somebody should find that poor
animal and put it out of its misery.
Wa, wa, wa-wa!
Wa, wa, wa, wa-wa!
Geez, man. I'm surrounded by amateurs.
[Scuttle] Wa, wa, wa, wa!
You want something done
you've got to do it yourself.
First we got to create the mood.
Percussion.
Strings. Winds.
Words.
# There you see her
# Sitting there across the way
# She don't got a lot to say
# But there's something about her
# And you don't know why
but you're dyin' to try
# You wanna kiss the girl
Did you hear something?
# Yes, you want her
# Look at her
You know you do
# Possible she want you too
# There is one way to ask her
# It don't take a word
# Not a single word
Go on and kiss the girl
Sing with me now.
# Sha-la-la-la-la-la
My, oh, my
# Look like the boy too shy
He ain't gonna kiss the girl
# Sha-la-la-la-la-la
Ain't that sad?
# Ain't it a shame?
# Too bad he gonna miss the girl
You know, I feel really bad
not knowing your name.
Maybe I could guess. Is it Mildred?
[laughs] OK, no.
How about Diana? Rachel?
- Ariel. Her name is Ariel.
- Ariel?
Ariel? Oh.
That's kind of pretty. OK. Ariel.
# Now's your moment
# Floating in a blue lagoon
# Boy, you better do it soon
- # No time will be better
- # Ya, ya, ya, ya, ya
# She don't say a word
# And she won't say a word
until ya kiss the girl
[fish chatter]
# Sha-la-la-la-la-la
Don't be scared
# You got the mood prepared
Go on and kiss the girl
# Sha-la-la-la-la-la
Don't stop now
# Don't try to hide it
how you wanna kiss the girl
# Whoa, whoa
# Sha-la-la-la-la-la
Float along
- # And listen to the song
- Wa, wa, wa, wa-wa!
- # Song say kiss the girl
- # Whoa, whoa
# Sha-la-la-la-la-la
Music play
# Do what the music say
You gotta kiss the girl
[kissing sounds]
# Kiss the girl
- # Why don't you
- # Kiss the girl?
# Go on and kiss the girl
- Go on and...
- # Kiss the girl #
- Whoa!
- [Eric] Hang on, I've got ya.
- [both cackle]
- [Ursula] Nice work, boys.
That was a close one. Too close.
The little tramp!
Ah, she's better than I thought.
Well, at this rate, he'll be
kissing her by sunset for sure.
Well, it's time Ursula took
matters into her own tentacles.
Triton's daughter will be mine!
And then I'll make him writhe.
I'll see him wriggle
like a worm on a hook!
[cackles]
[pipe plays]
Eric? If I may say,
far better than any dream girl
is one of flesh and blood,
one warm and caring
and right before your eyes.
[sighs]
[Ariel's voice vocalizing]
Ariel!
Ariel, wake up! Wake up.
I just heard the news. Congratulations.
Kiddo, we did it!
What is this idiot babbling about?
Right, as if you two didn't know, huh?
The whole town's buzzin' about the
prince gettin' hitched this afternoon!
You know, he's getting married.
You silly side-walker.
I just wanted to wish ya luck.
I'll catch ya later. I wouldn't miss it!
[Grimsby] Well, now, Eric.
It appears that I was mistaken.
This mystery maiden of yours
does, in fact, exist.
[Grimsby] A-And she is lovely.
Congratulations, my dear.
[Eric] We wish to be married
as soon as possible.
[Grimsby] Oh, yes, of course, Eric, but,
uh, these things do take time, you know.
This afternoon, Grimsby.
The wedding ship departs at sunset.
Oh. Oh. Very well, Eric,
uh, as you wish.
[snickers]
[organ plays]
[chatter, laughter]
[cries]
[hums: The Wedding March]
[Ariel's voice] # What a lovely
little bride I'll make
# My dear, I'll look divine
[laughs]
# Things are working out
# According to my ultimate design
[laughs]
# Soon I'll have that little mermaid
# And the ocean will be mine #
[cackles]
The sea witch! Oh, no!
She's gonna... I gotta...
Ariel!
Ariel, I was flying...
Of course, I was flying. And...
I saw the... the watch...
The witch was watching the mirror,
and she was singin'
with a stolen set of pipes.
Do you hear what I'm tellin' you?
The prince is marrying
the sea witch in disguise!
- Are you sure about this?
- Have I ever been wrong?
I mean, when it's important?
What are we gonna do?
[Ursula's voice] Before the sun
sets on the third day.
[echoes] Day...
Ariel, grab onto that.
Flounder, get her to that boat
as fast as your fins can carry you.
I'll try!
I gotta get to the sea king.
He must know about this.
- What about me? What about me?
- You!
Find a way to stall that wedding!
Stall the wedding. W-What am I?
What? That's it! [squawks]
- [squawks]
- [chirping]
[squawks]
- [chattering]
- Let's go!
We got an emergency here.
[squawking, chirping]
[organ plays]
[Max growls]
[yelps]
Dearly beloved...
[pants] Don't worry, Ariel.
We're gonna make it.
We're almost there.
Yes, um, do you, Eric, take Vanessa...
to be your lawfully wedded wife
for as long as you both shall live?
I do.
It being... And do you...
[squawking, chirping]
[gasps]
- [screams]
- [barks]
Oh!
[seals bark]
Oh! Oh! Oh!
[screams]
Then by the power...
[Ursula's voice] Get away, you slimy...
- Oh!
- [barks]
- [chattering]
- [squawks]
- Oh, why, you little...
[barks]
- [growls]
- [screams]
[Ariel's voice vocalizing]
[moans] Huh?
[vocalizes]
Ariel?
- Eric.
- [barks]
You... You can talk?
- You're the one.
- Eric, get away from her.
- It was you all the time.
- Eric, I wanted to tell you.
- [Ursula] Eric, no!
- [moans]
You're too late! [cackles]
You're too late!
- [all gasp]
- [cackles]
- [gasps]
- So long, lover boy.
- Ariel!
- Poor little princess.
It's not you I'm after.
I've a much bigger fish to...
- Ursula, stop!
- Hmph!
Why, King Triton!
[chuckles] How are you?
- Let her go!
- Not a chance! She's mine now!
- We made a deal.
- Daddy, I'm sorry! I-I...
I didn't mean to! I didn't know!
[Ursula laughs]
You see?
The contract's legal, binding
and completely unbreakable,
even for you.
Of course, I always was a girl
with an eye for a bargain.
The daughter of the great sea king
is a very precious commodity.
But I might be willing
to make an exchange
for someone even better.
Eric, what are you doing?
Grim, I lost her once.
I'm not gonna lose her again!
Now, do we have a deal?
Ha! It's done then!
- [Ursula laughs]
- No! Oh, no!
Your Majesty.
Daddy.
- At last... it's mine.
- No.
- [cackles]
- You!
You monster!
Don't fool with me, ya little brat!
Contract or no, I'll blast... Ow!
- Why, you little fool.
- Eric! Eric, look out!
After him!
[pants]
Come on!
Ow!
Say goodbye to your sweetheart.
[shrieks]
[both scream]
Babies! My poor little poopsies.
[growls]
Eric, you've gotta get away from here.
No, I won't leave you.
[cackles]
[guttural laughter]
You pitiful, insignificant fools!
Look out!
Now I am the ruler of all the ocean!
The waves obey my every whim!
- Eric!
- [Eric screams]
The sea and all its spoils
bow to my power!
Eric!
[pants]
Oh! Oh!
[Ursula cackles]
So much for true love!
[screams]
[all moan]
[murmuring]
She really does love him,
doesn't she, Sebastian?
Mmm. Well, it's like
I always say, Your Majesty,
children got to be free
to lead their own lives.
You always say that?
[chuckles]
[sighs] Then I guess
there's just one problem left.
And what's that, Your Majesty?
How much I'm going to miss her.
[cheering]
[chef] Ah-ha!
[chef shouts]
[laughs] Yes!
Thank you. Thank you.
[whispers] I love you, Daddy.
[chorus] # Now we can walk
Now we can run
# Now we can stay all day in the sun
# Just you and me
# And I can be
# Part of your world
[chorus vocalizes]
www.moviesubtitles.org