Hi, I'm John Musker, one
of the co-writers, directors
and producers of the movie
you are about to witness.
And this is Ron Clements.
I'm a co-writer, director,
I guess a producer as well,
along with John, of this movie.
And I am Amy Pell,
co-producer of Aladdin,
and we want to welcome you on
our journey through the Arabian desert.
CLEMENTS: It's been, actually,
about over 10 years, I think,
since we actually worked on this movie,
so we will be commenting
on this from a distance,
but I think things will hopefully
come back as we start seeing them.
MUSKER: What we have here,
obviously, is our title sequence,
which we did over Alan Menken
and Howard Ashman's wonderful song
"Arabian Nights,"
and one of the conceits we
had when we made this sequence
was we tried to really make
it seem almost like one shot,
so we were disguising the
transitions from shot to shot.
So even here we go down into the palace,
and then we push toward the palace.
But it was too far to get all the
way to the palace in one shot,
as I recall, so we had to
kind of jump a little bit here.
Let's see… How did we do this?
CLEMENTS: Yeah,
there's a jump cut right here,
where the guy blows the flames.
MUSKER: We timed this to Alan's
big cymbal crash here, of course.
CLEMENTS: Oh, and there's our names.
That's exciting.
But, actually, there was a
much longer version of this song.
This is actually the shortened
version of Arabian Nights.
Originally, it was a much bigger
song, and for various reasons,
length reasons, we ended up
with just a small portion of the song.
MUSKER: The song was sung by Bruce Adler,
a great Broadway performer,
the spoken part here, of
course, by Robin Williams.
PELL: And when we originally had
the song, it was broken up into stanzas.
We revisited the narrator
throughout the film at one point.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, the
narrator originally was going
to play more of a role in the movie
and come back at various things.
MUSKER: The animation here
was done by Duncan Marjoribanks,
who also did the
character Abu the Monkey.
And he got done with the monkey in
time to have time to do something else.
So the narrator generally was
animated toward the end of the film.
CLEMENTS: I remember Duncan
very, very much wanted to do the narrator
and was bartering
anything he could do to get it.
PELL: And also, for Robin here,
we brought in different props for him.
MUSKER: Right, this was a
Jeffrey Katzenberg suggestion.
I had written some stuff, I
think, and Jeffrey didn't like it
and he said, "This is what
you gotta do, bring Robin in,"
"put him in a room full of junk"
"and have him improvise à la
Jonathan Winters or something."
CLEMENTS: So we did that.
He came in to do the narrator,
and we had tons of props
and it was like a Robin routine.
He actually probably
recorded about an hour of stuff
with the different props,
and what you have here is just a sampling
of the very best of
that recording session.
PELL: Even just looking at the lamp
brings me back to Richard Vander Wende,
who was our production
designer and brilliant at it.
But every detail, especially the lamp.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, Richard was a
perfectionist and is a perfectionist.
MUSKER: And a genius, I think.
PELL: Absolutely.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, yeah, very talented.
MUSKER: And we'll probably
be talking about the color scheme
as we go through the film.
There's a lot of ideas
in terms of the color
and how it's used and what
the individual colors represented.
But, in basic terms,
I think blue represented
water, which was good,
red represented heat,
which was always bad,
and I think then there was
gold, which was kind of bad
but was a little neutral,
and green was a good color.
You can see how that plays throughout.
This sequence, there
are some elements of this
that we were influenced by an early
draft of the script by Linda Woolverton,
who had a sequence
out in the desert like this,
and actually Don Yip, who is
a very talented, tall Dutchman,
story-boarded this sequence,
and a lot of the cinematics of this
Don created, as well as Rasoul
Azadani, our head of layout.
There's a scene coming
up that we think of Rasoul,
that's no longer in the movie.
But right here Jafar, for a long
time, used to say, "Rasoul Azadani."
CLEMENTS: To make the cave open up,
and then some people got concerned
that it might mean
something in Farsi or Arabic,
so we wound up having
to lose it unfortunately.
MUSKER: It always got a good
laugh at the employee screenings.
PELL: The Cave of Wonders is
our first CG element in the film,
and Steven Goldberg
was responsible for that.
MUSKER: Yeah, Steve Goldberg.
The rest of the treasure is
yours, but the lamp is mine.
CLEMENTS: And I think
this tiger's head that's here
is actually one of the first things of
character animation done digitally.
It was done that way
so that the tiger's head would
match the look of the backgrounds,
but it was all animated digitally.
[ECHOING RUMBLE]
MUSKER: T. Dan Hofstedt was
the animator on this thief character.
He did a great job.
Again, Richard Vander Wende
designed that tiger's head.
It was actually sculpted out of clay,
and they did a 3-D digital scan of it
to try and put it into the computer.
It was a giant behemoth of a head there
that they actually took
to a scanning place.
PELL: And we worked very hard to
make sure that it didn't feel separate
from the 2-D element,
so we worked very hard to make
it integrate into our 2-D world.
CLEMENTS: And Frank Welker,
who did the monkey sounds of Abu
and who also did the monkey
in Raiders of the Lost Ark,
which is how we got him. But he
also did the voice of the tiger here,
so that's two sides of Frank Welker.
PELL: He also did Rajah, the tiger.
CLEMENTS: He did. Right, right.
He did Rajah as well. Multitalented guy.
PELL: Very, yes.
MUSKER: Now we also
might mention here, Jafar.
The great animation
on Jafar is Andreas Deja,
one of the great animators
at the studio here,
who did Scar and
various other characters.
Iago here is done by Will
Finn, the very funny animator,
voiced by the inimitable
Gilbert Gottfried.
Jeffrey did give us a little
hard time with the voice.
[SHRILLY] "He sounds abrasive."
[NORMAL VOICE] And we're like,
"Well, that can be
entertaining in its own way."
PELL: Yes, there was concern
about it being too anachronistic.
CLEMENTS: Although after we
had cast Robin Williams as the Genie,
we felt we needed
something fairly strong early on
to just balance the film out a bit,
so I think we felt Gilbert helped
keep that sort of broad comedy aspect
and establish it early in the movie.
PELL: Jafar's voice was Jonathan Freeman,
a very talented actor.
MUSKER: Talented, and
a guy who didn't fit the…
He looks nothing like Jafar.
PELL: He's a nice, nice gentleman,
and a wonderful singer as well.
MUSKER: Right, terrific singer.
The voice of Aladdin here, Scott Weinger,
we went through a
couple of different voices,
and Scott really had a great
mix of just youthful exuberance
and cockiness, and likeability, appeal.
CLEMENTS: Howard
Ashman, the lyricist on the movie
who wrote the songs with Alan Menken,
actually died early on in
the beginning of this movie,
but he had written three songs before
he died that are still in the movie,
Arabian Nights, the
Genie's introductory song
and the Prince Ali song.
It's one of the cartoonier
movies that Disney's made
in terms of the features, and
it was designed to be cartoony
and it just seemed
to fit the tone of that.
Eric was the very first
animator on the movie,
and he had a lot of influence
on the style of the movie
and the Hirschfeld aspect, which
is a very fun, fluid way to draw,
very simple, very cartoony, I
think very fun for the animators.
So I think that lent itself to that, too,
that there was something
really fun about that.
And it's like, we are
making a cartoon, you know?
There's nothing wrong
with making a cartoon.
If you make a cartoon
well, cartoons can be great.
[SINGING] …snack, guys Rip him open
MUSKER: So this song was based
on a song that Howard and Alan did
called Babkak, Omar, Aladdin, Kasim,
which was about Aladdin
and his three buddies.
It was a very jaunty tune,
and it didn't really work
in the current storyline
'cause we'd cut those characters out.
But Ed Gombert, our head of story,
realized that, that would help us
do this sort of action-y set piece thing
in a much jauntier way.
So he dug up the song that
was already out of the movie
and said, "Why don't you use this as
a template and storyboard it to that?"
Even though the
lyrics didn't fit with this.
Then Tim Rice went back and rewrote
the lyrics to work with the idea here.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, we
were really struggling.
We had a few different versions that
just didn't seem like they were working,
and then Ed really solved the problem.
PELL: Also, here we
have Aladdin being the thief
And we spent many hours
discussing how do we still make him…
MUSKER: Yeah, make him morally
acceptable or likable or whatever.
PELL: Acceptable, absolutely.
MUSKER: The sort of Robin
Hood-ness of all this was important.
MAIN GUARD: Get him!
PELL: So the scene at
the end, after the song,
is imperative to answering that.
CLEMENTS: Right.
The scene with the two little urchins
and the bread that Aladdin has
stolen and the sharing with Abu,
and then he actually then
shares his bread with the urchins,
as does Abu, that really helped,
I think, for us to really
sympathize with Aladdin,
even though at the
beginning of the movie,
his moral character may
have a little loose edge to it.
But we realize it's just
circumstances that he can't help.
And that's also addressed in the
lyrics of the song here by Tim Rice,
as far as why Aladdin has no
choice but to live this kind of life.
MUSKER: This is the scene
that Amy was alluding to.
This scene was really put in
to soften Aladdin's character
and to make it seem that
he wasn't just out for himself,
but that his thievery…
That he had a soft heart
and that he was in his
own way sympathetic
to the plight of people less fortunate.
PELL: Well, he denies himself even here,
after working so hard
for this piece of bread.
MUSKER: As opposed to Abu,
who we said is a ruthless opportunist.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, Abu
really wants to eat that bread,
but even Abu can't bring himself
to go all the way after he sees
what Aladdin does.
MUSKER: He has to be
dragged into it by a better impulse.
PELL: He still had the humorous element,
but his heart gave over in the end.
CLEMENTS: At least he got a bite.
I think there's something satisfying that
at least Abu got a bite of that bread.
Ah, don't.
CLEMENTS: Now this is
an interesting bit coming up.
PELL: Right there.
CLEMENTS: Those two guys on screen…
The guy with the red beard,
who is kind of the roly-poly guy,
he actually resembles me quite a bit.
MUSKER: Yes, and the hatchet-faced guy
with the gray mustache is me,
John Musker, sort of
These are characters that Mike
Cedeno animated of us there.
CLEMENTS: And we actually
did the voices of the characters,
and it became a little
Hitchcockian cameo in the movie,
once again, that no one really
cared about except the staff enjoyed it,
and our relatives really,
really got a kick out of it.
And we've since tried to
do that in other movies,
somewhat less successfully, I
think, but it worked nicely here.
MUSKER: This whole aspect of
Aladdin as street rat and all that,
that was really pushed in the
rewrites by Ted Elliott and Terry Rossio.
I think that whole idea of
him being sort of an urchin
who really wanted to validate himself
was pushed even more strongly by them.
CLEMENTS: And this
scene with Prince Achmed,
I think, is a really critical thing in
terms of Achmed's humiliation of Aladdin.
Where he says, "You
are a worthless street rat"
"and basically that's
all you'll ever be,"
that really helps us understand
what Aladdin aspires to,
and that he is sort of
trapped by his station in life,
which is a theme that
goes throughout the movie.
All of the characters in the
movie are trapped in some way,
and this is how we establish that.
MUSKER: I was gonna say, we struggled
with this song moment here a little bit,
and I think, ultimately,
Alan came up with the idea
that it really would be a reprise,
because he didn't have enough
time to state a whole, fresh song here.
So he wanted to draw on the melody
that had already been established
and that was, I think, the right idea.
CLEMENTS: Yeah. Absolutely.
MUSKER: There just wasn't enough time.
CLEMENTS: Originally,
we had done a version
where he did a whole, complete song,
a different song,
and it just couldn't
sustain, at this point.
MUSKER: This palace, again,
Richard Vander Wende's design,
and Jeffrey did harass us about them
looking like bagels on
the top or something.
I've never been so insulted.
Oh, Prince Achmed.
You're not leaving so soon, are you?
Good luck marrying her off.
PELL: You also had an
underwear shot, which is almost…
CLEMENTS: Obligatory, yeah.
PELL: obligatory, right.
CLEMENTS: And a lot of people
have mentioned this doesn't make sense,
that the underwear in Rajah's
mouth has the hearts on it.
Because if you physically
ripped the prince's pants off,
it would be his pants, not his underwear.
PELL: It's funnier this way.
That's why we did it.
MUSKER: So Princess Jasmine,
Mark Henn was the animator,
a great animator who did Simba
and Belle in Beauty and the Beast.
And Rajah was done by Aaron Blaise,
who more recently directed
Brother Bear for Disney.
And the Sultan is Dave Pruiksma.
PELL: Also Mark Henn
and Aaron Blaise were both
in Florida at the Florida studios,
so it was a challenge to keep
all the characters on model.
I think that our staff was so
terrific in being able to do that,
so that whether it was
done in California or Florida,
they all look like the same
character throughout the film.
CLEMENTS: I think the Florida
studio was pretty new at this point,
and this was the first time, actually,
that we used some of the people
in Florida in the actual production.
Not only did they do Jasmine and Rajah,
but there's a couple of sequences
where they did everything in the movie.
PELL: I think the clean-up
staff needs a lot of credit,
and that was led by Vera Lanpher.
And Renee Holt was in charge of Jasmine.
MUSKER: And they were really
trying to get this calligraphic line,
this thick-and-thin
line to the characters
to make it fit with calligraphy
and the Hirschfeldian line
that Eric Goldberg had
really been pushing us toward.
CLEMENTS: There's no inking,
but it's a beautiful thick-and-thin line
that really feels like an ink line,
a beautiful calligraphic ink line.
MUSKER: This movie was
done on the CAP system,
the computerized ink and paint
system, so there are digital coloring used
and things to create an effect
of the multi-plane camera.
The auto-focus thing
and a lot of the reflections you
see in this sequence in the floor,
they were able to flop
the images in the computer
and sort of blur them out
and do all sorts of little mattes
and things like that to make
it look as rich as it does.
Between Richard Vander Wende
and Bill Perkins, the art director,
they were really cooking up ways
to soup up the production
value throughout this.
Originally, the parrot was
gonna have a British voice.
We wrote the parrot
to have a British voice,
so he went from
this very mellifluous, British thing to…
[MIMICKING PARROT SQUAWKING]
'Cause we thought it was a big contrast.
And then we saw Gilbert on something…
CLEMENTS: It was
Beverly Hills Cop II, I think.
Just a little bit he did in that,
but he made an impression.
And Douglas Seale does
the voice of the Sultan,
the sort of befuddled sultan.
I think he did a great job.
Also, in terms of Richard Vander Wende
and his color scheme,
basically we loved everything,
all of Richard's color ideas,
except possibly the outfit of Jafar.
The original outfit. I mean, he's
still basically in reds and blacks,
but the original outfit
was just bright red.
MUSKER: To go with his color scheme idea
of red being the color of evil.
In the desert, he had
him completely in red,
and we thought he looked
too much like a fire engine,
so we begged Richard
to give him some black.
CLEMENTS: He relented, but
that was about the only thing,
I think, where we questioned that.
But the use of color is just really
amazing through the whole movie.
PELL: It's not only
the color, but also lines.
When it's Jafar, it's elongated lines.
When you're with the
Sultan, it's more round, cuddly.
CLEMENTS: They are very few
straight lines in the whole movie,
which was part of the conceit of
this Arabian calligraphic approach.
Almost everything is
curves, except primarily Jafar.
MUSKER: We were
trying to go for an analogy
of she's escaping from prison here,
so we had the long shadows of
the cypress trees cast on the ground,
just to give you a
subliminal prison effect here,
when she's leaving.
This whole idea of her going
out into the city in disguise
came up more in the
rewrite, after an earlier version
of the story had gotten mauled kind of,
and we had to come up with a
different way to introduce the Princess
with Ted and Terry, again.
Ted Elliott and Terry Rossio,
who more recently did Pirates
of the Caribbean, wrote that.
They suggested her
really going out into the city
and mingling with the populace in
this kind of Roman Holiday moment
that we have here now,
which really did give us a nice way to
contrast the secluded
life of the Princess
with being out in the streets and
meeting this kid of the streets here.
Okay, Abu. Go.
Try this.
MUSKER: This is a slight
caricature of Zero Mostel here,
a little bit, that Dave Stephan animated.
[TAUNTING]
Why, you…
Get away from here, you cursed…
CLEMENTS: And Ellen
Woodbury did the Abu through this.
Goodbye.
-Nice going, Abu.
-[COOING]
MUSKER: We did let Abu have a few
little words of English here and there,
just to make him communicate.
Pretty lady, buy a pot.
No finer pot in brass or silver.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, we actually rigged this
up in live action. It was very tricky.
MUSKER: This was a very difficult scene.
It took a long time.
And a lot of it is what
we call "on-ones,"
which means Jasmine changes
every frame, so she doesn't strobe.
So it took a lot of beautiful
drawing by the clean-up department
to really carry it.
Mark Henn animates it.
CLEMENTS: Really beautiful
animation that Mark did
throughout this bit, and Nik Ranieri.
MUSKER: Yeah, Nik
Ranieri did those vendors
and this fire-breather here.
Nik, who also animated on Jafar,
and later… He had done
Lumiere in Beauty and the Beast.
CLEMENTS: And he did Hades
in Hercules, a memorable role.
Hello? Hello?
Oh, you must be hungry.
Here you go.
MUSKER: The voice of Jasmine
here, Linda Larkin, we loved
the musical quality in her voice.
She doesn't have a song,
but we thought her
voice was very musical.
CLEMENTS: She does sing.
MUSKER: We did have to fight for her,
'cause there were some
questions about her voice,
'cause she does have an unusual voice.
But I'm married to a woman
with an unusual voice,
so I voted for this one, and
I really like what Linda did.
PELL: There was a tendency to go
with what was known and comfortable,
and we really fought to have
a slightly different
sound for our female lead.
MUSKER: This is a little wacky, just
with the character design and whatnot,
'cause the guy on the left, his
hands are bigger than their torsos.
And Chris Wahl animated these guys,
but we were able to kind of cheat it.
CLEMENTS: People
from two different worlds.
MUSKER: It fits the
cartoony style of the movie.
This movie has a cartoonier style
than, really, most of the Disney films,
and it was really the Genie,
actually, that was designed first
then that design was reflected
pretty much in all the character designs.
But there was some question
about how cartoony you could go
and still maintain the
believability in the story,
but we went pretty much, I think,
as far as we felt that it was possible.
PELL: And Al Hirschfeld was
an extreme resource for us.
MUSKER: Because of Eric Goldberg
really pushing us in that direction.
He was a huge fan of Al Hirschfeld.
More on that later.
PELL: Eric Goldberg, who
designed and animated the Genie.
CLEMENTS: It's reflected
mostly in the Genie,
but it is really in all the
designs of the characters.
PELL: I want to mention Don Paul as well,
who was the head of effects,
and especially in a sequence like
this where you see all the effects.
MUSKER: Yeah, this is a
real effects showpiece of Don.
PELL: And if you look very closely,
the Persian influence on all
the effects is extraordinary.
CLEMENTS: People don't realize
there's character animators
who actually do the characters,
and effects animators do all
the other animation, like lightning
and spark and water
and fire and explosions.
MUSKER: The glow on
Jafar there, which is nice.
CLEMENTS: And Don
is a great effects animator
and did a wonderful job supervising
all the effects in the movie.
Once again, some fairly
bold color choices in this.
MUSKER: Yeah, they really
wanted to go, Richard and Bill,
for the magenta sky here.
So, this is your first time
in the marketplace, huh?
MUSKER: The animators,
like on Aladdin and Jasmine,
there's a number of
animators that worked on them
'cause there's so much footage,
so I think Tony de Rosa
did a bunch of these scenes
under Glen Keane's supervision.
Hmm. I'm a fast learner.
PELL: We also liked that Jasmine
was a strong, independent woman.
MUSKER: We did.
PELL: She chose to…
Whoa. Watch your head there.
Be careful.
MUSKER: We do try in this sequence, too,
to show that they both feel trapped,
they have this common
bond that they're trapped,
Aladdin and her golden palace…
CLEMENTS: Yeah, earlier,
there was the analogy
that Jasmine is like a bird in a cage,
and as we see her with the birds
and as the Sultan takes the bird
from her, puts it back in the cage.
And then they both talk
about, in a similar situation here,
how they are both trapped,
but in very different ways.
She's a princess and
he's kind of a street rat.
It's better than here.
You're always scraping for
food and ducking the guards.
You're not free to make your own choices.
-Sometimes you feel so…
-You're just…
-Trapped.
CLEMENTS: Glen Keane did a
bunch of the animation on Aladdin,
so he came up with this whole
little business here with the apple,
and rolling it off his arm and
popping it over with his elbow.
Which is used later in the movie
as a way that Jasmine recognizes Aladdin.
My father's forcing me to get married.
CLEMENTS: Very romantic
moment here, but a little comic relief
MUSKER: Counterpoint to it, yeah.
And we did show the movie to
Steven Spielberg after it was done.
He saw it at a screening,
we talked to him a little bit
and he said, yeah, whenever
things got too gooey in the movie,
always cut to the monkey.
He thought that was a good idea.
I don't know if he would still say that.
CLEMENTS: It's been our
experience that male leading men,
the straight leading men,
are harder to do in animation
than the women.
MUSKER: You can slightly
caricature the female movement
and look,
and the slight exaggeration
just makes it more appealing.
But when you do that with the
male figure, that slight exaggeration,
it's a little off-putting.
This character's name, I don't think
he's ever mentioned in the move,
but we called him Rasoul,
after our head of layout,
the mild-mannered Rasoul Azadani.
CLEMENTS: Although Rasoul is much nicer.
MUSKER: He is, yes.
He has better teeth.
Rasoul has really good teeth.
PELL: He's very talented
because of all the different
multi-planes in this movie.
MUSKER: Right, Rasoul has
such a great cinematic sense,
so a lot of, particularly
the action set pieces,
where the camera is,
the low eye-levels
in a lot of these shots
and where the camera was
stationed, the camera movement,
Rasoul was a huge
influence in shaping all that.
CLEMENTS: Rasoul was great
casting for this movie as head of layout,
since he is actually Iranian
and from Isfahan in Iran,
and really knows the architecture
and designs really, really well,
and actually went back
to Iran in the early stages
as we were visually developing
the movie, for research.
MUSKER: We did have a
discussion with Richard on that,
I remember, 'cause, yeah, there was a
fire going in the fireplace in the desert.
He's like, "That's the thematic idea."
"But, Richard, do we need the fire?"
He's like, "It's gotta be there."
"Okay, we'll put the fire in."
PELL: And if you notice,
again, here we are in the castle,
but we're in Jafar's part of it,
so it's the long lines, the deep red.
I can't breathe, Jafar.
CLEMENTS: Also, do you notice the
little jewels on Jafar and on Jasmine?
That's a little Richard touch.
They each wear a
jewel, as does the Sultan.
It's a very simple design,
but it beautifully makes this
feeling of a very shiny jewel effect
achieved in a very simple way.
What do you mean?
Sadly, the boy's sentence
has already been carried out.
CLEMENTS: Jasmine is
dressed in the bluish-green,
because she's good.
-By beheading.
-No.
PELL: And even the
cinematography reflects the characters
and the angles that you look.
Jafar is often from below.
MUSKER: I mean, the basic
Disney approach we grew up on
was to try and really
tell the story visually,
so that even without the
dialogue, you can follow the film,
and the camera movements and all that
would help communicate the story,
and that's what we really tried to do.
CLEMENTS: Particularly
in scenes like that,
that are really dialogue scenes
that could be done as two
characters just talking to each other.
There's a lot of thought
put into visual storytelling,
to let the visuals communicate.
So that you could turn the sound off
and still know what's
basically happening.
PELL: And I think Ron and John
deserve a lot of credit for that.
That's Ron Musker.
MUSKER: As others have known to call us.
Please, get the names right.
MUSKER: This was a multi-plane shot,
with all these things
moving in the foreground.
Although, again, it's
through the CAP system,
so all these different levels can
be composited in the computer.
So you've got this moving foreground
that's moving at a different speed.
It was a nightmare of registration.
We call it "registration" when
we have to fit a character"
to the background or
to another character,
and his wrists and
those stocks on the wall
were just very problematic
when they went to clean it up.
CLEMENTS: No one will give it a
second thought, but it was tough.
MUSKER: And the shadows falling over him…
Oh, this was a hard thing.
CLEMENTS: Duncan Marjoribanks
animated Abu in this section,
and I think one of his best scenes
is coming up right here, yeah.
MUSKER: Duncan always had
this thing about dressing in drag.
No, he didn't really, but he…
Whatever. He's a tall Canadian.
PELL: If you see Duncan,
he's a very manly, tall…
MUSKER: A manly, burly
lumberjack of a Canadian guy.
CLEMENTS: Duncan
also was the lead animator
on the crab in The Little Mermaid,
so this was his second sidekick for us.
PELL: He's a very big guy
who does very petite characters.
CLEMENTS: Well, then I think
he did the bad guy in Pocahontas,
just as a change of pace.
He got to do a large character.
MUSKER: This, who, actually,
we learn is Jafar in disguise,
was animated by Kathy Zielinski,
who is really good at quirky,
dark characters, villains.
She later did the villain in
Hunchback of Notre Dame.
PELL: And Kathy was pregnant during this.
MUSKER: Kathy was pregnant
during the making of this,
so she did her climatic scenes,
we'll see later in the film as
she was about to give birth,
so it gave an added sense of
urgency, I think, to the whole thing.
And Kathy, she had a thing
about teeth in her scenes.
She always said, "The
more teeth, the better."
Whoever has the gold makes the rules.
CLEMENTS: This is a great scene.
MUSKER: Ted Elliott and Terry Rossio
did a lot of the writing in this scene,
which has to do with the whole,
"Whoever has the gold makes the rules."
That was Ted and Terry's line.
So we had a little smoke
effect in the moonlight there,
just to keep it alive.
CLEMENTS: Big scope shots.
MUSKER: We didn't
have that many wider shots,
so we wanted to have some
in here before we cut in close.
CLEMENTS: Probably the reason we
didn't have more scope shots like that
is our length problem,
which is traditionally
we've always got more
movie than we have time to tell,
so we're constantly
looking for ways to shorten it.
Certainly that was
true of Aladdin, I think.
It tends to be a fairly fast-paced movie,
and it would be nice to say
that was totally an artistic choice.
I would say somewhat an artistic choice,
but somewhat, we just had
more story than we had time.
PELL: We would have to have meetings
where we'd go through it editorially
and say, "We have to cut out
a second here, a second there,"
'cause, of course,
that's a lot of animation
and we had to fit within
a certain time period.
CLEMENTS: And animation is expensive,
so we were always looking for
anything that we might be able to trim.
PELL: That big scope
scene was great, though,
in showing the effects again,
and also, if you look,
you can see the Persian…
MUSKER: Yeah, the little spirals
are done in a Persian calligraphy.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, Don Paul
really brought that consistency,
so that even things like smoke and fire,
they still always follow
the same design elements.
PELL: Here is another of our
computer-generated elements,
the Persian carpet.
MUSKER: Yeah, it was actually
animated by Randy Cartwright,
and he would do it on paper,
actually, and then Tina
Price would help wallpaper
our elaborate pattern on it
to give it the Persian effect.
So it was a combination of
hand-drawn and CG, in a way.
CLEMENTS: Once again, one of
the early uses of CG for a character,
and it really could not have
been done any other way.
It was a perfect use of that,
'cause no artist could have
drawn that pattern frame by frame.
MUSKER: Just like any character,
there's a lot of Randy in this.
Even though it's just a
carpet, it's like a playing card.
But the way it sneaks around
here and the playfulness of it
and the entertainment
sense of it, that's really…
As well as the storyboards
here, Ed Gombert did that really…
CLEMENTS: But it is really just,
"I'm giving personality to a rectangle."
The carpet is a rectangle
and he doesn't speak, so it's
totally a mimed performance.
It really shows a good
demonstration of the animator's art,
where if you give something
a personality, it comes alive.
MUSKER: These were the first
scenes we did of the carpet in the movie.
Every character, you
pick a certain sequence
that's going to establish its…
It may not necessarily be its first
sequence that appears in the film,
but in this case, this was the
first stuff we did on the carpet.
CLEMENTS: This was
one of the first sequences to
go into production on the whole movie.
MUSKER: Right, 'cause it gave us all the…
You like to play off one
character off another,
so this gave us a chance to play
the monkey off Aladdin, off the carpet.
PELL: Also, Tina Price was
experimenting with the texture mapping
to see how we could make it work.
MUSKER: Yeah, on the production system.
PELL: On the production system.
CLEMENTS: With anything new
like that, there is a lot of question,
like, "Can it be done?"
"And if it can be done, is it viable
within the production system?"
MUSKER: We did have to sell
Jeffrey on the carpet 'cause he was like,
"Do I want to pay all that
money for a bunch of squiggles?"
I remember was his quote. But we're like,
"When you see it, you'll like
the squiggles. Trust us on this."
CLEMENTS: Yeah, there was
also some question for a while
whether the carpet should
talk or the monkey should talk.
Because in storyboards
they weren't really coming off
the way they do now in the finished film,
and we had to say, "Trust
us, when they're animated,"
"there's going to be an added
dimension that you're not getting yet."
And, certainly, once
the carpet was animated,
it was much more obvious
that the effect was gonna work.
PELL: This, also, is a sequence
that shows Richard's use
of color and the contrast.
MUSKER: And Richard did
design the walls of this place.
I remember him looking at
crystallized caves and stuff.
He had stills of real caves,
a very interesting thing.
This sequence, because it
was one of the first in production,
there are some Aladdins that
were animated very early on,
and then had to be cleaned up
when we changed the model later on.
So you'll see some variation
in the way he's drawn,
if you're really looking closely.
CLEMENTS: There definitely is
a Raiders of the Lost Ark element,
and when we talked to Steven Spielberg,
we actually referred to that,
were a little apologetic about that,
and he said, "I stole all
that from other movies."
It's like, that's the way it works.
Abu! No!
This is really an effects tour de force
that we're getting into here once
again with Don Paul and his crew.
Because this was one of the first
sequences to go into production,
it had the luxury that
you really could go all-out
in terms of effects.
MUSKER: So it's a combination of
hand-drawn and computer effects.
The lava that you see on the ground
is CG bubbles and texture there,
but there's other hand-drawn elements.
PELL: And James Tooley did these.
MUSKER: James Tooley coming up on this…
CLEMENTS: Roller coaster ride.
PELL: He did the
computer-generated images in this.
MUSKER: And Ted Kierscey
did a lot of the lava here,
the hand-drawn elements, the
lava explosions. Ted did a lot of that.
PELL: And we sent the layout
group and the effects group on…
MUSKER: We were trying to get
Holt to sign that shot, but it's gone.
PELL: They went on a roller coaster
ride with a camera and took pictures, too.
CLEMENTS: Rasoul actually
went to Magic Mountain
through this part, to do research.
MUSKER: That's an amusement park here.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, in California.
-'Cause the feeling was to be…
-MUSKER: He left the lens cap on.
CLEMENTS: He had to go through
twice because he left the lens cap on.
But we really wanted this to be kind
of a roller coaster ride for the audience.
Some of these effects
are pretty standard now,
but at the time they were innovative
and nothing like that had
ever been done before.
This is probably the biggest
effects sequence in the movie.
I always liked this shot of the tiger in,
and in terms of Aladdin's cue,
I think that the music
through that is really good.
MUSKER: Yeah, Alan
Menken did the underscore
for the movie as well as the songs,
so this gave him a chance to
strut his action-adventure stuff here.
CLEMENTS: Two Academy
Awards, for both Song and Score.
First give me the lamp.
[MANIACAL LAUGHTER]
CLEMENTS: We didn't talk earlier
about that first shot of the lamp.
How many times we redid
that first shot of the lamp.
MUSKER: I don't know what the
problem was, but it took… Oh, that.
This one, too, when
he was handing it off,
took a lot, but I can't remember why.
PELL: That was a discussion
about the close-up of his eyes,
of Aladdin's eyes.
How to get at a more
emotional moment in here.
Just by adding that close-up,
it added just what was needed.
[ROARING]
MUSKER: We wanted this
contrast after all that racket
to have this moment of near
silence while the track disappears.
I… Where is it?
No.
No!
CLEMENTS: So this scene actually was one
of the last scenes added in the movie.
It wasn't there for a long time.
It was a controversial scene.
I think Jeffrey wanted this
scene particularly because
he felt we'd been away from
Jasmine and the Sultan too long
and we needed to get back to that.
At the time, I think, because we
were in such pressure on length,
we weren't sure it was necessary.
But in retrospect, I kind of feel
like it was probably a good idea
-just to bring that thread back in.
-MUSKER: Remind us of her story.
PELL: And I think more so this segment
is where you see Aladdin
change in his design
'cause this was the
earliest in production.
And Aladdin started out
looking a little younger,
and we realized once Jasmine was
designed and was looking so spiffy
that she wouldn't be attracted
to a young-looking Aladdin,
so we aged him up.
CLEMENTS: Originally,
we were thinking of him
as kind of a Michael J. Fox-type.
And then Jeffrey said,
"No, he's Tom Cruise,"
and we kind of went through a
little bit of a Tom Cruise makeover.
Of course, there's a lot
of makeovers nowadays,
-but that was hard.
-[PELL LAUGHING]
PELL: It wasn't an extreme makeover.
CLEMENTS: But the cleanup people
had to remake him in this section.
And here he comes, the Genie of the Lamp.
MUSKER: And Eric Goldberg,
the lead animator on the Genie,
who designed the Genie
and helped sell the concept,
really pushed us in this… Al Hirschfeld,
the noted caricaturist
of The New York Times,
Eric was a huge fan of his
and he really was influenced
by that in designing the Genie,
and that fed into the other
designs of the film as well.
CLEMENTS: I think Robin Williams…
One of the first ideas
that we had on the movie was actually
that Robin Williams could
be the voice of the Genie,
and it was a big question of whether
we would be able to get him or not.
We actually wrote the first version
of the script with Robin in mind.
A lot of people wonder, "How
much of Robin was ad-libbed?"
And the truth is not a single word.
It was all written almost to the syllable
and he followed the script exactly.
MUSKER: He's lying through his teeth.
CLEMENTS: It actually was
written to begin with in a Robin form,
but then Robin would
take the script as written
and do it a few times, and
then start just playing with it
and improvising and coming
up with so much material,
so much great material, of course.
Isn't that the Governor of California?
MUSKER: The Governator? Yeah.
Well, there were
discussions at the beginning,
how close, when Robin
does his celebrity voice,
should we caricature that person?
At first, we were more reticent,
and then we realized,
upon prodding from Eric,
I think, that's part of the
fun of all this, even though…
CLEMENTS: No one will
know who Ed Sullivan is.
PELL: Yes, it doesn't matter.
They're just a funny character.
CLEMENTS: But, yeah,
we found people laughed
even if they didn't get the references.
MUSKER: And they could
understand the cash register,
but they might not get Groucho
Marx here, or You Bet Your Life.
So Robin singing here
was a new thing for him.
I don't believe he had ever sung.
Well, no, Popeye, he had sung,
but kind of the narrow
band of musicality.
PELL: It wasn't the thing he
was most comfortable with.
CLEMENTS: We were
thinking, sure, Robin can sing
'cause he can imitate anything,
so all he has to do is imitate a singer,
but he was a little
nervous about the singing
and really worked hard on it.
MUSKER: We worked with David
Friedman, our musical director.
Robin would rehearse in the
evenings after shooting all day
and doing test footage for Hook,
where he was hung on wires and exhausted.
He was staying at Barry Levinson's
house in Beverly Hills, I think,
and we would go there at 9:00
or 10:00 at night with the piano,
and he'd be, "No, go ahead. That's fine."
CLEMENTS: He'd drag in just
looking completely exhausted,
like the last thing he ever wanted
to do was rehearse these songs,
but then he pulled this
energy from somewhere
and he'd be great.
MUSKER: He threw himself into it,
and the lyrics on this song are so great,
Howard Ashman lyrics,
just one gag after
another on these lines.
It plays with food. Howard's
lyrics often had fun with food jokes,
baklava and all this.
PELL: I also think one of the ways that
you made Robin feel more comfortable
would be to say,
"Sing it with an accent."
-Sing it again with a different accent.
-MUSKER: He could shift personas.
We had a little section
where he's a western guy
and he was Cab Calloway.
CLEMENTS: It was the
same thing as the dialogue,
he would sing it different each time
and try different things
each time he sang it.
PELL: We should also mention Danny Troob.
MUSKER: Danny Troob's
orchestrations on this, and really…
CLEMENTS: Throughout the
whole movie, but this is some of the…
MUSKER: The original demo
of this was just a piano track,
and then Danny Troob went wild
with the big, brassy sound of this thing.
It became bigger in scale,
and so the visuals had to come
up to the scale of his orchestra.
PELL: The music talent was amazing.
Between Tim Rice
and Howard Ashman and Alan Menken
and David Friedman and Danny Troob,
we really had an incredible,
incredible team on this show.
-This took a lot of animation.
-[CHUCKLING]
And this was the first
sequence we did complete,
and it served as kind of motivation
for all the animators on the picture
because it's so energetic
and just works so well.
CLEMENTS: And it got shown
outside of the studio a little bit.
I know that it was screened
at CalArts and other places.
And I think it got a great reaction,
and just the reaction to this sequence
really was encouraging to everybody,
that this whole idea might actually work.
MUSKER: We struggled
with the end of the song, too,
trying to get the
appropriate button for it.
I think it was Eric who
just, "Just forget it."
"Just stick an applause sign in.
He's so shameless, it's possible."
I'm like, "You know what?
You're right. That's the way to do it."
Ah, almost.
MUSKER: Kids in the audience,
that's William F. Buckley.
Like?
Ah, rule number one,
I can't kill anybody.
So don't ask.
Rule number two.
MUSKER: And he does
Peter Lorre coming up here,
but in this case, we just made him
look like a big grotesque guy, and not…
You have a little Yiddish there.
You got the whole shebang there.
Eric had to explain to us the
Yiddish, us Catholic yo-yos
that don't know what ponems are.
Other than that, you got it.
-Hmm.
-Oh!
CLEMENTS: And this Robert De Niro bit
that the Genie goes
into here was a lot longer,
and Robin was having
so much fun with this.
It would have been
funny to use the whole bit
'cause he went on this extended rant
that was one of the most
hilarious things I've ever seen.
But we couldn't use the whole bit,
but I think we still used enough of it
that you get it pretty well.
Did you rub my lamp?
Did you wake me up?
MUSKER: Robin's a
friend of Robert De Niro.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, he had just done…
What was the film with Robert De Niro?
PELL: Awakenings.
CLEMENTS: Awakenings. Right.
So he had Robert De Niro on the brain.
MUSKER: We did see this film
with Martin Scorsese in New York,
and were watching his reaction
as this was going to come up
and he was laughing quite a bit.
So we thought it was okay that we had…
He was amused that it
was Robert De Niro there.
PELL: I think it's important,
while we're in the Sultan's castle,
while it's still under
the Sultan's reign,
that you look at the color and the shapes
-of the pillars and the backgrounds.
-MUSKER: The background painting.
CLEMENTS: This background
is one of the most beautiful
backgrounds in the movie.
Ian Gooding, who we've
worked with on other films as well,
painted this background.
MUSKER: Jasmine's outfit,
this mint greenish outfit,
came from Persian miniatures.
It was Richard's suggestion
to use that. We liked it. Of course Amy,
who's sitting here, she won't mention it,
but she gave us such a hard
time about that bare midriff,
but ultimately she…
CLEMENTS: This has sort of
become a fashion statement.
PELL: And I think you did it.
-You affected fashion from…
-MUSKER: Yeah, all these younger…
My daughter now has the
bare midriff that I can't stand.
PELL: That's right. It's because of you.
MUSKER: I should've listened to you.
-[ALL LAUGHING]
-Boy, was I wrong.
I had gotten that lamp.
"I will have the power
to get rid of you."
MUSKER: When Gilbert did this imitation,
I couldn't believe how accurate that was.
[CHUCKLING]
Yes, that was Gilbert's tour de force,
him imitating Linda Larkin as Jasmine.
Only until she finds a chump husband.
Then she'll have us banished.
Or beheaded.
BOTH: Eww!
MUSKER: That's our
homage to Lucille Ball there.
What if you were the chump husband?
What?
Okay, you marry…
MUSKER: When we
recorded Gilbert, as I recall,
they had to back away the microphones
'cause he's a diminutive
guy, but a powerful performer.
I become the sultan.
-The idea has merit.
-Yes, merit. Yes.
And then we drop papa-in-law
and the little woman off a cliff.
Yaaah!
CLEMENTS: The guys
really enjoyed this laughing bit.
They actually recorded that
with the two of them together.
MUSKER: They would laugh
for about 15 minutes straight.
[CHUCKLING] They just went on and on.
MUSKER: This is our oasis sequence.
This is one of our simpler
sequences, arguably,
in that we didn't have a lot of effects
-and it was a little simpler.
-CLEMENTS: Rasoul was really happy
'cause the same background
is used over and over and over.
But its fine, and it saved us some money,
and it's a nice background,
so it looks great.
Now, about my three wishes.
CLEMENTS: This was, there
again, Ted and Terry's thing
of how they could get out of
that thing and not use up a wish.
It solved a big problem.
In the earlier version of Aladdin,
we had the idea of unlimited wishes,
which is actually the way it
is in the Arabian Nights story,
which was the idea that
once you get a genie,
you can just wish for as
many things as you want.
The good thing about that is
from a visual fantasy standpoint,
you can do a lot.
You can do anything you
want, as long as you want.
But I think rightfully, in terms
of the adjustments to the story,
the three wishes seemed
better and became important,
but the challenge was then to
figure out ways within the three wishes
that we could still get all
of the fantasy and magic.
By going with three
wishes, it raised the stakes,
so each wish was really important.
It gave a rising action to
the movie where the climax…
When you're down to your last
wish, it would have more import.
The ending wouldn't work if
he could have a million wishes.
The ending really became more powerful
when he only had one left to use.
MUSKER: He can't wish for more wishes,
that was one of the rules, so
you couldn't get around it that way.
Such a thing would be
greater than all the magic
and all the treasures…
CLEMENTS: The question
with the Genie, as broad as he is,
I think we wanted the audience to feel
that this really meant something to him.
His freedom was really important.
I think Robin did a good job of
selling the sincerity of the things,
when the Genie had to be sincere.
-This is a great bit.
-[CHUCKLING]
Robin threw that in,
that little Pinocchio bit.
MUSKER: And Eric really picked up on it.
PELL: And it got so…
The laughter was so
strong the first preview
that we actually had to
add a few seconds to it.
MUSKER: You're right.
CLEMENTS: There were
several places like that,
which I guess is a good problem to have,
but there were several
cases after the first preview
where the audience laughed
so hard at certain things,
you missed huge stretches of dialogue.
So we had to try to open things up,
so you could at least get some of it.
And this hair. Wow.
And her smile… [SIGHS]
Ami.
C'est l'amour.
But she's the princess.
To even have a chance, I'd have to be…
Hey, can you make me a prince?
CLEMENTS: This is actually
some of the first Aladdin animation
done in the Tom Cruise mode,
as I remember, that this was
where he got his makeover.
PELL: So we just passed…
MUSKER: Sebastian making a cameo?
PELL: You try to have some inside jokes.
CLEMENTS: And then Alan threw
in a little homage to Under the Sea
in the underscore, too, which
helped the audience get it.
MUSKER: In every
animated film we've done,
we've tried to find an angle
that makes it better to do an
animation than a live action.
Certainly in these days of digital stuff,
that line has gotten
blurrier and blurrier.
But certainly then we said, "How
can we do the Genie in a way"
"that they wouldn't
have done in any of the"
"live-action film adaptations of it?
What can we do with that character,"
"as well as others like the
carpet, that you just wouldn't do?"
So that's why we really thought
Robin was ideal, with his mimicry,
his speed, his quickness,
his improvisational ability.
It's great to have an
improviser in animation
because the voice is
always recorded first,
so whatever he comes up with,
we can write around and write to.
CLEMENTS: But it was risky,
too, and I think we knew that
'cause we knew we were a
little bit jumping off the cliff.
Because in order for that to
work, the film had to be a comedy
and it had to have a tone that
was a little bit looser, I think,
than any Disney film that
had been done up to that point.
GENIE: He's got the outfit.
He's got the elephant.
But we're not through yet.
Hang on to your turban, kid.
We're gonna make you a star.
CLEMENTS: So if you look
closely, you can see the Beast there.
We're just passing him now,
from Beauty and the Beast.
MUSKER: Rewind that and look at it,
you'll find the Beast in that pile of toys
that he just stacked up there.
A solution to the problem
with your daughter.
Awk. The problem with your daughter.
Oh, really?
Right here.
CLEMENTS: I think Rasoul was in
charge of any of the Arabic writing,
-like on this scroll.
-MUSKER: Is it real? I don't remember.
CLEMENTS: I don't
think the scroll is real,
but there are places where
we do have real Arabic writing,
and we were always nervous
that there might be something said
that someone in Iran might
read and be concerned about, yes.
"A princess must then be wed to…"
Hmm. Interesting.
What? Who?
The royal vizier.
Why, that would be me.
CLEMENTS: No, I don't think that's
genuine Arabic writing. [CHUCKLING]
MUSKER: No, I think it might…
Maybe Rasoul did it.
I don't remember now.
We have our Don Paul effects here
with the squiggles in the snake's eyes.
I will order the princess to…
But you're so old.
The princess will marry me.
MUSKER: I did do a
caricature of this scene
with Ron and I as the Sultan and Jafar,
talking about making
changes to the movie.
CLEMENTS: Oh, yeah.
MUSKER: Now this is this
great song that Howard and Alan…
Howard did write this new
song for this version of Aladdin,
and threw everything from
every Macy's Day Parade he could
into the whole production value of it.
CLEMENTS: We looked at Cleopatra
and other things for inspiration.
MUSKER: There was originally a long intro
that we cut out and we
went right to the song.
PELL: When we recorded
this, Robin Williams came in
and he made up a song
called Prince Jeffrey.
MUSKER: Oh, yeah, that's right.
CLEMENTS: Oh, yes, that's right.
We should get that.
PELL: And he was
making it up on the spot.
It was so impressive.
[GENIE SINGING] Prince Ali, fabulous he
CLEMENTS: Yeah, this was Howard Ashman.
This was, I think, the only
song we used in the movie
that was written after Howard
had gotten sick, but before he died.
But it's one of the best songs.
Even though Howard was very
sick when he wrote this song,
he did a fantastic job on it.
[SINGING] Prince Ali,
mighty is he Ali Ababwa
CLEMENTS: Sort of a press agent.
The Genie is Aladdin's press agent
and is selling him to
the people of Agrabah.
MUSKER: We divide the
movie up, Ron and I do.
When we are directing it,
we pick different sequences
in the film, so Ron did this one.
For example, I had done Friend Like Me,
this was Ron's tour de force here.
CLEMENTS: We both
got to do one Genie song.
Has he got a zoo I'm telling you
It's a world-class menagerie
CLEMENTS: I'm sure all kids
know who Ethel Merman is,
-but this is the Genie as Ethel Merman.
-[CHUCKLING]
Robin would pretty much come up
with those different
personalities himself,
and then we'd find visuals to go with it.
You can see that Jasmine is not shallow
-like a lot of..
-MUSKER: We are.
[SINGING] And to view
them he charges no fee
He's generous So generous
He's got slaves He's
got servants and flunkies
MUSKER: The lyrics to this are great.
But the production value
was, yeah, a slight nightmare.
PELL: Yes, this was a
major, major sequence
that kept everyone busy for a long time.
MUSKER: Many, many
animators worked on this.
PELL: But worked out brilliantly.
CLEMENTS: Still one
of the earlier things done
in the movie because it was a song.
Heard your princess
Was a sight lovely to see
And that, good people, is why
MUSKER: The reflections in the
floor, that production is really cool.
CLEMENTS: Howard always
loved these little lyric things
where you go through a string of things,
and that's very Howard in
terms of these quick images.
Yeah, lightning quick.
PELL: The list song.
CLEMENTS: Like Under
the Sea, where he lists
all the different band of characters
and of fish.
Absolutely marvelous.
[CLEARS THROAT]
Your Majesty…
PELL: Prince Ali was
such big production values,
and our production manager, Alice Dewey,
really helped coordinate
all of it to get it done.
I mean, that's true of the whole movie.
MUSKER: One of the ways
is, in a sequence like this
now playing, obviously
it's fewer characters,
we didn't have tones on the characters.
We did have shadows,
but we tried to restrict the amount
of effects in a scene like this.
Just sneak as many as
we could get away with in.
CLEMENTS: It was really a
challenge 'cause budget-wise,
we were on a pretty strict budget,
particularly for the
early part of the movie.
And so it was really trying to
watch everything and pick our spots,
and Alice and Amy and
everyone really helped
in terms of putting it where it counted
and in the most effective way possible.
MUSKER: This is, yes, our
Masterpiece Theater sequence
where we insisted on only getting
the most elevated gags possible in here.
PELL: One of my favorite gags
is here, where Brian Ferguson
-animates Iago clunking in.
-MUSKER: This one coming up here?
PELL: Yes, the one coming up.
CLEMENTS: With the little Sultans?
PELL: The little Sultans
around his head, yeah.
MUSKER: Yeah, Brian
Ferguson, another Canadian,
tall, eccentric Canadian animator.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, this was Brian.
Out of the way. I'm coming in to land.
Jafar, watch this.
-Spectacular, Your Highness.
-That was lovely.
MUSKER: That's fun with the
voice actors, like on Douglas Seale,
when we just had him ad-lib all his…
[WHOOPING] Flying around.
It's just fun for an actor, I
think, on the recording stage
'cause they can be so free
with their improv-y type stuff.
-I don't trust him, Sire.
-Nonsense.
One thing I pride myself on, Jafar,
I'm an excellent judge of character.
Oh, excellent judge. Yeah, sure. Not!
CLEMENTS: Even when we did that,
I think we thought it would be David.
MUSKER: An homage to Wayne's World.
I think Mike Myers
later sued the studio for…
No, he didn't really.
CLEMENTS: But that was something…
PELL: It was a concern.
MUSKER: It was an issue, yeah.
Would it be too topical? Fortunately,
it still is as alive today as it ever was.
Isn't it?
PELL: Not. MUSKER: Not.
-[ALL CHUCKLING]
-Yeah, right, there you go.
I do like her standing up
to him, and all these guys…
CLEMENTS: I like this scene
of them all being awkward.
MUSKER: I think,
actually, this was influenced
slightly by The Dick Van Dyke Show,
if any of you know the one
with the dance hall sequence.
It's a long story, but check
your Dick Van Dyke DVDs
and you'll see what I'm talking about.
I think it's time to say
goodbye to Prince Abubu.
MUSKER: It was fun
coming up with malaprops,
or just different names for him.
ALADDIN: What am I gonna do?
MUSKER: Here's our Rodney
Dangerfield moment coming.
CLEMENTS: I think people still
know who Rodney Dangerfield is.
I think this is a fun
little bit with the chess,
the two of them playing chess.
MUSKER: Like in a sequence
like this, we wrote this line,
"I can't believe it.
I'm losing to a rug."
But he did it as Rodney,
and that was Robin's
addition to the scene. The line.
CLEMENTS: And same as this.
He did this actually as
John Wayne, as well as Jack.
MUSKER: Yeah, and
then in the editing room,
we had things to play with.
No way.
MUSKER: And I think we
made a good choice with Jack.
CLEMENTS: And this is my
favorite gag that never got a laugh.
I thought, "Oh, this will be
funny, he turns into a lamp."
For whatever reason, no laugh ever.
But it's a sure thing.
MUSKER: I will take
responsibility for that.
I thought it would be funny.
CLEMENTS: A lamp on
your head is a sure thing.
MUSKER: How could
you be funnier than that?
Okay, I'm gonna go see her.
I just… I gotta be smooth…
PELL: I also like the
chess game in the beginning
because it establishes the
friendship between the Genie and…
MUSKER: Yeah, a little
relationship between them.
PELL: And that continues in the end.
MUSKER: There's a canopy over her bed,
which is really meant
to echo the birdcage
that's out in her garden, 'cause we
had this whole visual analogy going
that Jasmine was a trapped
bird waiting to get free.
And Bill Perkins, who was
our art director, really came up
with that visual idea of really trying…
Even within the palace,
that she was confined and she
was really looking for a way out.
That was Bill's idea,
and he, throughout the film, looked
for visual things to support the story.
CLEMENTS: Now we get to this…
MUSKER: Urban myth.
CLEMENTS: The urban
myth, the controversial thing
where there's a little bit of
Aladdin ad-libbing offstage.
Many, many people believe that he says,
"Good teenagers take off their
clothes," and he does not say that."
We did not record that.
We would not record that.
But it is an urban myth.
It actually is an ad-lib that he…
MUSKER: Yeah, Scott
Weinger, the actor, actually said,
"Good tiger. Take off. Scat. Go."
And it was all ad-Liby, improv
stuff he did to fill in a gap
because we had, in fact,
lengthened the scene,
and we needed more
dialogue to continue through it.
So that's really what he's saying.
CLEMENTS: And
Jasmine looks at him kind of
strangely right after you hear that line,
but the reason she
looks at him strangely is
because his turban has come
off, so she's actually thinking,
"He looks kind of familiar," in that
brief glimpse of him without his turban."
It has nothing whatsoever
to do with what he just said.
-Punctual.
-Punctual?
-Sorry.
-Uh, beautiful.
-Nice recovery.
Hmm.
I'm rich, too, you know.
Yeah.
MUSKER: I like the interplay
between the characters.
We were really trying to
build up the romance here,
but this playful thing
between the two of them,
and yet her being this
strong, independent…
CLEMENTS: And then
Genie as the bee adding
little comic buttons within the…
A prince like you.
CLEMENTS: This is nice animation.
Stuffed shirt, swaggering
peacock I've met.
Mayday! Mayday!
JASMINE: Just go jump off a balcony!
-What?
-Stop her. Stop her!
-Want me to sting her?
-Buzz off.
Okay, fine. But remember…
MUSKER: I seem to recall Robin
doing a few off-color ad-libs here
and there that we did not use.
-CLEMENTS: Not just in this part.
-[LAUGHING]
Throughout the movie there
was a lot of, "You can't use that."
Just some prize to be won.
You should be free to
make your own choice.
I'll go now.
-No!
-What? What?
How… How are you doing that?
It's a magic carpet.
CLEMENTS: So here, I
know we discussed it a lot,
we wanted to make sure
the audience would
get the connection here,
so we staged it…
MUSKER: We tried to parallel the staging.
Yeah, the earlier scenes.
CLEMENTS: He says, "Do you trust me?"
Sure. Do you trust me?
CLEMENTS: And then we cut
to her exactly like we did before,
and then we cut to him
exactly like we did before.
Do they get it? I don't know.
MUSKER: And it's starting to dawn on her,
"I think there's
something going on here."
CLEMENTS: Just a connection is made.
MUSKER: This song we're moving into,
A Whole New World was written
by Alan with his new collaborator,
Tim Rice, and it was a
really big moment, I think,
for Alan to write without
Howard Ashman in this case.
And Tim really did a wonderful
job on the lyrics in this,
and the feeling of this expansive…
We always envisioned
a big, open-vista, visual
set piece here, but we didn't know
what the musical statement would be.
PELL: And they were honored
with the Oscar for this song.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, and Chris
Montan, who was the music…
MUSKER: The maven of music.
CLEMENTS: in terms of this, I know.
He was the first one to hear this,
and he told us before
we ever heard the song
that they had come up with
something amazing and memorable,
and it was gonna be
great, and he was right.
PELL: I think the
animation in this sequence
is beautiful. The backgrounds,
which Kathy Altieri was in
charge of all the backgrounds.
The whole background
team was just so talented.
MUSKER: It was a
difficult movie to paint,
but they really rose to the challenge.
CLEMENTS: I remember
her describing this one scene,
we wanted the effect of ice-cream clouds.
MUSKER: Yeah, the snow-cone effect,
and Scott Santoro's animation…
Or was it Ed? It was Scott Santoro.
PELL: And also, as you said before,
even though you have romantic moments,
there's humor throughout
that cuts it every time
it gets a little too sappy.
MUSKER: Yeah, and Lea
Salonga did the vocals on this song.
Linda Larkin does not
sing, or at least sing
with the kind of range you got here.
So Lea did an absolutely fantastic
job with her soaring soprano.
CLEMENTS: Lea Salonga of Miss Saigon.
I guess she won a Tony for that.
MUSKER: Again, Brad Kane
is doing the vocals for Aladdin.
Every moment red-letter
BOTH: I'll chase them anywhere
PELL: And yet they match
the speaking voices beautifully.
It's seamless.
CLEMENTS: And there's Aladdin
doing that little apple thing again.
-Once again. Now she knows.
-MUSKER: Now it's like,
-"He's that guy."
-CLEMENTS: Now she's sure.
That's where we'll be A thrilling chase
MUSKER: I got to direct this song,
so I did try and make this thing
work at the end. Time it to the music
so that this little thing
on the carpet there,
just works with the little twinkle
and the little fireworks introduced
to give it a little button at the end.
Transition into the…
They've gone around the world,
and they've wound up
in the Forbidden City.
It's The Last Emperor.
You're gonna see Bernardo Bertolucci
climb over the back of that in a second.
I think there's fun stuff
on the carpet in this
that Randy did that's a counterpoint.
Randy Cartwright animating the carpet.
Just little reactions.
CLEMENTS: Some nice
interplay with Aladdin and Jasmine.
MUSKER: Yeah, great
stuff between the two of them.
Really good expressions.
PELL: This sequence, even
in rough pencil animation,
was just beautiful to watch.
The acting in it was so clear.
-And Mark Henn…
-MUSKER: Mark Henn and Glen.
PELL: and Glen Keane did
just a beautiful job on this.
The truth?
MUSKER: I like this next
scene, "Yeah, come on."
The very distinctive reaction on her
that I really love, the way Mark did that.
I sometimes dress as a commoner, um,
to escape the pressures of palace life.
MUSKER: And Scott's vocal performance
in this, I think, is really fun.
And as well as Linda's.
All the elements came together,
and then the fireworks just
gave this neat visual thing.
We had to go through this
nightmare of coordination,
though, that I think Ron was
more involved in than I was,
even though I think I did this sequence.
"Okay, we'll have blue in this scene,
"then we have to decide. This is red."
And it's like, "Just let them do it."
But somehow it had to get mapped out,
which was a slight horror, as I recall.
'Cause a lot of them, the
transitions went over cuts,
which was the big nightmare.
CLEMENTS: I think in
terms of the musical score,
this is a really beautiful little…
MUSKER: Really tender violin thing.
The orchestrations, Danny
Troob's and Alan's composing here,
really tender, sweet.
My handsome prince.
MUSKER: Tony Fucile was the
animator who did these scenes,
really a wonderful draughtsman,
and a fairly soulful kiss,
which I always thought
was good, as kisses go.
And this look back, just like the
little button to this. The music there.
PELL: I thought, storytelling-wise,
this transition was just terrific.
She left with such an "Ah" feeling."
Yes!
CLEMENTS: A good date. [CHUCKLES]
For the first time in my life,
things are starting to go right.
PELL: No, they're not.
[MUFFLED] Abu. Abu.
MUSKER: Yes, it's the
ham-on-a-string sequence.
I'm afraid you've worn out
your welcome, Prince Abubu.
[MUFFLED] Why, you…
Make sure he's never found.
CLEMENTS: A pretty nasty Jafar there.
This was actually a Ted
and Terry idea, I think.
Originally, we'd had a different
way that Aladdin was taken out,
but they wrote this idea of
him being thrown into water,
and it's pretty uncomfortable, I think.
MUSKER: Of course, Robin here,
his whole mock German that he
came up with on this was very funny.
That was not written to
be German necessarily.
I think that was Robin's…
It's coming up, when he
does his submarine thing later.
Al?
[GASPING] Al! Kid…
MUSKER: Actually, all
this calling of Aladdin, "Al,"
that was something Robin did ad-lib.
CLEMENTS: In the first
session, he just threw that out.
MUSKER: And then we wrote to it.
Once we heard it,
we decided, "Wait, we could
actually take advantage of that"
"in terms of their relationship"
"and what Aladdin means
versus Al in terms of the…"
Yeah, that's his homage
to Sid Caesar, there, I think.
[COUGHING]
CLEMENTS: We get their relationship,
a nice, warm moment between them.
I, uh…
I…
-Thanks, Genie.
-Oh, Al.
I'm gettin' kind of fond of you, kid.
Not that I wanna pick
out curtains or anything.
CLEMENTS: A little
controversy about that line.
SULTAN: Jasmine.
Oh, Father, I just had
the most wonderful…
PELL: At first the idea of not
having a mother, we thought,
"No, every animated movie
doesn't have the parents.
-"We don't wanna go that route."
-MUSKER: Yeah, here we go again.
"My mother's gonna kill me."
PELL: But there is some emotional element
that worked, especially in
terms of the street urchin.
MUSKER: Had to prove
himself, the low self-esteem.
Or the guy who's really
being denigrated on the street,
and he questions himself, even.
"Am I really the guy they say I am?"
"And I don't think I am, and I'm
going to prove to people I'm not."
CLEMENTS: And the
diamond-in-the-rough thing
kind of resonates, I think.
Even among teenagers,
I think there's a thematic
thing there that is valid.
On the surface, you can seem
like you've really been dealt
a poor deck of cards,
but really what's inside is
what's the most important.
Sometimes people in very
unfortunate circumstances
can find that they are
a diamond in the rough,
if they can find what's
inside them that's valuable.
So I think that message…
MUSKER: And the basic message
that came through in the rewrite,
stronger perhaps, was the whole,
just sort of "Be yourself" idea."
PELL: Owning who you were.
MUSKER: Really celebrate who you are,
and don't try and be something else,
which I think is thematically something
that people, including
teenagers and kids, can relate to,
just because there's often pressures
to be something other
than you really are.
PELL: I also think it's timeless,
and that's why Aladdin
has stood the test of time.
MUSKER: I think the
topicality, the humor and that,
that comes and goes and all that.
But I think the themes work.
And I do still think it's still funny
today. [CHUCKLING] So that helps.
CLEMENTS: Some nice
Sultan animation in this,
and Douglas Seale, again,
did a nice bit here
where he gets all excited.
PELL: David Pruiksma.
MUSKER: And Barry Temple as well.
Barry Temple did some of this in here.
Am I remembering that right?
CLEMENTS: Yeah.
Barry Temple was in Florida, so
he actually, probably did this part.
PELL: But David Pruiksma
was the lead for the character.
I didn't know if you had
mentioned him earlier or not.
He was a major
influence on the character.
CLEMENTS: Once again,
the theme of being trapped.
I think we were pushing the idea
that you can be trapped by success
as well as being trapped by failure.
MUSKER: Jonathan
Freeman, the funny thing is,
we heard Jonathan Freeman's
voice before we ever saw him.
He auditioned in New York for the part.
And we had no idea what he looked like.
We heard his name and we just thought,
"Wow, this is a cool,
great dramatic voice,"
and we pictured this rail-thin,
whatever, Vincent Price. Whatever.
CLEMENTS: The voice fits the character
much more than it fits Jonathan Freeman.
MUSKER: And then we saw
Jonathan Freeman, and he's handsome,
but a rounder-than-he-is-angular
sort of a guy,
and yet he brought such a fun, oily…
He just went to town with the voice.
He was a stage actor,
so he brought a stage actor sense
of timing and delivery and all that.
And that was really fun for Jafar.
Huzzah!
[SINGING] Hail the conquering hero
CLEMENTS: I wondered if this
gag coming up was going to date,
but I think people will still get it.
This is the…
You've just won the
heart of the princess.
What are you gonna do next?
CLEMENTS: They're still doing that?
MUSKER: Alan did the little
musical quote there. That was fun.
[WHISPERING] Psst. Your line is…
MUSKER: This is probably
the biggest breaking
of the plane we did in the movie,
where we said, "This is really a movie."
Reading from the script, and
it was something you don't see
in most of the others, and
it was a calculated thing.
CLEMENTS: We actually discuss that stuff,
even though it's taken for granted,
just how far can we go?
How far can we not go?
And I think that actually is the farthest,
but we felt within that
scene you could do it
and get away with it.
Our conceit with the
Genie was basically that
because he was almost
like a god-like figure
who transcended space and time,
he could know all the
cultural references of any time,
and even though the other
characters wouldn't get his humor at all,
he somehow thinks that's funny.
But the idea that…
MUSKER: He's trying to entertain himself
CLEMENTS: Right, yeah, he's been
cooped up for thousands of years,
and he has an audience now
and he wants to be entertaining.
But he's read the script? I mean, that's…
PELL: I think you both achieved
great emotion in this scene,
not only with the script, but
the visual of his size going down.
MUSKER: I think it helped to have
them to cut to, Abu as the elephant
and the carpet, to get a little
bit more of an audience cue
and to get more sincerity
and warmth in this.
PELL: And their disapproval
coming through, too.
And also puts him alone, again.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, he's isolated now.
He's gone past where he should be.
Robin's acting on that
and Scott's acting was
very strong and sincere.
And there, again, that was Robin.
When the sincere moments came,
he played them very straight,
and that was very effective.
MUSKER: I remember, this sequence,
we fooled around with a little bit.
Ed Gombert, I think,
came up with the idea
of this bizarre Iago on the
stilts, posing as a flamingo.
I seem to remember Ed cooking this up.
Or at least this gag. I can't remember.
-[GOOFY CHUCKLE]
-You got a problem, Pinky?
Jerk.
-MUSKER: I'm still amused by that.
-[PELL CHUCKLING]
Boy, Jafar's gonna be happy to see you.
[IMITATES JAFAR] "Excellent work, Iago."
Ah, go on.
"No, really.
On a scale of one to 10, you are an 11 ."
MUSKER: Our homage to Gary Franklin.
I don't know, is Gary
Franklin still around?
He was a film critic out here in
Los Angeles who did a whole scale.
"On the Franklin scale
of 1 to 10, 10 being best,"
"I give it a whatever."
Now there are many critics, I guess,
but Gary Franklin out here
was the guy that used to do that.
CLEMENTS: I've always
had parrots as pets,
and I testify that when they talk,
they are very good mimics.
They can actually do that.
MUSKER: In terms of
their relationship here,
I do like this little sequence here,
even with her primping him.
I've gone through this myself,
somebody tries to put you
together before you go onstage.
[CHEERING]
Look at them…
PELL: And it was her change of costume,
where she finally had
her midriff covered.
CLEMENTS: You were happy
then, I think, Amy, weren't you?
You know, Al, I'm getting really…
CLEMENTS: She actually does
have a few changes, but it took a while.
Will be played by a tall,
dark and sinister ugly man.
-I am your master now.
-I was afraid of that.
Genie, grant me my first wish.
MUSKER: This is where we did…
A lot of rewriting happened
here from the earlier version
because, really, there was the
whole idea of Jafar becoming Sultan
and using the limited
wishes and all that.
CLEMENTS: This was
really the trickiest part
of the movie in some ways to solve,
and I think we had the
whole movie all together
while we were still struggling
with the story in this part.
One of the big questions was,
is Jafar going to have a song?
Can he have a song? We wanted…
Jonathan Freeman is such a great singer.
We wanted him to have a song.
There are actually several versions
that Alan wrote of a
song here, along with Tim,
but all of them seemed like
it just slowed things
down a little bit too much.
And then finally, I think,
maybe it was Alan who came up
with just doing the reprise
of the Prince Ali song here.
MUSKER: I think he felt that the
length of time we were gonna devote
to this in song had to be brief enough
that he couldn't come up
with a whole new melody
and have it land and not
feel like an interruption.
So he used a reprise of Prince Ali.
This is Alan's idea to
go back to that melody.
And I think that worked in
terms of not asking the audience
to digest a whole new musical motif
CLEMENTS: At least we got to
hear Jonathan sing for a little bit.
PELL: But the action is
going so strong at this point,
you wanna know what's going on.
MUSKER: We're going
into the third act here.
PELL: We needed to just
keep it moving at this point.
MUSKER: Right, you couldn't
stop for a song so much.
So it had to be a quicker story element.
Genie, stop!
Ladies and gentlemen…
CLEMENTS: That was, I think,
the unique thing about Jafar,
was he was a malevolent
guy behind the scenes.
The guy in power, the Sultan,
is a little bit inept and
a little bit fumbling,
and it's really the guy behind it,
the number-two guy, who
secretly wants to be number one.
And he's so officious
and he's totally two-faced.
PELL: And, again, all
the colors are changing.
Even the blues have tints of red.
[SINGING] Read my lips
And come to grips with reality
MUSKER: My homage to
Johnny Carson's coming up here,
with the golf swing at the end.
Whose lies were too good to last
CLEMENTS: We always
intended for Jafar to have
a great villain song in the movie,
and we went from Humiliate the
Boy to, I think, several other songs.
I think there were more versions of
the Jafar villain song written for this
than anything else in the movie.
We finally settled on a shorter
version of Jafar's villain song
that actually became just a
reprise of the Prince Ali song.
Give me adequate cause
MUSKER: We wanted him to slap
him just to make him that much nastier.
Give him a little physical abuse.
He is the bad guy after all.
Here's the Johnny Carson.
That was the end of his
monologue all the time.
No one would care, but I…
CLEMENTS: Well, also, Iago does
little Ed McMahon bits throughout,
so there's a lot of references.
PELL: That wonderful laugh at
the end that Jonathan… It's so great.
CLEMENTS: He loved the laugh.
Could not get enough of that.
MUSKER: This was
animated in Florida, again.
Rob Bekuhrs was the
CG supervisor in Florida
who animated this whole
parapet tumbling down the slope.
We did want to get snow just 'cause
we thought it was such a contrast
with the desert
environment we had been in,
and you'd been in that for so long.
It was just nice to get away
and to make it this exotic,
completely foreign locale.
CLEMENTS: So this was really
some of the first sequences animated
by the Florida studio,
then they went on to do
Mulan and Lilo & Stitch.
MUSKER: Yeah, full movies.
I mean, this was
sequences within a movie,
and ultimately they did their own
films and did a great job on those.
PELL: This was another
very emotional moment,
when his best buddy is in danger.
It just adds to the humanity of Aladdin.
MUSKER: Right, makes
him more likeable here.
Carpet.
MUSKER: Poor old carpet.
CLEMENTS: I think this gag coming
up is based on a Buster Keaton bit.
MUSKER: Where the house falls around him,
and he manages to be standing.
It's great, one of the classic
sight gags of the silent era.
-And we stole it.
-[CHUCKLING]
CLEMENTS: Although
here it's not so much a gag
as how clever Aladdin is to figure out…
How clever is he to watch that…
MUSKER: Richard Vander
Wende was this unbelievable painter.
His command of light and
shadow and reflected light
and his rendering skills
were the most amazing thing.
CLEMENTS: Color. His color sensibility.
MUSKER: His colors were just exceptional.
CLEMENTS: Now everything is
red, 'cause Jafar has taken over,
so the progression of red has
consumed the movie at this point.
PELL: And also, the columns in the palace
are much more elongated
than when the Sultan was there.
CLEMENTS: Yeah, he redesigned everything.
MUSKER: Sue Nichols, our
storyboard artist, did this sequence,
and she did a lot of
great stuff in the boards
that then we tried to
get in the animation,
in terms of some of the
attitudes here and the ideas.
His repellent attempts
to take advantage of her.
I'll teach you some respect.
CLEMENTS: Nasty.
No. Genie.
I have decided to make my final wish.
MUSKER: A subdued Genie,
something we haven't seen very much.
He's a beaten guy.
CLEMENTS: And the second appearance
of William F. Buckley is coming up.
MUSKER: You didn't have enough.
-There was a groundswell…
-CLEMENTS: Yes, we gotta have more
-William F. Buckley.
-of conservative Republicans
who wanted… The National Review
readership was demanding, please.
CLEMENTS: I know when we first brought
Robin in and we worked with him,
there was some question if he
should do some sort of persona
as the Genie in neutral.
If he should have an Arabian accent
or play him as a character.
I think we tried a few things,
but it seemed really obvious
that, no, the Genie is
Robin in his own mode.
You think of a personality like Robin,
if he were trapped in some sort of prison
for years and years and years,
just what a sad thing that is,
just because of the
energy and the impulse
to just entertain and be a bright light.
We have all the stuff we did
with Robin that we didn't use.
I think there was probably
more recorded for this sequence
than any other part of the movie.
JASMINE: Cute little
gaps between your teeth.
MUSKER: We had him cheering Aladdin on.
He did all sorts of variations.
He was Patton. He was Sylvester Stallone.
A fight promoter.
CLEMENTS: We actually
ran the whole sequence
for him in storyboard form,
and he would just do commentary.
MUSKER: Howard Cosell.
CLEMENTS: He did tons
of totally hilarious stuff,
and in the end, we only
used just a smidgen,
'cause it just felt like if we got
too carried away with the Genie,
it would take away from the
seriousness of the situation here.
MUSKER: Most horrifying
scene in the movie there,
the kiss with the bad guy.
Fortunately, the monkey
could react like we did.
CLEMENTS: Like the whole audience did.
MUSKER: The audience
did give a big vocal reaction.
We were trying to work with their reaction
and let it play out for a little bit.
Get the lamp.
No!
Ah, ah, ah, Princess. Your time is up.
MUSKER: He's doing his
James Bond villain lines.
CLEMENTS: A lot of puns, a lot of puns.
MUSKER: Just kill them with puns.
It always works.
Oh, nice shot, Jaf…
Don't toy with me.
MUSKER: Another one.
Abu!
JAFAR: Things are unraveling fast now…
MUSKER: [CHUCKLING] He won't stop.
It's just…
Get the point?
[LAUGHING]
[STRAINING]
I'm just getting warmed up.
[LAUGHTER]
MUSKER: Okay.
It's not Eugene O'Neill, all right?
CLEMENTS: It's Jafar's character.
He just loves those.
Take my villain, please.
MUSKER: So now this
is where we talk about
Kathy Zielinski animated this
scene of him transitioning into a snake
just as she was about to give
birth to her daughter Jennifer, I think.
Her water broke as she was
animating this, I think, it was.
AMY: She handed in her final
scene, and then her water broke.
MUSKER: All for the cause.
Way to go, Kath.
[SINGING] Rick 'em,
rack 'em, rock 'em, rake
Stick that sword into that snake
You stay out of this.
Jafar, Jafar, he's our man.
If he can't do it… Great!
MUSKER: In films, often in the third act,
you have what's called a ticking clock,
where you're trying to
prevent something happening
and you're cutting to something
that's marking time going by.
So here we have a literal one
with the hourglass,
which helped achieve that.
PELL: A literal.
MUSKER: A literal or
a silent ticking clock.
CLEMENTS: And then Andreas did
a lot of the climactic
stuff with the snake.
MUSKER: Yeah, the snake. It was
fun to reinterpret Jafar as this reptile.
Without the genie, boy, you're nothing.
PELL: I know that we were
concerned at one point, how scary is it?
Is it too scary for kids?
But, ultimately, I think
we found the balance.
MUSKER: We tried to leaven it with humor
and make a balance between
the scariness and the humor.
Face it, Jafar.
You're still just second best.
CLEMENTS: We were really
worried as this was going in front
of the ratings board if
we would get a PG rating.
And we were relieved
when we got a G rating.
But at the same time a little
disappointed. [LAUGHING]
Maybe this wasn't as
powerful as we wanted it to be.
MUSKER: So we demanded
a recount, didn't we?
Genie!
All right, your wish is my command.
Way to go, Al.
CLEMENTS: Ted Elliott
and Terry Rossio, the writers,
came up with this bit at the end
where Aladdin tricks Jafar.
It was set up earlier in the
movie, where they have the line,
"It's all part and parcel
of the whole genie biz,"
"phenomenal cosmic powers…
Itty bitty living space."
And Aladdin turns that on Jafar here.
So that the idea is that
becoming a genie means
that you have to live in a lamp.
The universe is mine
to command, to control!
MUSKER: It's the
downside of being a genie.
CLEMENTS: It's his way of tricking Jafar.
You wanted to be a genie, you got it.
What?
And everything that goes with it.
CLEMENTS: It can't be fun
being cooped up in that lamp
with Gilbert Gottfried for all eternity.
You're the genie. I don't want…
Itty bitty living space.
Al, you little genius, you.
MUSKER: The magic
of animation restoration.
[CHUCKLING]
CLEMENTS: I know there was huge
concern as we got into color timing
and doing our first
release prints of the movie.
It was tricky to retain
the color intensity,
particularly of some
of the reds that we had.
I think Richard was concerned about it.
Even to maintain from
answer print to release print,
which is what goes out into the theaters,
that there was danger of
not getting the full effect.
Very nice musical bit here, too.
Some nice animation
as we get into the finale.
About being a prince.
I know why you did.
Well, I guess…
PELL: There was a lot of
discussion about the ending,
whether it should end
in a wedding or not.
MUSKER: At one point, with
Howard Ashman's original reprise,
there was a wedding, and
people were invited or something,
but we weren't sure, like,
"Should we do that or not?"
'Cause there was a question,
"Was the narrator gonna
come back at the end?"
It was all back and forth.
Hey, it's only an eternity of servitude.
This is love.
Al, you're not gonna find another
girl like her in a million years.
CLEMENTS: When we did this,
we weren't expecting any sequels,
and there have been
a couple video sequels
to Aladdin done since then.
Which is good because what
happens at the end is vague.
I mean, it almost implies a
wedding, but not completely.
MUSKER: Yeah, it's not explicit.
Genie, you're free.
MUSKER: We were trying
to look for a visual symbol
to symbolize his
freedom from his shackles,
and we came up relatively late,
I think, the idea of him
losing his arm bracelets
to just somehow visually communicate
-that he was no longer imprisoned.
-CLEMENTS: Which is good.
Although he loses a lot of his character
-without his arm bracelets.
-[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, he's naked
without his arm bracelets.
MUSKER: He looks sort of naked somehow.
But so much freer.
Wish for the Nile. Try that.
-Uh, I wish for the Nile.
-No way!
MUSKER: I remember just before
the film was going to be released,
we were meeting on
another project with Jeffrey,
and Ted and Terry were
there, and Jeffrey was saying,
"I don't know, I got a
good feeling about this."
"Everybody I talk to says
they wanna go see it."
This was literally the week
before it was gonna come out.
He's just like, "You never
know on these things."
"Are the movie gods
gonna smile on you or not?"
"But I'm telling you, everybody I
see is curious about the movie"
"and they wanna go see it."
Me, too, Al.
CLEMENTS: This is, once
again, the sincere Robin,
where he can pull back and really,
really play it very warmly and sincere.
That's right.
You've certainly proven your
worth as far as I'm concerned.
CLEMENTS: And in terms of
everybody being trapped now,
the Genie has been freed of his trap
and Aladdin's been freed,
and now the Sultan, actually, we realize…
He realizes that he's
imposed these rules on himself,
and he can change them if he wants to.
So in a way, it frees him from his
trap, which frees Jasmine from her trap.
All the characters in the film
that were trapped in some way
are now freed, except for
Jafar, which is just as well.
This was Eric Goldberg's
bit, dressing up the Genie.
Actually, the Genie is
wearing the same outfit
that Robin Williams wears in a film
that was done for Walt Disney World.
MUSKER: Back To Neverland,
which was produced by Don Ernst,
who has produced this movie.
Our homage to Don Ernst there.
Jerry Rees directed the piece
and Don Ernst produced it,
but that's what Robin was
wearing in the live-action film
for the theme park.
CLEMENTS: And here's where we leave.
We have this thing,
"Are they getting married or not?"
There's a big celebration,
but we'll never know for sure.
MUSKER: In an earlier
version of this that we previewed,
we did have a reprise finally here,
with the narrator coming back and singing
Arabian Nights, and Jeffrey did
give us a hard time, and rightly so.
He said, "Guys, your movie's over.
Your movie's over."
"People were getting up.
They were putting their coats on."
CLEMENTS: So we lost
the idea that used to be here
that the narrator actually
came back in the end,
and then turned into the Genie.
So, originally, the narrator was revealed
to be the Genie in the end of the movie.
But now he's not.
PELL: It's very hard to give up
something before you think it's perfect.
And yet, we had a schedule
to keep and we had a due date.
So it's very much about
keeping everything moving
and reaching your schedule and
getting everything done on time.
So the challenge was
to make the best movie
possible in the time allotted.
Dan Hansen was also integral
to getting different
areas coordinated into it,
especially in the earlier
stages of layout and design.
MUSKER: This is the first movie, I
think, where we created a new position
that subsequently is on a number of
Disney films, the artistic coordinator,
where he really helped pull
different departments together
to really make sure that
it all worked in terms of
continuity and design issues.
CLEMENTS: And really solved problems
that involved both technical
and creative problems,
in terms of just how to achieve things
and make sure it worked
within a production process.
MUSKER: The clean-up
animators on this have
done such a great job and, of course,
hand-drawn animation
relies on the draughtsmanship
not only of the animators, but
particularly of the clean-up department.
And this movie really
couldn't have been what it was
without the people who really spent
a lot of time crafting these drawings
and not just making the characters
look proper, look well-drawn,
but have an aesthetic
appeal, in addition to that.
CLEMENTS: A cartoonier
movie, in some ways,
is easier to do than a
more realistic movie,
but we complicated it here slightly
because even though
we're a cartoony movie,
the line quality, we were
asking for a very elaborate,
beautiful line quality in the clean-up.
The staff really embraced that
and really made that work
and they did just a beautiful job.
PELL: I think we had the
créme de la créme of the artists.
It was the last film where
all the team was all together.
MUSKER: Yeah, after this, there
were more fragmented productions,
'cause they overlap things more.
So some people went off to do one
film and others stayed on another film.
But we had an all-star team
of people in many areas,
-both animation, layout…
-CLEMENTS: Up to this point,
it was pretty much the same
crew that worked on each film,
so most of the artists who
worked on this film worked
on Beauty and the Beast, as well as
Mermaid and Rescuers Down Under.
But after this, then it started to
break up into more varying units
that were on different films
going on simultaneously.
PELL: Also, we had an
incredible production team
that have all gone on to either
produce films or production manage.
We really had a terrific
team all the way around.
MUSKER: But the great
thing with the release too is
that it opened around Thanksgiving.
It did well at Thanksgiving, but
then it played through Christmas,
and then, in fact, its best
week, I think, was the week
either between Christmas and
New Year's, or right around that time.
They added theaters,
and so it just played out.
CLEMENTS: It wasn't a film
nowadays that exploded in its opening.
It had a very good opening,
but not like you see nowadays.
And it was in a smaller
amount of theaters,
as it opened over Thanksgiving.
But it actually didn't
become the number-one film
until around Christmastime,
and then it stayed number one
for quite a few weeks in a row.
MUSKER: And, of course, it was
exciting, as it was in the preview,
to see it cross over in
terms of its audience.
That it wasn't just parents and kids.
I mean, there were single
people that went to see it.
People went on dates to see it.
It really sort of helped
expand the audience,
as Mermaid had
and Beauty and the Beast certainly did.
This did, and Lion King did as well.
It was great just to see
the stigma of animation
being just a kid's medium
kind of get peeled away
by these various films,
which, when we were making
the film, certainly we just thought,
"We're making this movie for ourselves,"
"and we're trying to please
ourselves in terms of our own taste"
"as an audience and hope
that other people will like it."
CLEMENTS: We wanted
it to be fun and entertaining
and for the audience to
really have a good time.
I think they did, for the most part.
-This is Amy Pell.
-And John Musker.
And Ron Clements, and goodbye
and thanks, everybody,
for being with us for this.