Read the charges.
Dr. Jumba Jookiba,
lead scientist of
Galaxy Defense Industries,
you stand before this council
accused of illegal
genetic experimentation.
How do you plead?
Not guilty!
My experiments are only theoretical,
completely within legal boundaries.
We believe you actually
created something.
Created something?
But that would be
irresponsible and unethical.
I would never, ever,
make more than one.
What is that monstrosity?
Monstrosity?
What you see before you is
the first of a new species.
I call it Experiment 626.
He is bulletproof, fireproof
and can think faster
than supercomputer.
He can see in the dark
and move objects 3,000 times his size.
His only instinct,
to destroy everything he touches!
So it is a monster.
Hey, just a little one.
It is an affront to nature.
It must be destroyed!
Calm yourself, Captain Gantu.
Perhaps it can be reasoned with.
Experiment 626, give us some sign
you understand any of this.
Show us that there is something
inside you that is good.
So naughty!
I didn't teach it that.
Place that idiot scientist under arrest!
I prefer to be called "evil genius"!
And as for that abomination,
it is the flawed product
of a deranged mind.
It has no place among us.
Captain Gantu, take him away.
With pleasure.
Uncomfortable?
Good!
The council has banished you
to exile on a desert asteroid.
So relax, enjoy the trip,
and don't get any ideas.
These guns are locked
onto your genetic signature.
They won't shoot anyone but you.
Why, you...
May I remind the Captain
that he is on duty?
Secure the cell!
Aye, Captain.
Captain on deck.
All ahead full.
Does this look infected to you?
Quiet, you.
-Gunfire in the cell bay!
-Open a channel.
He's loose on Deck C!
Red alert. Seal off the deck!
Security, converge on Door 7!
Deadly force authorized. Fire on sight!
Fire on sight!
There he is!
Security to Bridge.
It's in the ventilation system.
He's headed for the power grid.
What was that?
I don't think he's on the ship anymore.
Confirmed. He's taken a police cruiser.
Yeah, he took the red one.
That's it! We've got it. We've got it!
Hyperdrive activated.
System charging.
He's engaged his H-drive!
Warning, guidance is not functional.
Pursuit Commander, that crazy trog
is about to make a jump!
Break formation! Get clear of that ship!
Navigation failure. Do not engage...
Get me Galactic Control.
Where is he?
He's still in hyperspace.
Where will he exit?
Calculating now.
Quadrant 17, section 005, area 51.
A planet called Ee-arth.
I want an expert on this planet
in here now!
What is that?
Water. Most of the planet is
covered in it.
He won't survive in water.
His molecular density is too great.
No.
Of course.
How much time do we have?
We have projected his landing
at three hours, 42 minutes.
We have to gas the planet.
Hold it! Hold everything!
Earth is a protected wildlife reserve.
Yeah. We've been using it
to rebuild the mosquito population,
which, need I remind you,
is an endangered species!
Am I to assume you are the expert?
I don't know about "expert."
Agent Pleakley at your service.
Can we not simply destroy the island?
No! Crazy head!
The mosquito's food of choice,
primitive humanoid life forms,
have colonies all over that planet.
Are they intelligent?
No, but they're very delicate.
In fact, every time an asteroid strikes
their planet,
they have to begin life all over.
It's fascinating, isn't it?
With this, I've been able to study...
What if our military forces
just landed there?
Well, that'd be a bad idea!
These are extremely
simple creatures, miss.
Landing there would create
mass mayhem and planet-wide panic!
A quiet capture would require
an understanding of 626
that we do not possess.
Who, then, Mr. Pleakley,
would you send for his extraction?
Does he have a brother?
Close grandmother, perhaps?
Friendly cousin?
Neighbor with a beard?
He got away?
I'm sure this comes
as no surprise to you.
I designed this creature
for to be unstoppable.
Which is precisely why
you must now bring him back.
What, me?
And to reward you,
we are willing to trade
your freedom for his capture.
626 will not come easily.
Maybe direct hit from plasma cannon
might stun him long enough to...
Plasma cannon granted.
Do we have a bargain, Dr. Jumba?
But it's a delicate planet!
Who's going to control him?
You will.
Very good, Your Highness.
I didn't quite...
You're not joking!
So, tell me, my little one-eyed one,
on what poor, pitiful,
defenseless planet
has my monstrosity been unleashed?
Stop. Stop.
Lilo, why are you all wet?
It's sandwich day.
Every Thursday, I take Pudge the fish
a peanut-butter sandwich.
Pudge is a fish?
And today
we were out of peanut butter.
So I asked my sister what to give him,
and she said a tuna sandwich.
I can't give Pudge tuna!
Do you know what tuna is?
-Fish?
-It's fish!
If I gave Pudge tuna,
I'd be an abomination!
I'm late because I had to go to the store
and get peanut butter,
'cause all we have is stinking tuna!
Lilo, Lilo, why is this so important?
Pudge controls the weather.
You're crazy.
Please! Please!
Everybody calm down!
Girls.
-Lilo...
-I'm sorry! I'm sorry!
I won't do it again!
Maybe we should call your sister.
No! I'll be good! I want to dance.
I practiced.
I just want to dance.
She bit me.
I called your sister.
She said to wait for her
here on the porch.
We'll try again on Sunday.
Does this look infected to you?
Yeah.
You better not have rabies.
If you have rabies,
the dogcatcher is going to have to cut...
Are you going to play dolls?
You don't have a doll.
This is Scrump.
I made her, but her head is too big.
So I pretend a bug laid eggs
in her ears, and she's upset,
because she only has
a few more days to...
Lilo!
Lilo?
Oh, no.
You better be home.
Hey! Watch where you're going!
Stupid head!
Lilo!
Lilo! Open the door, Lilo!
Go away.
Lilo? We don't have time for this.
Leave me alone to die.
Come on, Lilo, that social worker's
going to be here any minute!
You are so finished when I get in there!
I'm going to stuff you in the blender,
push "purée," then bake you into a pie
and feed it to the social worker!
And when he says, "This is great.
What's your secret?" I'm going to say,
"Love and nurturing."
Hi.
You must be the...
The stupid head.
You know, I'm really sorry about that,
and if I'd known who you were,
of course I never would've...
I can pay for that.
It's a rental.
Are you the guardian in question?
Yes. I'm Nani.
Nice to meet you, Mister...
Bubbles.
Mr. Bubbles. That's a strange...
Yes, I know.
Are you going to invite me in, Nani?
I thought we could sit out here and talk.
I don't think so.
Right.
This way.
Wait here.
Hey!
So, lemonade?
Do you often leave
your sister home alone?
No. Never.
Well, except for just now.
I had to run to the store to get some...
You left the stove on
while you were out?
Low heat! Just a simmer.
It's coming along great.
I found that this morning.
Lilo! There you are.
Honey face, this is Mr. Bubbles.
Nice to meet you.
Your knuckles say "Cobra."
Cobra Bubbles.
You don't look like a social worker.
I'm a special classification.
Did you ever kill anyone?
We're getting off the subject.
Let's talk about you. Are you happy?
I'm adjusted. I eat four food groups
and look both ways
before crossing the street
and take long naps and get disciplined.
Disciplined?
Yeah. She disciplines me real good.
Sometimes five times a day.
-No.
-With bricks.
Bricks?
In a pillowcase.
Okay! That's enough sugar for you.
Why don't you run along,
you little cutie?
The other social workers
just thought she was a scream.
Thirsty?
Let me illuminate to you
the precarious situation
in which you have found yourself.
I am the one they call
when things go wrong,
and things have indeed gone wrong.
My friends need to be punished.
Call me next time
you're left here alone.
Yep.
In case you're wondering,
this did not go well.
You have three days
to change my mind.
Lilo!
Why didn't you wait at the school?
You were supposed to wait there!
Lilo!
Do you not understand?
Do you want to be taken away?
Answer me!
-No!
-No, you don't understand?
-No, what?
No!
You're such a pain!
So why don't you sell me
and buy a rabbit instead?
At least a rabbit would behave
better than you!
Go ahead! Then you'll be happy,
because it'll be smarter than me, too!
And quieter!
You'll like it, 'cause it's stinky, like you!
Go to your room!
I'm already in my room!
Hey.
I brought you some pizza,
in case you were hungry.
We're a broken family, aren't we?
No.
Maybe a little.
Maybe a lot.
I shouldn't have yelled at you.
We're sisters. It's our job.
Yeah, well, from now on...
I like you better as a sister than a mom.
Yeah?
And you like me better as a sister
than a rabbit, right?
Yes.
Yes, I do.
I hit Mertle Edmonds today.
You hit her?
Before I bit her.
You bit her. Lilo, you shouldn't...
People treat me different.
They just don't know what to say.
I'll tell you what.
If you promise not to fight anymore,
I promise not to yell at you,
except on special occasions.
Tuesdays and bank holidays
would be good.
Yeah? Would that be good?
My camera's full again.
Aren't they beautiful?
A falling star!
I call it! Get out! Get out!
I have to make a wish!
Can't you go any faster?
Oh, no! Gravity is increasing on me.
No, it's not!
It is, too, Lilo.
The same thing happened yesterday.
You rotten sister!
Your butt is crushing me!
Why do you act so weird?
It's me again.
I need someone to be my friend,
someone who won't run away.
Maybe send me an angel,
the nicest angel you have.
What we when hit?
There it is.
It stayed jammed under the fender.
We better call somebody.
We're looking for something
that can defend itself,
something that won't die,
something sturdy, you know?
Like a lobster.
Lilo, you                 lolo.
Do we have a lobster door?
No. We have a dog door.
We are getting a dog.
So nice to see your pretty face again!
Jumba?
We need your name and address
at the bottom of the form...
The kennel's back this way.
Go. Pick someone out.
Hello?
Are there any "aminals" in here?
Hello!
Hi.
Wow!
Yes. All of our dogs are adoptable.
Except that one!
What is that thing?
A dog, I think,
but it was dead this morning.
It was dead this morning?
Well, we thought it was dead.
It was hit by a truck.
I like him! Come here, boy.
Wouldn't you like a different dog?
We have better dogs, dear.
Not better than him.
He can talk! Say hello.
Dogs can't talk, dear.
He did.
Does it have to be this dog?
Yes, he's good. I can tell.
You'll have to think of a name for him.
His name is Stitch.
Now, that's not a real name
in Iceland, but here it's a good name.
Stitch it is.
And there's a $2 license fee.
I want to buy him!
Can I borrow $2?
He's all yours.
You're all mine.
Well, what's he doing?
Keep quiet. He's listening for us.
How good is his hearing?
I mean, can he...
Why don't you run?
Coming! I'm coming!
Stop!
I have just determined this situation
to be far too hazardous!
Don't worry, I won't hit her.
No! That girl is a part
of the mosquito food chain.
Here! Educate yourself.
Using a little girl for a shield.
This is low even for you!
Tear him apart
with all both my bare hands!
Have you lost your mind?
What is it, Stitch?
We cannot be seen!
Bad dog, barking at nothing!
You can't shoot, and you can't be seen.
Look at you! You look like a monster.
We have to blend in.
Okay, I got to get to work.
Stick around town
and stay out of the roads, okay?
I'll meet you at 1:00.
Okay, I guess we should be going.
What about Stitch?
My friends!
What do you want?
I'm sorry I bit you and pulled your hair
and punched you in the face.
Apology not accepted.
Now get out of my way
before I run you over.
I got a new dog. His name is Stitch.
That is the ugliest thing
I have ever saw.
-Yeah.
Get it away from me!
I'm gonna get a disease!
Somebody do something!
Oh, great! He's loose.
His destructive programming
is taking effect.
He will be irresistibly drawn
to large cities
where he will back up sewers,
reverse street signs
and steal everyone's left shoe.
It's nice to live on an island
with no large cities.
Are you okay?
Hey, over here, little buddy.
When you're ready to give up,
just let us know.
Yeah!
This is you.
This is your badness level.
It's unusually high
for someone your size.
We have to fix that.
Lilo!
Your dog cannot sit at the table.
Stitch is troubled. He needs desserts.
You didn't even eat your sweet potato.
I thought you liked them.
Desserts!
David!
I got a new dog.
You sure it's a dog?
He used to be a collie
before he got ran over.
Hey.
How's it, Nani?
Did you catch fire again?
Nah, just the stage.
Listen, I was wondering
if you're not doing anything this...
David, I told you, I can't. I...
I got a lot to deal with right now.
I know. I just figured
you might need some time...
You smell like a lawn mower.
Look, I got to go.
The kid at Table 3's
throwing                 poi                 again.
Maybe some other time, okay?
Don't worry.
She likes your butt and fancy hair.
I know. I read her diary.
She thinks it's fancy?
Look what I find! Get restraints!
-Right.
-Take that! Hurry!
Hold still just a...
Hey, Nani!
Is that your dog?
All is well.
Please, go about your business.
I'm okay.
Your head looks swollen.
Actually, she's just ugly.
Darling. He's joking.
Ugly, look at me.
This is not working out.
But...
Yeah?
Well, who wants to work
at this stupid fakey                 luau                 anyway?
Come on, Lilo.
Did you lose your job
because of Stitch and me?
Nah. The manager's a vampire,
and he wanted me to join
his legion of the undead.
I knew it.
This is a great home. You'll like it a lot.
See?
Lilo...
Comfy.
-Hey!
What is the matter with you?
Be careful of the little angel!
It's not an angel, Lilo.
I don't even think it's a dog.
We just have to take him back.
He's just cranky
because it's his bedtime.
He's creepy, Lilo.
I won't sleep
knowing he's loose in the house.
You're loose in the house all the time,
and I sleep just fine!
Hey, what are you doing?
Stop that, Stitch!
Hey!
Look at him, Lilo.
He's obviously mutated
from something else.
We have to take him back.
He was an orphan,
and we adopted him!
What about                 'ohana?
He hasn't been here that long.
Neither have I.
Dad said                 'ohana                 means "family."
'Ohana                 means "family."
-"Family" means...
-Nobody gets left behind.
-Or?
-Or forgotten.
I know. I know. I hate it
when you use                 'ohana                 against me.
Don't worry,
you can sleep right next to me.
Look how curious the puppy is.
This is my room, and this is your bed.
This is your dolly and bottle.
See? Doesn't spill.
I filled it with coffee.
Good puppy. Now get into bed.
Hey! That's mine!
Down!
Be careful of that! You don't touch this!
Don't ever touch it!
No! Don't pull on her head!
She's recovering from surgery.
No! That's from my blue period.
There.
You know, you wreck
everything you touch.
Why not try and make something
for a change?
Wow. San Francisco.
Save me!
No more caffeine for you.
This little girl is wasting her time.
626 cannot be taught to ignore
its destructive programming.
Push that over.
-What are you doing?
-Nothing!
-Say, I want to try it on.
-No!
-Share!
-Hey!
You're just jealous 'cause I'm pretty!
Don't move.
A mosquito has chosen me
as her perch.
She's so beautiful.
Look, another one.
And another one!
Why, it's a whole flock.
And they like me!
They're nuzzling my flesh
with their noses.
Now, they're, they're...
I think it might be a koala, an evil koala.
I can't even pet it.
It keeps staring at me,
like it's going to eat me.
Hello?
Nani?
Are you there?
-Now, this is interesting.
-What?
626 was designed to be a monster,
but now he has nothing to destroy.
You see, I never gave him
a greater purpose.
What must it be like to have nothing,
not even memories to visit
in the middle of the night?
Nah!
That's the Ugly Duckling.
See? He's sad because he's all alone
and nobody wants him.
But on this page,
his family hears him crying
and they find him.
Then the Ugly Duckling is happy,
because he knows where he belongs.
Want to listen to the King?
You look like an Elvis fan.
Nani.
Nani!
Yeah?
Look.
Heard you lost your job.
Well, actually, I just quit that job,
because, you know,
the hours are just not conducive
to the challenges of raising a child...
Hey!
I am so sorry about that.
What is that thing?
That's my puppy.
Really?
Thus far, you have been adrift
in the sheltered harbor of my patience,
but I cannot ignore you being jobless.
Do I make myself clear?
Perfectly.
And next time I see this dog, I expect it
to be a model citizen,                 capisce?
Yes?
New job.
Model citizen.
Good day.
Mrs. Hasagawa?
I'm here to answer your newspaper ad.
Elvis Presley was a model citizen.
I've compiled a list of his traits
for you to practice.
Number one is dancing.
I can't talk now, dear.
I'm waiting for someone
to answer my ad.
That's why I'm here.
Hands on your hips.
Now follow my lead.
That's my want ad.
I know!
Why is everything so dark?
I am all about coffee.
Let's move on to step two.
Elvis played guitar. Here.
Hold it like this,
and put your fingers here.
See? Now you try.
And I make great cappuccinos
and lattes with...
I wish I could, Nani,
but I just hired Teddy,
and with tourist season ending...
Concierge-er-ing is my life.
I just love to answer phones...
This is the face of romance.
She looks like
she could use some loving.
We might have something.
Good. Now kiss her.
I'm sure Elvis had his bad days, too.
I'm all about saving people.
Actually, I do think
we have an opening.
-Really?
-Okay, this is it.
Time to bring it all together.
That'd be so great!
You have no idea
how badly I need this job.
It's all you! Knock them dead!
Don't crowd him!
Hey, knock it off!
Hey, Lilo!
How's it, Nani?
We've been having a bad day.
Hey, I might not be a doctor,
but I know that there's no better cure
for a sour face
than a couple of boards
and some choice waves.
What you think?
I think that's a great idea.
Yeah!
Can't complain, Mom.
I'm camping out
with a convicted criminal,
and I had my head chewed on
by a monster!
Wait, something is not right.
626 is returning willingly to water.
Hold on, Mom, another call.
Mr. Pleakley, you are overdue.
I want a status report.
Things are going well.
He cannot swim!
Jumba, aren't they going well?
Why will he risk drowning?
Jumba? Jumba, help me out here.
I would have expected you back
by now with 626 in hand.
Just a few things left to pack,
and we'll be...
Hang up. We are going swimming.
Yeah!
Lilo!
What happened?
Some                 lolo                 must have
stuffed us in the barrel.
Where's Stitch?
Get off of her!
What happened?
Stitch dragged her down.
We lost Stitch!
Lilo? Lilo, look at me.
Look at me, baby. Are you hurt?
No.
He's unconscious,
but I think he's alive.
David, take Lilo.
This isn't what it looks like.
We were... It's just that...
I know you're trying, Nani,
but you need to think about
what's best for Lilo,
even if it removes you from the picture.
I'll be back tomorrow morning for Lilo.
I'm sorry.
Nani? Is there something I can do?
No, David.
I need to take Lilo home now.
We have a lot to talk about, you know.
Thanks.
You know, I really believed
they had a chance.
Then you came along.
Lilo, honey,
we have to...
Don't worry. You're nice,
and someone will give you a job.
I would.
Come here.
One fond embrace
Until we meet again
That's us before.
It was rainy, and they went for a drive.
What happened to yours?
I hear you cry at night.
Do you dream about them?
I know that's why you wreck things
and push me.
Our family's little now,
and we don't have many toys,
but if you want,
you could be a part of it.
You could be our baby,
and we'd raise you to be good.
'Ohana                 means "family."
"Family" means
nobody gets left behind,
but if you want to leave, you can.
I'll remember you, though.
I remember everyone that leaves.
I...
Lost.
I'm lost.
Help!
I don't like the ocean!
Look, a friendly little dolphin.
They helped sailors in the war...
It's a shark!
It's a shark, and it ain't friendly!
It looks like a dolphin.
Tricky fish! Tricky fish!
Octopus, come and help me?
The octopus is worse than the shark!
I hate this planet!
Little monster!
Agent Pleakley here.
I have lost patience with you both.
Have you captured 626 or not?
Consider yourselves fired
and prison-bound.
Your incompetence is
nothing short of unspeakable!
But...
We're fired!
Now we do it my way!
Your way?
Wait!
It seems I have overestimated
Jumber and Blinkley.
Jumba and Pleakley.
Whatever. The mission is in jeopardy.
This could be your chance
to redeem yourself, Captain Gantu.
How soon will you be prepared
to leave?
Immediately.
Don't run. Don't make me shoot you.
You were expensive.
Yes. Yes, that's it. Come quietly.
Waiting.
For what?
Family.
You don't have one.
I made you.
Maybe I could.
You're built to destroy.
You can never belong.
Now come quietly,
and we will take you apart.
No, no, no, no, don't, don't run!
Don't run!
Lilo.
I didn't hear you get up.
Baby, what's wrong?
Stitch left.
Really?
It's good he's gone.
He didn't want to be here, anyway.
We don't need him.
Lilo,
sometimes you try your hardest,
but things don't work out
the way you want them to.
Sometimes things have to change,
and maybe sometimes
they're for the better,
even if...
Nani!
-David!
-I think I found you a job.
You what?
Old man Kuakini's store,
but we got to hurry.
Okay. Lilo?
Baby, this is really important.
I need you to stay here
for a few minutes.
I'm going to be right back.
Lock the door
and don't answer it for anyone, okay?
Things are finally turning around.
David, I owe you one.
That's okay.
You can just date me,
and we'll call it even.
Come back here, you little...
Stitch?
What is it?
Hiding behind your little friend
won't work anymore.
Didn't I tell you?
We got fired this morning.
New rules.
What are we going to do?
I love this song!
Pliers.
-Screwdriver.
-Check.
Come out, my friend,
from whomever you're hiding behind.
What the...
Come on! What's the big deal?
I'll put you back together again.
I'll make you taller and not so fluffy!
I like fluffy!
No. No. No!
Leave my mother out of this!
You could do with a makeover.
I tried to give you my good looks,
but let's face it, something went wrong.
No!
Quick! Follow me! If we make it to...
-You're alive!
-They're all over the place!
Running away? Here, let me stop you.
You always get in the way!
Where's the girl?
What have you done to the girl?
Hello? Cobra Bubbles?
Aliens are attacking my house.
No, no, no! No aliens!
Blue punch buggy!
No punch back.
They want my dog!
There's no need to alert the authorities.
Everything's under control.
Lilo, who was that?
Good, my dog found the chainsaw.
Lilo! Don't hang...
You shouldn't play with guns.
Okay.
Thank you.
I just remembered. It's your birthday!
Happy birthday!
-Merry Christmas!
-It's not Christmas.
Happy Hanukkah!
We're leaving Stitch?
Trust me. This is not going to end well.
-One potato.
-Two potato.
-Three potato.
-Four.
-Five potato.
-Six potato.
Seven potato, more.
-My...
-Mother...
-Told...
-Me...
-You...
-Are...
-It.
-I win!
Thanks.                 Mahalo                 plenty.
You won't be disappointed.
I'll show up early to help
with the morning...
Don't turn left.
No.
One of them had a giant eye
in the middle of his face.
Lilo!
Please don't do this.
You know I have no choice.
No! You're not taking her!
I'm the only one who understands her!
You take that away,
she won't stand a chance!
You're making this harder
than it needs to be.
But you don't know what you're doing!
She needs me!
Is this what she needs?
It seems clear to me that you need her
a lot more than she needs you.
Lilo! Lilo!
Lilo!
You ruined everything.
You're one of them?
Get out of here, Stitch.
Surprise!
And here I thought
you'd be difficult to catch.
Silly me.
Lilo?
Lilo!
There you go,
all buckled up for the trip.
And, look,
I even caught you a little snack.
No! Stop!
Lilo.
Okay, talk.
I know you had something
to do with this.
Now where is Lilo?
Talk! I know you can.
Okay, okay.
Where's Lilo?
Lilo...
Now all your washing is up!
You're under arrest!
Read him his rights.
Listen carefully.
Hello? Galactic Command?
Experiment 626 is in custody.
We'll wait right here.
Don't interact with her.
Where's Lilo?
Who? What?
Lilo, my sister.
Sorry, we do not know anyone by this...
Lilo! She's a little girl, this big!
She has black hair and brown eyes,
and she hangs around with that thing!
We know her.
Bring her back.
We can't do that.
That would be a misuse
of Galactic resources.
See, problem is we're just here for him.
So she's gone?
Look at the bright side.
You won't have to yell
at anyone anymore.
Come.
'Ohana.
Hey! Get away from her.
No! What did you say?
'Ohana                 means " family."
-"Family" means nobody...
-Nobody gets left behind.
Or forgotten.
Yeah.
Hey.
What?
After all you put me through, you
expect me to help you just like that?
Just like that?
Fine.
Fine? You're doing what he says?
He's very persuasive.
Persuasive?
What exactly are we doing?
-Rescue.
-We're going to get Lilo?
Good! I was hoping to add theft,
endangerment
and insanity to my list of things
I did today.
You, too?
Yeah, yeah, yeah!
What? Did you think we walked here?
This is Gantu,
requesting hyperspace clearance.
Stand by for clearance.
Clearance is granted on vector C-12.
Connect me
to the Grand Councilwoman.
Gantu, what's going on?
I thought you'd like to know
that the little abomination is...
Yes, Captain?
I'll call you back.
How did you get out of there?
So what exactly are we doing?
Don't worry, is all part of plan.
We are professionals.
Hey! Get that out of your mouth!
Hold on!
Okay, is show time!
This is it!
Go! Go! Go!
Little savage! Get off my ship!
Stitch!
Computer, locate Experiment 626.
626 located.
We finish this now.
Stitch is unconscious.
-What do we do now?
-We stay close. Hope for a miracle.
That's all we can do.
No!
Don't leave me, okay?
Okay.
Target 626 is in motion. Speed is 84.
Impossible!
Stitch!
Abomination.
Stupid head.
You're vile! You're foul! You're flawed!
Also cute and fluffy!
You came back.
Nobody gets left behind.
Lilo!
Good dog.
David!
Hey, Lilo.
Can you give us a ride to shore?
Sure,
but I have to make two trips.
So you're from outer space?
I heard the surfing's choice.
We have 626.
Take him to my ship.
-Leave him alone.
-Hold on.
Grand Councilwoman, let me explain.
Silence!
I am retiring you, Captain Gantu.
Actually, credit for the capture
goes to...
Goes to me.
You'll be lucky if you end up
on a Fluff Trog farm
after we sort this thing out.
I think I should...
You! You're the cause of all this!
If it wasn't for your Experiment 626,
none of this...
-Stitch.
-What?
My name Stitch.
Stitch, then.
If it wasn't for Stitch...
Does Stitch have to go in the ship?
Yes.
Can Stitch say goodbye?
Thank you.
Who are you?
This is my family.
I found it all on my own.
It's little and broken, but still good.
Yeah. Still good.
Does he really have to go?
You know as well as I
that our laws are absolute.
I cannot change
what the council has decided.
Lilo, didn't you buy that thing
at the shelter?
Hey!
Three days ago,
I bought Stitch at the shelter.
I paid $2 for him. See this stamp?
I own him.
If you take him, you're stealing.
Aliens are all about rules.
You look familiar.
CIA. Roswell. 1973.
Yes. You had hair then.
Take note of this.
This creature has been sentenced
to life in exile,
a sentence that shall be
henceforth served out here
on Earth.
And as caretaker
of the alien life form, Stitch,
this family is now
under the official protection
of the United Galactic Federation.
We'll be checking in now and then.
I was afraid you were going to say that.
This won't be easy to explain
back at headquarters.
I know what you mean.
Don't let those two get on my ship.
CIA?
Former.
Saved the planet once.
Convinced an alien race
that mosquitoes were
an endangered species.
Now, about your house...
Wait.