Hi, this is Ron Clements,
I'm the co-writer,
co-director of Little Mermaid.
Hi, I'm John Musker, I'm the other guy,
the other co-director, co-writer
of The Little Mermaid.
Hi, I'm Alan Menken,
the composer of Little Mermaid.
You're gonna hear a lot
on this audio commentary
about Howard Ashman,
who I consider to be the greatest
theatrical dramatic talent
of our generation, as a writer.
Howard passed away before
Beauty and the Beast was released
and after Little Mermaid came out.
Coming up is an earlier interview
that Howard and I did
at the time of the release of the film,
and it's great to hear his voice
adding to ours.
This is Ron again.
We had a really tough time
getting this to work right
with the ship coming through the fog.
This is John.
This was generated by a computer
but then painted in traditional
ink and paint style.
You really saw a change
in perspective there,
in a way that we couldn't have done
with traditional animation.
We tried to keep color very low-key,
it's kind of an overcast day,
because we wanted to save the color
for when we went underwater...
We shot this with traditional
fog filters on the animation camera
just to give it the feeling of a foggy day.
This is Alan, and I remember
how many times Howard and I
took stabs at the top
of the movie musically.
We had a much longer song, originally,
which told the whole story of Eric
and the boat.
The back story of the witch and Triton,
there was a whole story created.
And a lot of dancing and sweeping.
It's a big, elaborate production number.
And it actually got story-boarded.
Roger Alters, the great story artist,
story-boarded it, it exists.
Ultimately, it seemed like it took
a little too long and was too involved,
so we went with a shorter,
trimmer version.
One thing we did want
to do, though, was
to start the movie on the water surface
and save going below,
'cause we felt it was like going
to Oz or something like that.
So, it's almost like this is our
black-and-white section
going into color now.
Classic moment for me is when
the fish jumps and hits the water
and we go into this theme,
and that's where the heart of the movie
just jumps out at you.
I remember we demoed this
so many times.
I can remember
you and Howard Ashman
were sitting there at the piano,
and Howard would be like,
"Alan, give me that musical figure,"
"something watery, something watery."
That's right.
And then Alan would come up
with this thing.
I'd never even heard
the term "musical figure" before,
and I'm like, "Well, that's what that is."
I'd create this little...
It came off the top of my head,
and it became this unmistakable
stamp, now, of Little Mermaid.
-Musical signature.
-Anytime one hears it...
And also, with any musical,
and Howard would say this too,
you have to establish right at the top
what are the rules for this musical.
If somebody is coming out
and they're on a stage,
and they're singing All That Jazz,
you go, "Okay, I get what this is."
If somebody comes out
and they're animated,
and they're doing a sea shanty
about the fable of The Little Mermaid,
you go, "Okay, I get..."
So long as you get what world
you're in, you can accept it.
Ron again.
This first shot of King Triton's palace
is a multi-plane shot.
After CAPS was developed,
a shot like this would be easy,
but at the time, if you wanted
to move in on something
and give some sense of dimension,
you needed to use multi-plane.
I think this film was the first
use of multi-plane since...
I think there might be a shot
in Jungle Book,
which was kind of reused
in The Rescuers, I think.
Those trumpet fish
were the first real explosion
-of higher key colors.
-Really bright color.
If you look, still-frame, as he passes
in front of the camera,
on the lower left corner of the screen,
you can see Mickey, Donald and Goofy
there in the audience, watching.
Will Ryan did the voice
of the little seahorse.
Speeded up a little bit.
You hear the fanfare
as Triton sweeps in,
and then when Sebastian comes in,
there's a little dinky fanfare,
and that is actually me
playing the kazoo.
Listen to the last note particularly.
We did have fun.
Sam Wright and Ken Mars
doing the voices of Sebastian the crab
and King Triton.
Sam Wright was wonderful
to work with.
He's been playing Mufasa
in The Lion King on Broadway,
but prior to that,
he'd been the father
in a musical called Tap Dance Kid.
He was in the
Fruit of the Loom commercials
as a dancing raisin or something.
A great, great comic actor and singer.
He was one of the New York actors,
both he and Jodi Benson
were cast without John
or I having ever met them in person,
we just heard their voices on tape,
'cause they auditioned in New York,
but we loved what they were doing.
Ellen Woodbury did some
of this animation here.
-And Will Finn I think did some.
-And Will Finn as well, yeah.
In the lyrics coming up in this song,
when you talk about the sisters,
among the sisters,
Atina is a musical I had written,
actually, that
Michael Bennett produced,
called Atina: Evil Queen of the Galaxy,
which was a big flopperoney.
Arista, Attina
Adella, Alana
And Howard, in the lyrics,
makes reference to Alana,
and that was Howard's way
of including me in the lyrics.
One other bit, Andrina was actually
my aerobics teacher at the time,
-I was taking an aerobics class.
-Is that right?
We used to have more dialogue
in this scene,
we had a backstage scene
that got cut out.
It's like, "Where's Ariel?
She's not here! What am I gonna do?"
And then he's forced out
onto the stage.
We just liked the staging
of the shells opening.
It just seemed kind of fun and
it's a little campy, I guess.
But we liked it and Howard
went along with it eventually,
but we had to sell him on the idea.
Howard always had very specific ideas
of how he visualized the staging.
This set-up shot of the sunken ship
has cross-dissolving beams.
Mike Peraza, our art director,
did the layout for this.
It really helps set a great mood
for the rest of this sequence.
We knew this movie would have
more effects animation
than any movie that had been done
in a long time.
And virtually every scene underwater
has effects in it,
it has either bubbles,
or light refractions or distortion.
It added a huge amount of complexity,
but it's just a really great motivator
in getting the whole crew together,
knowing that they were facing,
in some sense...
I think we presented it as almost
an impossible challenge.
People like impossible challenges,
because it gets them excited,
and I think
the whole effects department
was very excited about
the challenge of this film.
Alan had never written an underscore
for any movie before,
and he wanted to do it,
and we were interested in doing it,
but he'd never done it before,
"so we said," Let's use this
as kind of a dry run, so to speak,
"or a trial run, and let Alan get
his fins wet on this one."
So, this was the first thing he wrote.
I was terrified.
It was an action cue,
it wasn't just a romantic cue,
it was something where you really had
to hook into the...
There's a big shark chase
coming up and all that stuff,
so Alan had to hit all these accents
and beats and all that,
so it was something different for Alan.
And I also remember,
when we scored the movie,
this was the first cue that we recorded.
I remember sitting next
to the orchestrator,
I listened to it, and I said,
"Oh, my God, this is awful."
"Oh, my God, this is just terrible."
And I see Howard and John and Ron
conferring at the front,
their heads are down
and they're talking to each other.
"And I'm thinking," Oh, my God,
"they're trying to figure out
how to fire me."
Then finally Howard gets up slowly
and walks over to me
behind the board.
I said, "Yeah, I know it's terrible.
We can work on..."
He says, "No, in this one measure,
"could you move
this one beat forward?"
I said, "Yes. "He says, "That's great."
I made a choice to do this
very much in the style
of the earlier animated features,
in which, instead of sound effects,
you're basically using music for a fall,
or music for an impact or for anything,
almost like ballet.
So, it's a very busy score.
I learned how to get less busy
after Little Mermaid.
I might also mention
that the shark here
is animated by Matt O'Callaghan,
who story-boarded
this sequence as well,
and that doesn't always happen.
So, he really shaped it,
both in terms of the storyboarding,
and then he wound up
animating the shark,
as well as Louis, the chef, later on.
The shark, his name is Glut,
although his name is never
brought up in the movie,
he was originally going
to return later in the movie,
and Flounder was going
to actually defeat him
and Flounder would have
his moment of glory, finally.
But as we simplified the story,
Glut never does return.
When this sequence
was first developed,
there was Flounder,
but Ariel also had another companion,
a dolphin, which we called Breaker,
but he left very quickly.
We thought that there were too many
characters with her along for the ride.
So we gave some of
Breaker's personality,
which was a very energetic,
gung-ho type,
we moved that into Ariel,
and that actually made her
a more lively sort of character,
to give her some
of the dolphin's personality.
If they would have given us
more money,
some of these scenes where
Scuttle was walking on this rock,
would've had more contact shadows,
where you'd see his shadow
cast on the rock,
but that was a concession
to the budget
and the time restraints
that we were under,
that we didn't put those things
in the film.
I miss them.
Buddy Hackett.
Buddy Hackett. There was
a different voice for Scuttle, originally.
Our boss, Jeffrey Katzenberg,
didn't like the other voice we had.
He's like, "Guys, guys, get a comedian.
That's what we did on Oliver."
"Richard Mulligan, we got him
and the character came alive."
"Find a comedian."
We went through a list of comedians...
Buddy improvised some here,
which we encouraged,
I think that was fun.
He also, when we first recorded Buddy,
he had written a song for Scuttle.
Have you heard
the song that he wrote?
No, but he actually sang it
on The Tonight Show.
Yeah, he did sing it
You'll never know what lonely is
till you live by yourself on a rock
Once we cast Buddy, we wrote it
to sound like Buddy,
and Buddy was saying,
"Don't write for me, write for the part."
His very first takes,
he was playing Scuttle
with an artificial seagull voice
that we kind of thought,
"This is not the way to go."
We wanted him to just be himself
and be natural,
which he did, and he was great,
but there was a little bit of tension
just at the very beginning
of his first session.
Jason Marin,
who did the voice for Flounder,
his voice changed
by the end of the movie,
and we were trying to get Little Jason.
He came in, "Yes, I'm here
to do the finishing lines on Flounder."
We're like, "Jason, can you just..."
He had to cheat it up a little bit.
We like to give characters entrances,
and so to give Ursula theatrics,
we really wanted her
to come out of shadow,
even the sort of descent
into the camera
is all just meant to give her theatrics.
She's a very theatrical character.
The first time we screened
this with an audience,
and we see that she's an octopus
for the first time,
there was an audible reaction
from the audience,
just a little shudder.
And that made it feel like,
"Yeah, that's working for her intro."
Seriously, 'cause originally, the witch
wasn't conceived to be an octopus,
she was a different fish, but not octopi,
but it really went with
the musical approach,
in terms of the silky, tentacly,
trying to wrap Ariel in
and reel her in snakily.
The snake charmer thing in here,
I think, worked well with Alan's music.
On the witch, we actually took
some live-action footage
from a documentary,
Disney Mysteries of the Deep,
and Roy Disney was
very versed and familiar with that,
and worked on that
and brought that to our attention.
Rob Minkoff, the initial animator
of Ursula,
did a walk cycle literally on top of that.
So her lower half was this octopus.
We really were able to get
real-life observed behavior,
combined with the character
of this big, overweight,
but exaggeratedly
graceful vamp, villainess.
And that really became the basis
for all her movements later.
Well, it was ruined! That's all!
Completely destroyed!
This concert was to be the pinnacle...
Ed Gombert was one of the great
storyboard artists
that worked on the film,
and he really came up with
the recounting of the tale
that Flounder does
and the way it was played,
and that's really pure Ed Gombert
in there.
Probably, you can see it,
if you look at a still frame,
Flounder actually
transforms into Scuttle
for a couple of frames there
as he's talking about Scuttle,
he physically transforms to Scuttle.
But then this seagull came, and it was,
"This is this, and that is that..."
Most of these bubbles are hand-inked,
which is a throwback to the old-school,
most of this movie is done with
the Xerox process,
which is something that was done
from 101 Dalmatians forward.
Little Mermaid was actually the last film
to use cels and Xerox.
Right, the older films, Snow White
and Pinocchio, were hand-inked.
There was actually a person
who traced the hand drawings
of the animation onto cels.
The Xerox process actually
photographed them onto cels.
However, to get the look
of those older movies,
we really wanted the bubbles
to be inked, so, in fact, they were,
but as a way of trying
to do it on budget,
those were actually inked in China.
So, the problem for us was,
when the Tiananmen Square incident
was happening in China in 1989,
it looked like there could be
a civil war in China,
and we weren't sure
we were gonna get
our cels back
with the bubbles on them.
Our bubbles were trapped in China.
The bubbles were trapped in China.
Tim Engel, who was really
overseeing all that, said,
"There's a possibility that we may
not be seeing any more bubbles."
And the movie was under the wire.
We were praying
for democracy in China.
But also praying
we got our bubbles back.
That was very funny.
Once again, we got our bubbles.
They came.
I don't know about democracy
in China, but...
The crab was animated
by Duncan Marjoribanks.
I'm always amused whenever I see it,
"'cause I think of 6'5"
Duncan Marjoribanks
animating this teeny little thing.
It's one of the great things
about animation,
that the animators don't have to look
like the characters they portray.
Also, Andreas Deja animated Triton,
who, I think, he's always said
he based on his father somewhat.
Without the fins, yeah.
A lot of these underwater scenes
involve those little
patterns of tight there,
those are live-action patterns,
the way you see light playing
under a swimming pool almost,
and those were double exposed over
the painted backgrounds we drew
to give a watery effect.
That's a technique we generally used,
as well as filters over the film,
to make this all seem like
it was happening underwater.
Mark Dindal, the head of effects,
who later became the director
of The Emperor's New Groove
and Chicken Little,
he came up with this effect.
It's actually fairly simple
and not that expensive to do,
but it added a lot
to the underwater scenes.
Particularly, in the song,
Part of Your World,
it gives an extra magic to that,
and was used more extensively there.
As you can see,
all the refractions of light
where the light is hitting
the underwater sections.
This pan of the grotto,
I think we made this too short.
It moves too fast, I think.
If we had to do this all over again,
it would've let you see things
just a little bit more.
But it's a nice shot.
If only I could make him understand.
I just don't see things the way he does.
We should mention,
in terms of this song,
that one of the very early screenings
we had for an audience,
we brought in a class of school kids
into the studio,
this sequence was pretty much
all black-and-white,
it didn't have the effects
and everything there,
and in the very first screening,
the kids squirmed a lot.
That brought up
the very controversial thing
that there was some talk
of either cutting this song
or cutting it down,
which, pretty much,
Howard was horrified at the idea,
we were horrified, Alan was horrified,
Glen Keane, who was
the lead animator on all this
and responsible for a lot of it,
was horrified.
And even though there was
a lot of discussion,
it finally came to a point where
we could leave it in the way it was
for an additional screening now.
And in this second screening,
there was more color.
For whatever reason, however,
it worked out, they didn't squirm.
They were quiet through
the whole number.
Thank God.
You know they almost cut
Over the Rainbow
from The Wizard of Oz.
And that was one of our arguments
with this song.
Howard's contention was
every musical needs a point
at which its central character,
the protagonist,
sits down on a garbage pail,
on a rock in the sea,
and says, "This is what I dream of."
And, of course, the rest of the story
is all based on creating obstacles
that this character has to overcome
to achieve their dream.
It sets Ariel's character, it sets her up,
what she wants, what she needs,
and so much of the rooting interest
of the mermaid comes out of this song.
And certainly, I think, we're all
very glad this wasn't tampered with,
'cause it's such a signature
of the movie.
Also, the earlier lyrics to this song,
I might mention,
Howard generally resisted
changes that we would suggest,
and rightfully so, 'cause many
of my own personal ideas were stupid,
but one that he did actually
slightly agree on,
his earlier lyrics of this song,
he talked about leather in China
and things like that.
And we said to Howard,
"Well, her information is from this guy"
"who doesn't have his story straight,
the seagull."
So Howard went back
and readjusted the lyrics,
so he put in the thingamabobs
and the whatchamacallits.
Those weren't in the first version
of the song.
'Cause he agreed that, yeah,
that actually was in character for her,
to have these offbeat terms for things.
That painting right there,
Glen Keane picked out that painting
'cause he wanted a picture, an image
of a fire underwater to go with the lyric.
This shot where Ariel reaches out
was the last shot done in the movie.
We wanted to do that
on the multi-plane camera,
and there were just too many problems
and we ended up doing it optically.
At the time,
it was technically very difficult,
and I think it was shot four or five times
and didn't turn out right.
The opticals didn't match right,
it had seams...
Her arm would not go outside
the hole properly.
And it got to a point that
we were running out of time, literally,
and we were on a budget
and other restrictions,
we had one last chance
to get that shot to work
or we had to use a compromise shot
that was a shot that we developed
as a last-minute resort,
where she didn't reach out
beyond the thing.
And the very last time, it worked.
Sebastian's presence as the witness
of the song is partly there
to mitigate the squirm factor.
He's judgmental about it, and you have
that extra dramatic tension.
If it's just being done
as a solo in one moment,
it becomes a little eggy
for an audience, a little bit cloying.
Now, for the students of film,
they can see some mistakes here.
Watch this thimble on his foot,
sometimes he's got it...
Now, no thimble, it's gone magically.
But now it's back.
Who let that mistake through?
This is your sequence.
It's my sequence, yes.
Ron directed some sequences
and I directed some sequences.
And this was Ron's sequence.
It's a nice sequence.
It's a beautiful sequence,
I wish I had done it.
We didn't have time
to redo everything on this.
We were aware of a lot of the mistakes.
But there were severe budget
and time restrictions,
in terms of making this film,
so we had to pick our spots carefully,
in terms of what we could fix
and what we had to leave.
Dorse Lanpher, great effects
animator, did the fireworks in that shot.
It really helped.
Thom Enriquez was the storyboard
artist that story-boarded this sequence.
Beautiful draftsmanship.
Our story team on the film overall
was really an amazing story team,
many of which have gone on
to be directors, art directors,
production designers...
In this scene,
we see several of the staff,
including the guy dancing,
Rasoul Azadani,
who was a layout artist on that,
and who we've worked with pretty
much in all the movies that we've done.
This dog, Max, we added,
didn't really exist in the fairytale,
but we wanted to give the Prince
a companion to bounce off of.
He was colored gray,
he was a big Sheepdog.
We did have a nightmare
with the paint of this character,
because a lot of times,
that gray would just crawl on film.
You can still see it, here and there,
it's a tough color to make work.
Mark Henn animated
these scenes of Ariel
as she came up over the side,
and I think he really did a great job
of capturing her innocence
and just her wide-eyedness
at this whole new world
that she's looking at,
the Prince in particular.
This is really the heart
of the story here, obviously,
her falling in love with the Prince.
This is one of the pieces
of music that I wrote first
as a source piece for you to animate to.
Right.
I know you talked about Grieg.
Although, I don't really know Grieg.
Yeah, it's sort of a little bit of
Hall of the Mountain King.
And Grieg was Danish,
so it all made sense somehow.
One of the more difficult
characters in this film was Prince Eric,
and there's a tradition
of Disney princes,
that they hadn't worked very well.
In Cinderella, I talked to Eric Larson,
who animated on it,
he said, "Yeah, he was stiff,
I didn't really get it right."
Animating the prince has been called
the most thankless job in animation,
because it's probably harder
to do than any other character...
Even in the Andersen fairytale,
you don't get much of a sense
of the Prince,
as much as you do
of the Little Mermaid,
and that's a challenge.
The more realistic human characters
are always the most difficult,
but, still, a character like Ariel
is still more fun.
Particularly, Ariel was a great heroine.
She at least had the extra aspect
that she was part fish,
and she could swim underwater
and she can move in ways
that humans couldn't possibly move,
and that's why his screen time
tends to be more limited too,
because it's just difficult.
We had Matt O'Callaghan
who animated the Prince,
Mike Cedeno.
Christopher Barnes did
the voice on the Prince,
and I think he did a really nice job
of trying to get an engaging,
likeable guy.
The storm sequence coming up
was actually one of the first sequences
done on the movie, along with
the Under the Sea sequence
and the Louis sequence,
those were actually the first things
that we actually started animation on.
Because it was almost like
a musical sequence,
in that it was so rich
in production value,
if we didn't do it early,
we knew that we might not get it done,
'cause it would take longer
and there'd be impulses
to simplify it and cut it,
and we'd be under the gun,
so we knew it would be difficult,
so the sooner we could get to it,
the better.
We called them "money shots."
Which, I guess, means that we're
gonna spend extra money on them.
It was also because it was
an action sequence,
there were just so many aspects of it
that could be done earlier on,
whereas sequences that were
primarily character-driven,
we almost wanted to save until
the animators had a little more time
with the characters.
This sequence certainly is a tour
de force of effects animation,
the fact that it was done first
really gave us a chance to go all out.
And Mark Dindal, who was
the head of effects on the movie,
did a great job on this sequence.
The gray-green cast of the skies
in all this
was inspired by an N.C. Wyeth
painting he had done,
I think it's from Kidnapped,
or one of these,
where there's a shipwrecked figure
in the foreground
and a ship in the background.
And that was the inspiration
for the visual look of this sequence.
I never had a successful solution
for this scene,
I directed this sequence,
and I wanted to be able
to see the statue before it sank,
so we cheated,
so the statue was floating for a minute.
It's a marble statue,
it made no sense whatsoever,
but I couldn't figure it out. "How do
we show that before it goes away?"
So, it was bizarre, but there it is.
The water animation
is beautifully done.
And water is very difficult
to animate convincingly,
and Ted Kierscey did a lot of it,
and a lot of the animators.
It's funny, when you score
a sequence like this,
every hit becomes a source
of stress for you.
Leading up to the session, you want
to make sure each hit is gonna work,
so they're all imprinted indelibly
on my brain.
I like that jazzy horn figure
for the action
when he's running across the ship.
I think that was cool.
I remember this was
very early scoring for me.
I should point out that
the orchestrations
were done by Thomas Pasatieri.
He was a great help to me
in learning the art of scoring.
Animation was not, at that point, hip.
I remember a film composer,
it was difficult, I was asking his advice,
"and he said," Look, man,
"nobody takes a score
from an animated film seriously."
He said, "Just take a powder."
-He just meant like...
-Phone it in.
You think about how that must've
turned on its ear within five years.
And now we're into the reprise
of Part of Your World.
Here's a rare interview
that Howard and I did
at the time of the release of the film.
Alan writes great ballads,
I think that's one of Alan's real gifts,
is Alan can bring
a tear to your eye pretty quick.
And ballads are really, really hard
in a musical for the whole family,
because kids aren't famous
for liking love songs.
So it's hard to write a song that moves,
and has a little bit of rhythm,
and also tugs at your heartstrings
and is a soft number.
And the challenge of this number was
to do a ballad that
also moved the plot forward,
which is why the subject matter
of being part of your world
was so important.
What is she realty longing for?
What is going to not just stop the action
but keep everything moving?
This is John here.
Howard's lyrics on this,
again, the original version
was slightly different,
in that Howard played the lyric of this
as, kind of, that she was disappointed,
and the original lyric on this was,
"I'll never be part of that world."
And she was sad
as she dove into the water.
I remember we talked
with Howard about it
and said, just because
of the shape of the story,
she's gonna be kind of moony
about the Prince
and feeling up about it.
We said we thought, actually,
it would be better to play this
as an up thing.
And Howard, again, that was the only
other thing we ever talked Howard into,
and he agreed
and he revised the lyrics
so that it was much more
of a positive statement
than a statement of regret or sadness.
Howard did mention to us early on
there was an element of this that was
like a handicapped girl
wanting to walk.
And I think that's what he drew on
for the lyrics of the song, partly.
Actually, the song itself should be
titled Part of that World.
And this is Part of Your World.
-They've both taken on one title.
-Yeah, that's true.
Glen Keane animated much
of Ariel in this part,
a great animator,
and he did this scene where
she's on the rock,
and I remember we shot this
with Sherri Stoner,
but Glen acted out this scene for her.
And Glen is a burly,
football-player-looking kind of a guy,
and there he was,
he's doing this action of just tentatively
coming up over the rock,
and I still remember
Glen's physical performance,
it had all the sensitivity that you see
here in his drawn version,
but picture a muscular
Gene Kelly kind of a guy doing this.
Here it is, a moment of determination.
Every teenage girl's desire
to be free of her parents.
It's a major story moment.
Everything up to that point
is really set-up.
Now the situation is really clear
that we've got a mermaid
who is in conflict with her father,
who wants something that is
forbidden in her world
and will do whatever it takes to get it.
Her daddy will love that.
King Triton's headstrong, lovesick girl...
I might mention Kathy Zielinski
animated the witch in this sequence.
And there aren't a ton of
women animators,
but she's one of
the best animators, period.
But she did
a great job with the witch there.
Those fish in that opening shot
were computer fish,
which we thought we might
use more of in the movie,
but at this point,
the computer animation
was not quite at a point where
we were totally happy with it.
So we used the computer fish
to a minimum,
but they were in that one shot.
And I do believe that this scene of Ariel
was the first scene of Ariel animated
in the entire movie.
Mark Henn animated this scene.
In the story reels,
we had a longer version,
and there were fish doing their hair
and there were various things
with the sisters that we took out.
Howard and I were both huge fans
of the earlier animated features.
He felt that
as the musical updated itself,
the animated musical
would also update itself.
For us, Little Mermaid was
the follow-up
to Little Shop of Horrors.
As different as they are, it really was.
And there are people who joke and call
Part of Your World,
"Somewhere That's Wet."
I haven't heard that.
-The other thing I want to say about...
-That's funny.
That's a joke on
Somewhere That's Green.
And so, we did a pastiche of
'50s and '60s rock and roll,
Little Mermaid, we did really
our own pastiche of Disney.
When we started working
on Sebastian,
first you guys had Sebastian
as a stuffy English...
Clarence the crab.
Reggae was very hip and Howard said,
"Let's make him a Jamaican crab"
"or a Caribbean crab. Calypso."
I think of Harry Belafonte,
that kind of warmth.
And so here are some thoughts
from an earlier interview
with myself and Howard Ashman.
It's very hard to write
contemporary sounding music
in a fairytale context.
You're dealing with
long ago and far away.
And you really still want to have
a feeling that modern kids and adults
can enjoy and start to move to,
because that's how you get energy.
And it was sort of a trick.
When I talked to John and Ron
before the script was actually written,
we had a long conference about that.
Was there a way we could give
the crab something in his personality
that would make it possible to have
a special kind of music that had
some kind of rhythmic edge
or contemporary feeling to it?
And what we came up with was that
there would be a Jamaican flavor
to what he did in the music.
And that was to get energy,
to get a little bit of a pop feeling,
and yet to have it be true
to its fairytale roots.
This song you guys finished
in Burbank.
We started out actually
at my farm in Pennsylvania,
and Howard said he always wanted
a figure that just circled back on itself.
That didn't end, so the song
really started with the figure.
And one of the things I always talk
about is in the world of animation,
they're so specific in their references,
and you guys especially,
so as we made all these references,
they animated the references.
And then when we went back
to scoring,
you guys wanted every one of
these things that you had animated
caught with different orchestral colors.
So you'll notice where there's
all these different sea creatures,
every single one is caught
with a very specific scoring reference.
And I remember
when we were working on this,
Alan was right next to us,
and Robby Merkin,
who was doing the arrangements
was right down the hall.
So they would go back and forth with
the storyboard artists and with us
and be seeing hits
that we were suggesting
or a different fish they could use.
And they'd come back, "Which one was
this again, that was doing this part?"
It was the overdub session of all time.
That's all I can say.
Overdub means
after you've recorded the basic track,
then you add other parts.
We did have to fight a bit
with Jeffrey on this,
in that we wanted to use colors as
the song got progressively more joyous
and that the color changed to
these oranges and these reds.
And Jeffrey had a hard time.
He's like, "Underwater is blue, guys."
And so we had
to convince him it's okay.
So in some scenes, we had to sneak
a little blue in the corners
to keep Jeffrey happy, but eventually,
he went along with it.
We felt the mood of the song,
no one's gonna worry that
it's not blue anymore. It's hot.
Howard recorded the demo vocal
on this one and he was just...
A lot of the jokiness of Sam's reading.
Sam did a great job, but Howard,
his original demo was full of spice.
Howard's vocals were definitely
the blueprint for the final result.
I think Sam's rendition of this song was
one of the big things, in terms of
getting cast for the role, because
we heard a lot of actors sing that song
and a lot of them were very good,
and certainly Howard set the tone for it.
But I think Sam just did
an incredible job with this song.
The interesting thing about Sam.
Howard auditioned him in New York.
And we cast him
never having met Sam,
but we heard a tape of Sam.
And he was so great just on the tape
that we said, "That's the guy to do it."
And then we really met Sam the first
time when he came in to record it.
We had never really
met him before at all.
The song that changed
the Academy Awards.
Alan won Oscars continuously...
I think there were eight,
but who's counting?
Every Academy Award
that Alan was involved in,
he would win multiple Oscars.
-Usually score and song.
-Don't they come in pairs?
Then at a certain point,
the Academy changed the awards
so that musical scores
would be a separate category.
We always looked at that, that that was
the Alan Menken adjustment
or whatever.
But Alan was winning so many awards,
and everyone else felt left out,
so they had to change the awards
so that other people
would have a chance.
Remember, I showed up for
the Academy Awards,
and they had me seated on the aisle,
which I guess said something,
because prior to that, I had been sitting
in the middle of the aisle
where I could never escape.
And I said to my friend, Dean Pitchford,
who wrote Fame and Footloose,
I said, "I don't know, what do
you think's going to happen?"
He says, "I don't know
who's gonna win the Oscar,
"but I looked backstage"
"and the Academy Award
had scales on it."
This sequence was very early
in production,
Ron directed this sequence.
This was the first stuff done
on the crab, it seemed like...
Yeah, it was the first animation
done on the crab.
Duncan Marjoribanks did the crab
in this
and Andreas Deja did Triton.
And Ed Gombert story-boarded this
and it's pretty much...
The water is just fantastic
to look at there.
But this was
a little sample of the movie
in a way that went first and as I say,
Ed Gombert story-boarded it,
and it pretty much is exactly
the way he story-boarded it.
And it is just a nice little bit
between the two of them
that we were very happy
with the way it turned out.
And it gave a nice sense
of setting those two characters.
But it's not a complicated scene
from a directorial standpoint,
except from the acting standpoint
that it's realty getting
a certain kind of dynamic in contrast.
It certainly is fun with the huge,
imposing character,
like the sea king and the little
teeny character like the crab
just kind of carrying on
everyday conversation
like they're not conscious at all
of their size difference.
We always thought Ariel's grotto was
like a teenage girl's bedroom,
and she's got her poster of a rock star
who was the Prince.
And that was the person
that she was infatuated with.
And we were trying to draw
the analogy with modern teenagers
and their trouble
with their fathers, obviously.
Overprotective parents
and kids that don't want to
have to be tied down by their parents.
If you notice, the statue gets
madder and madder
as the sequence progresses.
-Is that right?
-His expression just keeps getting...
Was that an accident
or was that deliberate?
Not just the King,
but the statue gets madder, too.
I never noticed that.
But, Dad, I...
Is it true you rescued a human
from drowning?
The father-daughter
relationship in this movie
I find to be one of the most emotional.
Possibly because I've had
two teenage daughters
and seen them grow up.
Yeah, my daughter was born
as we were making this,
and now she's more this age,
so I've seen it from both ends.
We got a lot of letters in terms of
this movie.
And there's fan letters
from people who liked the movie.
But I'd say we got more serious letters
from fathers and daughters
and things that
they were emotionally involved in.
In some cases, at least
with one father in particular,
that this kind of brought about
a reconciliation
with his daughter
who he was estranged by.
And that was nice
to get letters like that.
The only thing I find difficult is the idea
that she's Triton's favorite daughter.
The idea of having
a favorite daughter seems...
It's contrary to someone
who's got more than one daughter.
Our theory was
that she's the most like him,
and that that in effect was
what created the conflict.
To the extent that we said when Triton
was a younger man, he had red hair.
That they clashed
because they're both strong willed
and individualistic.
The children's book illustrator, Chris
Van Allsburg, did some drawings for us
when we were trying to develop
the look of the film,
and he did one of Triton's palace
with greens and golds,
and he also did a study
of the moonlit grotto
that was one of the earliest visual
representations of Ariel's grotto.
Paddi Edwards did the voice of
Flotsam and Jetsam,
and this voice was treated a bit,
but really, Paddi did have a very
distinctive, raspy, great, unique voice
that we thought
was perfect for these two.
And they're animated by Shawn Keller,
who's a quirky, nice guy,
but got a lot of
sinister mileage out of these guys.
What's very effective about them
is the idea that they trade off their lines
in a totally seamless way.
But there is something.
Howard was extremely specific
about what he wanted.
It was always a big concession
for Howard to have me play any role,
'cause he frankly
would like to have played every role.
It carried over with the actors when
Jodi was performing the number,
Howard had so many specific things
in his head and Jodi contributed a lot,
but Howard had phrasing ideas and
things that really were wrapped into
his approach to it. And Pat Carroll,
really, he helped steer her through it.
Certain songs more than others.
But the phrasing
just was very, very specific.
I know a few people
who could have written Ursula,
but nobody at the level of the way
Howard wrote her.
Howard had said that
one of the things he always wanted
to do was run a children's theater.
So you combine that with that West
Broadway or West Village sensibility
and you get a sense
of who the man was.
Tremendously emotional person
and also so hip and so cutting edge,
as far as the zeitgeist of our culture.
And certainly here, it's in Ursula,
but I remember Howard said
our assignment was
to write a score
for an animated musical
that could sit on the shelf alongside
Cinderella and Dumbo
and Peter Pan and Pinocchio
and, of course, Snow White.
That's what he always said. Right.
No! No!
She's a demon. She's a monster.
Why don't you go tell my father?
You're good at that.
That was Ron's line, "Why don't you
tell my father? You're good at that."
And I've always liked that line
just because it's so teenage girlish.
-Well, it was John's line.
-Believable.
"Teenagers, they think
they know everything."
"You give them an inch
and they swim all over you."
This exterior, the witch's place,
Mike Peraza, who is our art director,
did that really cool layout
of that sea creature
and her actual shell,
he designed that as well,
and I always thought it was kind of
Georgia O'Keeffe-esque.
Those out-of-focus, dangling tendrils
in the foreground,
that was actually shot
on a multi-plane camera.
The one done off the lot at Disney,
'cause the only one we could find
that was up and working
was actually done by a cameraman
that Mark Dindal knew
who shot stuff for Filmation.
So that's one of two or three
multi-plane shots in the movie.
A few of these first scenes
of the witch were animated
by Rob Minkoff,
but then he left to do other things,
and Ruben Aquino really did
98% of the witch
and most of this song coming up,
and this animation here
is Ruben's animation.
And he did a beautiful job,
in terms of just getting her personality,
as well as just the technical issue
of keeping all these tentacles alive
and moving, and I loved what he did.
Of course, Rob had also done an early
exploratory drawing
that Howard had really liked
and we had really liked of the witch,
where Howard said, "This is great,
she looks like a Miami Beach matron."
And we got into
a whole thing about Divine.
Divine is a cross-dressing guy,
George was...
What was his real name?
-His real name was Glen, but...
-Glen, okay, yeah.
Everyone knows Divine as Divine.
People also know Divine, of course,
as the original Edna Turnblad
from the hit movie, Hairspray.
He was from Baltimore,
where Howard was from, I think.
And so, some of the early
development art
that Rob was doing
and others were doing
was really trying to get some of
Divine's big, campy, overweight diva,
get that into the witch.
And so there are still vestiges
of it in the witch,
although at one point, the witch even
had a mohawk  la Pink Flamingos
-and all that.
-Also Divine.
Also, Divine played that character,
and Jeffrey thought that was
a little too extreme.
I don't think Jeffrey was aware
that we were relating it to Divine,
he just looked at us and he's like,
"Guys, it's 10% too much."
I think he was right on that,
as I remember, it was pretty extreme.
Just want to point out
the voice of Pat Carroll.
We knew Pat Carroll
from the Danny Thomas show.
And we really had a hard time
casting the witch,
because Howard had done
so great with the demos.
It was hard to find anybody
that could match Howard.
And then Pat Carroll came in
and she really did a great job.
Nailed it.
I know. She always talked about
how it was a cross between
Tallulah Bankhead and Maurice Evans,
Shakespearean thing in this vampy,
throaty Southern belle or something.
And that's what she got
in the performance.
But on the whole I've been a saint
To those poor unfortunate souls
Now, here's the deal.
I will make you a potion that will turn
you into a human for three days.
Actually, this song was done
in two separate sessions.
We did it, and then
we went back and did it again
-just to get all the nuances.
-Right.
I think Jeffrey was pushing for that.
She did a fantastic job.
Gary Trousdale story-boarded
this sequence.
And he really tried to visualize
all this deal making.
And I thought he did a great job
of really making it visual,
so that we'd understand,
even without the soundtrack,
what's at stake here.
Some thoughts
from Howard Ashman again.
We wanted to make songs
that would tell the story,
songs that would really
move the story forward,
really push the plot along
and keep things driving ahead.
So, it's not like you stop
and sing a song.
To my mind,
this recalls what it feels like
to write a successful musical
for the stage.
We were there at the genesis,
and we saw it through every step
of the way with our collaborators.
Life's full of tough choices, isn't it?
We perform when we write.
You have to.
Howard is the actor.
Pat Carroll is wonderful, but
you haven't heard the witch's number
until you've heard Howard perform it.
And you never should.
It's wonderful.
I generally get to play things like Ariel.
Just 'cause you're shorter.
Everybody would rather write
for Captain Hook than for Peter Pan.
They're just more fun.
I don't know why.
And Ursula's an especially fun villain,
not only 'cause she looks
like an octopus,
you have that great movement
with her lower regions.
But she's also very sophisticated
as a character.
She's much more verbal.
Then as a lyricist, that was fun for me,
because I got to make more rhymes
and more puns
and more sophisticated
humor with her.
I see her song as a comedy number,
first of all, and a character number.
And then, third, talk about things
that are driving the plot forward.
At the beginning of that song,
Ariel doesn't even know
who Ursula is practically.
And by the end of that song,
she's a human.
So, a whole lot changes
in that little three-minute sequence.
I think we are thinking of something
almost Kurt Weill-ish
from The Threepenny Opera,
for the basic feel of that number.
And it's very seductive
and Ursula's very seductive.
And she's seducing Ariel
into making this deal.
I remember when we did this, Howard
talked about the shape of this number,
and I'd never really heard that term
used, as far as music went.
But he was talking about how,
in terms of this last thing with the spell,
that it almost was like
a three-act play in itself or something.
Well, it's a big musical scene.
You have the basic body of the song.
You break for the dialogue when she's
outlining the terms of the contract.
Then she comes back in full
on the end of the song,
-and then we transfer into the spell.
-The spell section.
One thing we haven't talked about,
which is so great
about you and Howard
and the songs that you did,
is the storytelling aspect.
There are a lot of bad musicals,
where sometimes
you cut the songs out
and sometimes it seems better.
And the songs are so much a part
of just telling this story.
They're integral to the story
and they advance things.
We have to be good thieves.
We always have to take
from your script,
and sometimes take the best aspects
and incorporate it into our songs,
and cover as much of the plot
as we possibly can.
This shot, I might mention,
we always thought of it
as our Sports Illustrated shot.
But it was this backlit thing
and a girl in the water, like
a shampoo commercial or something.
There was something picturesque
we wanted to do about it.
In the Andersen story,
when the mermaid walks,
she left bloody footprints and all.
We didn't really want to do that,
but we did want to make this transition
where she got her legs
feel a little bit painful,
in an homage
almost to the Andersen thing.
That exterior of the palace,
Rowland Wilson designed...
He is a great draftsman.
He designed the Prince's palace.
He did a drawing that we loved
that combined
these Mediterranean elements.
It made it a palace unlike any other
Disney fairytale palace.
And with the whitewashed stucco,
it was really going for a warm
Southern Mediterranean feel
that he thought would be attractive
to a mermaid
who had been stuck all her life
in the cold ocean.
We had a challenge here to stage this,
because technically, in between
those legs and that upper body,
she's really not wearing any clothes.
So, we had to get her dressed
and yet keep it discreet.
So, it was staged in a way
where she was underwater
in this sequence. That helped us.
There's such a feeling to this movie
in scenes like this
that is just infused
with this fantastic innocence.
And it always makes
you feel just wonderful.
I got it. It's your hairdo, right?
You've been usin'
the dinglehopper, right?
No? No, huh? Well, let me see.
New seashells?
This scene right here,
where the crab goes through
this slight nervous breakdown,
and then comes through and decides
he's actually going to help Ariel,
actually Howard wrote that.
-That was added.
-Wrote the dialogue for that.
We had the basis of the scene,
but we were struggling.
And actually, Michael Eisner
had felt that
the crab needed
a real turning point here.
And we were really knee-deep in stuff
and a little bit burned out.
Howard wrote this scene,
and it's a beautiful scene.
-Is that right?
-Yeah, he did.
In terms of where the crab
comes around and says,
"You're going to be miserable
for the rest of your life."
This is Howard's dialogue here.
Because Michael Eisner
felt like his change
from being against Ariel to being
her ally in this happened offstage
in our earlier version
that we showed him, and he said,
"Unless you show that onstage,
people aren't going to understand."
I think it was a good point.
He was right.
And Howard did a great job
of comically putting this over.
When he goes from, "I'm not going to
help you. This is the worst thing ever."
To, "Okay, I'll help you."
And he did a great job.
Howard, of course,
as a book writer on our musicals,
he was an executive producer on this
and on Beauty and the Beast.
Actually, he moved out here
and was living out here.
But what a resource to have that
kind of person offstage, so to speak.
It says, "Additional dialogue
by Howard Ashman,"
if you watch the end credits.
There were two or three scenes where
he did rewrite some of the dialogue.
And this was the key one, really.
We weren't sure when he came in,
in terms of how that might work,
and he didn't write for a while
aside from the songs.
He held back.
Not that we would have had
a problem with it.
For whatever reason,
he held back for a while.
And he was involved with our writing
and would make suggestions
and would make things.
But he didn't write himself
until this point.
And then Howard stepped in
and wrote this,
wrote two or three other bits
that are all really memorable,
great little moments in the movie.
I never knew that.
I'd love to know where they are.
We'll tell you as we're going through.
We were really going for a watercolor
look with these backgrounds,
where you see the highlights really
almost showing through the paper,
that was really a throwback
to a Pinocchio painting style
and that kind of a thing,
in terms of the way this looks.
Glen Keane animated Ariel
in this section.
We did use live-action reference
for both Ariel and Eric
to help the animators
to get a jumping off point.
Sherri Stoner was an actress,
a great improv comedian,
and just brought a lot of spark to it
and helped to inspire Glen Keane.
The combination really worked
into some very nice acting.
You seem very familiar to me.
Have we met?
We have met. I knew it.
You're the one,
the one I've been looking for.
Glen animated this scene here,
where she's trying to do
her pantomime thing
'cause she can't speak.
And how can she put over
what she did?
And it's just a tour de force.
Animation is great
when you have to rely on pantomime
to really put over the ideas.
Certainly, early on in this movie,
there was a lot of controversy
over the idea that our leading character
would not speak
for a big portion of the movie.
And certainly in story reels,
it was a problem,
because she seemed to disappear a lot
in the scenes where she didn't speak.
But we were kind of saying
when she's animated,
when the acting is there,
it will be different.
And Glen Keane and Mark Henn,
who did a lot of this material
where she doesn't speak.
I think that was the case.
Once the animation got in,
she was alive and she kept alive.
And it's a tribute to the art of animation,
but that's animation acting at its best.
Pantomime can be a tough sell,
as we found out with the carpet
in Aladdin, similar idea that...
You have to say "Trust us" a lot.
"Trust us. It will work."
One of the things that I guess also
helps keep her alive without her voice
is that music plays a role.
-Yeah, absolutely.
-It was key.
The underscore
becomes basically her voice.
It does become her voice. Yeah.
This sequence in the earlier version
of the film,
as we were working on it,
had been longer,
and it was felt that
this needed to be paced up a little bit.
So, this whole section
was trimmed down a little bit.
These washerwomen had a longer rant
that they talked about.
All this got compressed
and turned into one little set piece
of mistreatment of the crab.
There's also a bit with Max the dog
chasing the crab around the castle,
that got cut.
We had trouble with that shot.
Making it read, I think.
We did it four or five times. Yeah.
Just wasn't clear that those
were stuffed crabs or something.
Just something about it wasn't so clear.
Here, again, for all you continuity fans,
you can watch the knives and forks
jump around on the sides of the plate.
And one scene they're there,
one scene they're not.
You got a napkin, you got no napkin.
I don't know how we let
all that through, but we did.
This is one of my favorite scenes
where she walks into the tight.
Mark Henn animated it.
Just the staging of it and the layout,
Dave Dunnet is our head of layout,
I don't know if that was Dave's layout,
but it's one of my favorite scenes.
We always called this
the Cinderella scene.
She's coming out
in her magic dress and everything.
Let me help you, my dear.
There we go. That's better.
See, now, she had a napkin
in that last scene and no napkin now.
No plate, either.
Grimsby is Ben Wright,
who is a great character actor.
And we cast him.
We loved what he did in the reading,
we cast him based on that,
not realizing that he was actually
the voice of Roger in 101 Dalmatians,
and that he also did a voice
in Jungle Book.
But we didn't know that
when we cast him.
Yeah.
Carlotta's voice is Edie McClurg,
who's a great comic actress
who's done a lot of work
in film and television,
and was on Pee-wee's Playhouse
and various things,
but a wonderful comedian.
I know we tested
a fair amount of actors for Louis.
And there again,
whenever Howard's done the demo,
you feel like you got to find somebody
that is at least where Howard is at
and hopefully can bring
something more to it.
And that's not easy.
I knew Ren Auberjonois
more as a dramatic actor, and I didn't
know him so much doing comedy,
but when he came in and read
for the part and did this song,
he really brought a lot of comedy to it.
Of course, in different countries,
they dub Louis differently.
So, in France,
I think he becomes an Italian chef.
-Is that right?
-Yeah. That's right.
It's always somebody else.
You look at Chef Louis and you go,
"Would we get away with a song
in an animated now"
"in which basically
one of our characters"
"is literally describing
how you're going to kill?"
-Right.
-They're tight.
And all the imagery,
knives and axes and all that.
We loved it.
And we did it as was constructed.
But now,
I think they would give us a hard time.
Well, because people overthink things.
Les Poissons is a very slight song.
It's very French musical.
It's very deliberately in that style.
And it's mostly a comedy song.
And this song as a song is
a fairly compact, short song,
which really completes itself
with the chase sequence at the end.
Originally, this was a longer thing, too.
Howard had a whole,
"Class, do this and class, do this."
It was just a little too long,
so we had to tighten it up a bit.
Gary Trousdale story-boarded it.
Don Martin,
Mad Magazine sort of drawing.
Like many other sequences,
I remember it was a lot of trial and error
for the chase,
for the music we used
and the length of it.
And it also had
the demo love aspect
in that I really did not want to
use the cancan, Offenbach...
I really wanted to use...
And for whatever reason...
Did we give you a hard time
about that? I don't remember.
I just finally said, you know what,
somehow the cancan,
it really worked better for all of us.
And I just went, "Okay."
And I think I may have played with it,
and in the end we said,
"You know what,"
"we're trying to reinvent the wheel.
Let's just go with the wheel."
And the association
of the original cancan,
which everyone knew, was so strong.
It was a question in a Disney film
how far you can go.
And I think Howard found
which was right.
Had he gone a little further than this,
it might've been too far,
but I think it really works well.
-Cruelty can be very funny.
-Yes.
And his sense of humor,
of course, was...
He loved to beat up his characters
and just make merciless fun of them.
Howard was so smart
and had such a tough sensibility.
-He was caustic.
-Caustic, I think, is the word.
Alan did something on this movie that
we haven't done in any other movie.
And he actually wrote, in effect,
the silent film score,
where he on a solo piano
recorded a bunch of themes
that we then put against the action.
Again, many of which Alan recorded
without having seen the action.
There were ideas of sketches
of tones and things like that.
And we fitted to that in cases.
Occasionally, it seems to me,
he did it live.
That is, you're just watching the picture
and doing music,
reacting to the picture and...
There were times where we got so
used to Alan's solo piano underscore
that even when we heard
the whole orchestra,
there were a few spots where
I missed the solo piano,
and I actually said to the orchestra
a little bit, I wasn't sure,
"What if we just left those in
as solo piano?"
I was thinking specifically of the scene
where Ariel is brushing her hair,
and she's out on the balcony at night
and there was a beautiful theme.
It still is, the music that's there,
but it was just the solo piano that had
a wistfulness or something,
so we got used to those things.
-Well, it's called demo love.
-Yeah, right.
Yes, we've had a lot of that,
unfortunately.
It's very tough when you get
very used to things that are temporary,
but they're there for maybe three years
before they get replaced.
And this was another scene
that Howard rewrote our dialogue on.
-Is that right?
-Yeah.
"Just pucker up your lips."
These are Howard's dialogue.
We talked about her bedroom,
the design of it.
Howard mentioned,
"I think it should be very Laura Ashley."
And so, that was one of the things
we were going for
when we designed her bedroom.
And the lighting on this was really nice.
There again, we had to pick our spots,
but this has a nice
-warm feeling to it.
- "You are hopeless, child."
And Duncan Marjoribanks
did the pucker up scene.
That's a beautiful scene of Sebastian.
John directed that sequence,
but the little bedroom scene
is one of my favorite scenes
in the movie.
You are hopeless, child.
You know that?
Disney had gotten away from
those kinds of lyrical scores
that go along with the visuals
and accent the visuals.
You really brought that back, I think,
which was good and we wanted that.
I think people think just because
something is retro,
going back to the '30s and '40s,
that the reference will mean nothing
because our audience are kids.
And they don't realize how much
in the subconscious of our culture
can be accessed by artists.
It's not just whatever is contemporary.
There's a lot that's timeless in this.
We wanted to keep the King alive
and the story of
the lonely King,
where's his daughter at,
'cause the father-daughter
story was so strong.
Occasionally in these films, I get
to write standalone pieces of music.
The Tour of the Kingdom
is one of them.
Yeah, I love what Alan did on this.
Again, we had
a piano track version of this
that we were animating to, originally.
That was a very simple thing.
You don't often get to, as a composer,
write a continuous piece of music
that lasts more than about 15 seconds.
And I loved that Penny Lane horn
in there.
-That was neat.
-That was very cool, I thought.
Brenda Chapman story-boarded
this sequence,
and we struggled
with this goofy puppet show,
trying to make it read
and yet be quick and funny.
-Probably a little too quick.
-Yeah, too quick, probably.
Here are some thoughts
from an earlier interview
with myself and Howard Ashman.
When I had been offered the
opportunity to write the underscore
for the entire picture, I was looking for,
"How do you do this?"
And there's nobody around
who does this anymore, really,
this kind of underscore.
In a sense, you're choreographing
like you would a ballet.
You're choreographing the movie.
Therefore, you're pulling from
traditions that haven't been putted from
in years, in terms of underscore.
In the old days,
a lot of the music was written first
before they animated a thing.
Just even the background music
was written first.
And in some ways, we've gone back
to some parts of that old tradition
in deciding the songs as the story itself
is getting developed.
So there are lots of places where
they have animated right to the music.
If there's a little...
They've animated to that.
That... was in the little demo recording
that we made.
And it's been there for three years.
And finally it becomes
a little dance step.
It's amazing to see.
Now we come up to Kiss the Girl.
If there was gonna be a single,
it was gonna be Kiss the Girl.
But that never really developed.
When we wrote our original treatment,
we had a little sequence,
and Howard said,
"I think there could be a serenade."
And so that evolved into this,
Kiss the Girl.
And the stakes in that song, they really
help give a dramatic tension to this.
And it has a plot point.
We could never get Howard to just say,
"I'm going to write a song for the pop
market," until Beauty and the Beast.
We basically took the rock riff...
Which is the standard riff
you'd think of, in terms of
Phil Spector or Billy Joel,
and just turned it on its ear in
a little bit of a Caribbean way with a...
And just built up through
all the animals
into the various sounds,
into a full arrangement.
Those reeds that are coming up are
reused from The Old Mill.
The old 1937 Silly Symphony.
We try not to steal things
from other movies too often.
Unless they're great.
We all steal what we have to.
I actually did a little corrected
animation on that one scene of Ariel,
just sort of looking over.
Somebody adjusted the timing,
so one of the few scenes
I quasi had something to do
with animating in the movie.
It's strange, but I did.
Howard Ashman again.
Kiss the Girl has a little bit of a
Caribbean or maybe even a little Latin
feeling to it, and I'm a doo-wop person,
so it's got just a little bit of...
Thrown in there for spice and for fun.
Sing with me now.
It's a good time to talk about the voice
of Jodi Benson, which we hear
as the voice of Ariel
and then it becomes the entire
emotional impetus for Eric.
Jodi is somebody who had worked
with Howard in Smile.
And I had known Jodi for years
in New York.
Very talented actress, singer, dancer,
the whole deal.
We had auditions here in L.A.,
we had auditions in New York
that Howard supervised.
And we heard her audition,
not having been there,
present at the audition,
but she did such a great job.
In most of the auditions,
people would come in and sing
Over the Rainbow
or something like that.
And then on call backs,
I think they did Part of Your World.
But I think Jodi was very comfortable
with doing those slips between
speaking some lines,
singing some lines.
There's a very real quality
in Jodi's voice and she has the classic
Menken voice, which I really like,
someone who can give you
a good Broadway belt
but then mix into a soprano.
One of the things we did totally
differently than any other picture was
we went directly from our demos and
we had all of the vocal performances
done to synthesizers.
And then we wiped away the synth
tracks and recorded orchestral parts
-to replace them.
-Which was the wrong way to do it.
Occasionally, we got
into some trouble on that.
'Cause the mistake that we made was,
we animated to those tracks.
Unfortunately then, those tracks
all had to be replaced at the end,
and they had to hit
all these musical accents.
So it made a nightmare for
the musicians at the end of the line,
trying to hit these on-stage musical hits
that we had animated to.
It was a slight nightmare
when we were recording.
But they were great synth tracks.
And it gave the studio the comfort
to move forward with the project
without having to spend
a fortune up front.
Disney animation is always done
in the warm-cool thing here,
where you play off warm things
against cool.
So the little fireflies
against the blue background.
I just like that play of color.
And it's our homage to
Pirates of the Caribbean or something.
-Really?
-Yeah.
We had originally written a longer
scene between the Prince and Ariel,
hadn't we, at the end of that,
that we wound up doing away with...
There was a whole scene
that was gone.
Where the Prince talked about
his conflict,
of he likes her, but there's this
other girl that he's heard her voice,
and rubbing it in a little bit,
it was a
Hans Christian Andersen-y scene.
But we certainly had to cut things down
a lot, in terms of the story,
it got simpler as it went along
and essentially,
that didn't seem like it was necessary,
that you got the Prince's conflict
without him having to articulate it.
So we took that whole scene out
before we ever animated it.
This idea coming up wasn't
in the Andersen fairytale.
The Prince was getting married
to another girl, but it wasn't the witch.
The witch was more prominent
in our thing,
in the idea of the witch actually
using her voice and transforming
into something to thwart Ariel
from winning the Prince's heart.
That was an idea that we added to
the Hans Christian Andersen fairytale.
Also one of the things that
surprised me in our early screenings
was that scene
when the Prince looks in the window
and you see Ariel combing her hair
with a fork.
It got a strong reaction,
and it's something
that you'd almost take for granted
as you're working on the movie, and
the fact that people really responded
seemed to indicate like
they were getting something here,
they were really into that.
Howard again.
It's just amazing the way
the animators enrich and bring to life
and cause something inanimate to act.
It's like having the greatest actors
in the world performing your material.
And it's just what we had in mind.
And it is what we conceived,
in terms of tone
and in terms of content.
There's just something
about the Disney fairytale cartoons,
going all the way back to Snow White
and then to Pinocchio.
I grew up on Pinocchio and Peter Pan.
And the idea of doing one of those,
it's like there's all these
library books on the shelf.
There's Snow White
and there's Sleeping Beauty
and there's Cinderella,
there's Peter Pan, there's Pinocchio,
and to try to make something that fits
comfortably on the shelf with those,
what a difficult thing to do,
but what a great thing to try to do.
It's a humbling experience, I'll tell you.
But to try to do something
that could actually
be comfortable in that line of titles
is pretty amazing.
I think it does give you latitude
to work in all kinds of musical styles
and just to dream.
And this is one of early CGI,
computer-animated steps,
was still the infancy of computer
animation, but we used it.
It generated a 2D drawing
that then was painted,
but the actual stairs were built
in the computer
and then painted by hand based on
the drawings generated from that.
Congratulations, my dear.
Patty Disney, the wife of Roy Disney,
I remember her talking
after the preview.
Where this scene coming up is one of
Patty Disney's favorite scenes.
Where she's hearing the news,
and she does this little thing
with her hands,
and she's just kind of disturbed,
and she always singled this out
-as one of her favorite scenes.
-That's Mark Henn.
And Renee Holt, I think,
did the cleanup on this.
The cleanup on the movie
Vera Lanpher supervised,
and the cleanup staff did a great job.
Yeah, and the cleanup animation is...
The animators actually work rough
and there are other artists
that clean up their work.
They take the scribbler drawings and
make them tighter and more precise
for painting later.
In this case, we used black Xerox
for the characters,
but we wanted a delicacy to it,
so people actually used
a mechanical pencil to give
a very fine line,
which almost gave an ink look, in the
sense that the lines were thin enough,
they would pick up
some of the color around it.
And it gave a delicacy to it.
It was hard to do.
But they did a great job on the cleanup.
Roy Disney's involvement in the film,
certainly Roy had a nautical
background, he was a yachtsman,
he loved the sea, so there were various
points in terms of terminology,
he changed some of our dialogue
to reflect the truer nauticalisms.
I think he changed something
we had to "a following sea."
I still don't know
what a following sea is,
but we used that line
based on Roy's suggestion.
I think Jodi enjoyed also playing
this sort of villainous character
when Ursula has gained
Jodi's voice, so to speak.
She was sick of being sweet.
Gave her a little angle to play with.
The sea witch! Oh, no!
She's gonna... I gotta...
We first started to record the actors
in 1987,
and some of the recording
continued till 1989.
So it was about a two-year period
from beginning to end,
in terms of recording sessions.
We actually recorded the entire movie.
Everybody was out for a week
where we recorded
all the dialogue in the script,
all the songs in terms of that week, and
we started since we had all the actors,
we did a reading of the entire script
with the songs,
everybody singing the songs
and the actors doing their dialogue.
And it was pretty exciting,
except that when it was over,
it turned out that
nobody had pressed record.
We hadn't recorded the entire reading.
And we actually
then went back and did it again.
We did the second take
of the entire film.
I guess I blocked all of this out.
You were there, Alan,
but it's okay not to remember it.
It was a horrifying thing for us,
we felt responsible and we were.
I think we were probably the ones
who should have told someone
to press record, but...
It's like nobody said action,
so they didn't roll the film
and they blew up the fort.
But at the same time,
after it's going for an hour,
it seemed like maybe someone might
have wondered whether or not
it was supposed to be recorded,
but it didn't happen.
'Cause we had had table readings
before that
that affected the writing of the script
and the casting of the characters
a little bit.
But at that point,
I think we got a sense of the actors
playing off of each other
more so than anything.
We were happy 'cause we usually hear
the actors in isolation
and don't hear them as much
together in the same room.
And we got a good sense of
Ken Mars really feeling like
he could be her father,
and the difference in voice quality
between the crab and Ken and all that.
I think it came to life in the room,
but I don't think that we really rewrote
much based on that reading.
No, I don't think
we did a lot of rewriting.
I know we were a little concerned
at the time,
because we may have been a little
over-rehearsed at this point,
which is the difference between
Broadway and movies.
In animation, normally,
we don't rehearse a lot.
The actor comes in kind of familiar,
but there's a freshness to that.
As they're just doing
the dialogue spontaneously,
that we realized that the actors
had learned this like a stage play.
But there's a certain slight sense
of losing spontaneity that way,
so that they almost had to work
in the recording
to try to get the spontaneity back.
Usually, the way we did
the recording of the actors,
Ron would be out
in the recording studio
with the actor helping prompt them
and give them specific
on-site direction.
I would be in the recording booth
trying to hear it more the way
an animator would hear it.
I didn't almost look at the actor,
and I would just listen to the tracks
and try and just listen
to the vocal performance.
And Ron was doing that with Buddy,
and Buddy didn't like having
somebody breathing down his neck.
So, he did mention to Ron,
"I'd like to do this again. Alone."
And I slumped out.
We did a little sound trick
on her voice there
when it's this disembodied voice,
we made it sound
a little bit more ethereal,
and then as it comes back
into her throat,
then we dissolved off that effect
to give it more of Jodi's natural voice.
In our first script,
our first treatment even,
it's very easy to write
that she has the most beautiful
singing voice anyone has ever heard.
And now comes the point...
Now, you've gotta find somebody
who can live up to that.
But I think Jodi was the girl.
One thing I do remember is
throughout the whole process,
dreading the post-production
in which we were going to have
to thread that voice through,
and orchestrate around it
and somehow make it work.
It's very complicated.
I know that the earlier scene
where Ariel loses her voice and
it goes into the shell works beautifully.
And it seemed like
it might be problematic,
but you really have the sense
that she's singing,
and yet suddenly,
the voice is now in the shell
and it's not in her anymore.
And through the mixing and through
the performance, everything,
-that just really sold the idea.
-Disney has great sound people.
Great mixers.
Mel Metcalfe was the music mixer
on this.
Terry Porter was the head mixer
and Mel did the music mix.
Terry Porter did all the dialogue mixing
and made all the different recordings
-to match perfectly with the rich vocals.
-Fantastic guys.
...binding and completely unbreakable,
even for you.
I remember we had big meetings,
long meetings, all about hair,
just about hair and how to handle hair.
Underwater, things need to move.
So, it made it
a more complicated movie,
in that we wanted the hair
generally not to be at rest,
just to keep alive the feeling
that you are underwater.
It added a lot of complexity,
because the hair had to move at
all times in the underwater sequences.
Whereas in normal animation,
characters go into holes, they rest.
That gives the animator a rest, too.
But in this case,
there was a lot of extra work
that the audience
isn't really conscious of.
But it adds a lot
to the underwater scenes.
We had a great story crew on this film,
all the storyboard artists, Ed Gombert,
who also did
the Under the Sea sequence,
and Roger Alters, who was
a director on The Lion King,
Gary Trousdale, who was a director on
Beauty and the Beast.
We just had
a fantastic storyboard crew.
Chuck Campbell, who did
the sound effects on Roger Rabbit,
his team, Lou Edemann
and Rick Franklin
particularly did a lot of
the specific cutting for the film.
They were the team that really helped
create the sound for the movie,
trying to get
a unique underwater sound
and a fuller effects track
than had ever been done
on an animated film to that point that
we had been involved with, certainly.
And they had to really try
a lot of things to get variety
in the underwater ambience.
And there was a lot of work done
with that.
One thing I felt was good on Mermaid
that we didn't have to deal with was
we didn't have to really
deal with comparisons,
in the sense that nothing like this
had been done before at all, really.
And certainly nothing
had been done like this for years.
So, it was like,
"This is a real musical!"
"This is fresh. These songs are so
great and they tell the story."
But then, say, like when
Beauty and the Beast is done,
you're now comparing music you're
hearing for the first time with Mermaid,
which is music
that's become a part of you.
So, I've always noticed on the reviews
that when the next film comes out,
there were early reviews
of Beauty and the Beast
that would say, "Well, this score
is good, but it's not Mermaid."
And then Aladdin would come out
and it would say, "This score is good,"
"but it's not Beauty and the Beast."
How can you compare something that
you're just hearing for the first time?
We had a different version
of this earlier
where the witch didn't grow huge,
and Ariel stepped in the way of her bolt
at the Prince
and there was
a whole different scenario here.
And our boss, Jeffrey Katzenberg,
felt like it wasn't a big enough climax.
And at the time,
the movie Die Hard had come out.
And he's like,
"Guys, I want more Die Hard."
"How do we get Die Hard
into The Little Mermaid?"
So, we wound up with this giant witch,
which wasn't in the earlier draft,
and tried to make her more of
a formidable obstacle,
'cause she didn't seem formidable
enough in the earlier version.
Also, I think it was always intended that
she would be killed, which is tricky.
But by transforming her
into this monstrous giant,
maybe that made it
more acceptable to do her in.
Although she still is done in
in a fairly violent way.
These were all long sequences,
and it was...
You're just pulling the music out of you.
"Okay, another 20 bars."
Are we done yet?
Another 20 bars of Sturm und Drang.
Every time I see the end of this movie,
the general feeling that I get inside
is exhaustion, I remember.
It was my first score.
And I had come through about
two-thirds of the way just fine.
I get to the last third and it's...
Or last quarter...
And it's nonstop wall-to-wall
action-adventure hits.
And this was actually
in slightly pre-computer days.
So, it helps that you have,
nowadays, in terms of synching cues
and all that you didn't quite have then.
Well, it was a transitional time.
It was getting into MIDI stuff
and all of that.
Right, we were just getting into it.
I was, I think, one of the first people
to work exclusively in MIDI.
And it was an amazing help,
because in the beginning
of doing the score,
I would write the score
with the click track,
and set up my measures
and write the music.
And then I said,
"I want to see how it sounds."
So then, I play it into my computer
in MIDI and play it back.
And at some point in the way,
I said,
"Duh! Why don't I just write it
right onto the computer"
"and avoid this second step?"
The mermaid on the rock
was in the identical pose
with the mermaid in Copenhagen.
That was our homage to
the iconic statue there in Copenhagen
of Hans Christian Andersen's
The Little Mermaid.
And in terms of Howard's
writing contributions,
this one may be the biggest of all.
This scene was originally
played more pantomime.
The same idea, but without words.
And then Howard,
as we were going through it, I think,
feeling that, "There should be some
spoken words here to put this over."
And Howard wrote this little scene
with the King and the crab.
And the great thing he did is that
he put it in subtext.
Obviously, the King is saying,
"I'm going to change her into a human."
But without ever saying that,
he just says,
"There's one problem left.
How much I'm going to miss her."
And that says everything.
And that was Howard Ashman's line.
I remember talking to Howard,
when we were down in Florida
when the film was done, and there
was, I think, a parade or something
where they played music from Mermaid
in this parade.
I remember Howard crying
because he thought,
"This movie is going to last
beyond me."
And I think that was his first feeling that
this actually might move into
the culture, move into something,
that was going to go
beyond his own life.
And so much of Mermaid is Howard,
I think, obviously.
-He got teary about that, huh?
-Yeah.
But I think it was because
he knew his days were numbered.
-And that's for Howard.
-He was so vulnerable.
A man who was so tough.
He could just tear you out of the room.
You come in, you go, "isn't this great?"
And Howard would go, "Well."
We did want to wrap up
all the characters here.
-Wedding bells and Louis.
-So we brought Louis back.
Again, Jeffrey felt like the crab needed
to give Louis his comeuppance.
And so, we story-boarded this rather
late in the process and animated it.
We had an earlier idea where Louis
and the crab become friends.
And shout, "Friends, schmiends!"
I still wince slightly at this "yes"
moment coming up on the crab, but...
Teeth coming out.
And to give Jeffrey his props,
he wanted to add the line,
"I love you, Daddy."
Originally, we didn't have that
in that scene.
We just had an over-the-shoulder shot.
"And he was like," Well,
you can put that over the shot
'just to cement the..."
And so, here, the first Disney chorus
probably for quite a few years.
At first, Howard wasn't so sure
about using a Disney chorus.
And he was like,
"Is that too old-fashioned?"
But eventually, I think he thought,
"No. That actually aligns the movie"
"with these great Disney classics."
We had to reflect back
to the classic Disney score.
Snow White and Pinocchio
and all those things,
and this was a chance to do it.
This particular shot right here
is actually the first CAPS shot,
which is Computer Animated
Production System.
Yeah, rather than using cels
in that shot,
all the characters were painted
in the computer,
and that ship
was all composited in the computer.
Then that process later went on
to be used completely
from The Rescuers Down Under
to Beauty and the Beast,
Aladdin, The Lion King.
But that was its first test run.
It didn't work particularly.
We had a lot of problems with it
just in that one scene.
Every aspect of this production,
you could say
we definitely tested the waters
-with The Little Mermaid.
-Right.
We were trying things that
hadn't been done in a long time.
And we didn't know
how to do it necessarily.
It was a stretch for all of us, I think.
That was fun for us
to challenge ourselves.
But this established a new mold
mandatory for
every animated film after.
It established the idea of
an "I Want" song,
which was not a formula
idea within this, but...
And it made the Disney choir
okay again.
And definitely break into song
was okay again.
And our attempt in all this was
we wanted to make a film that
reflected our sensibilities.
And it wasn't a film that you just found
like it came from 1940,
and you open the vault
and there it was.
And I think it's a testament
to the people,
Howard and Alan and all of the artists,
everyone involved in it,
that they tried to put something
of their own lives
and their point of view into it.
So, they brought themselves
into the movie.
And that spirit, I think, is what helped
make it the success that it became.
It was also the film that kind of
re-established the idea that
animated films could be
watched and enjoyed
by adults and young people
even without children.
It's hugely hip
among theater audiences.
It became a date movie.
I don't know that anyone expected that,
it wasn't made with that in mind.
But it was a film
for audiences of all ages,
and it lived up to that.
I think that it works on different levels,
so that a little kid watching it
can watch it in a certain way.
And an older person can watch it from
a completely different perspective,
but definitely get something out of it
that's meaningful.
That's what Sebastian's there for.
A whole generation of kids
are now interested in
going into musical theater,
going into film, going into animation
because of The Little Mermaid.
And swimming.
Swimming became popular.
Sometimes I feel guilty.
I hope that they can all make a living.
Yeah. I think the music is
central to the movie's longevity.
And just the freshness of it,
and the emotion that
Alan and Howard got into this music.
And the relatability of
the father-daughter story,
as well as the characters
and the fantasy,
and the entertainment values of it.
I think musicals had sort of
become out of fashion
to some degree in film,
and that this reminded people
that there's something really wonderful
when it's all mixed together
-in a way that works.
-Yeah.
We were sort of regarded as heroes
for making this movie, in a way,
in that the movie musical
was dead and buried
-and eulogized and gone.
-Right.
It's still hard.
Right now, it's hard to get the movie
musical back on its feet again.
But every generation
has something that at least
keeps the flame alive.
And it's interesting how beloved this is.
It trumps all the other projects.
It was the one that
everyone attached to emotionally.
And when you think back,
-how young and innocent we were.
-Innocent is the word, I'd really say.
More so, at the time, I think,
we were sort of,
"Gee, this is kind of edgy
for a Disney movie."
"This has some things that's
never been done,"
"and Louis the chef and those things."
But you look at it again,
and this is so sweet and so innocent.
But not even just the film, I think
the atmosphere in which it was made,
there was an atmosphere of
"We're behind the eight ball,
gotta get the movie done."
It's usually, "Go faster,
you're behind schedule."
And yet, we didn't have the weight of
Lion King and Beauty and the Beast,
and all those other things, it was like,
we wanted to do a fairytale, we had the
weight of Disney fairytales behind us.
We'd all like to do something
that lives up to that legacy,
and that was imposing,
but there wasn't cynicism about,
"We have to repeat this,
or we have to avoid this."
It was just do what we felt
seemed right for it.
And you just went with your gut,
and I think it was
very innocent that way.
And everybody was young.
So this is John Musker,
thanking you for joining us
on this little trip down memory lane,
and hope you enjoyed
The Little Mermaid
as much as we enjoyed making it.
And this is Ron Clements, thanking you
for listening to this
and watching all this.
And hoping that you learned a little
more about the making of this film
that's certainly very special to me
and to all of us who worked on it.
This is Alan Menken, and I want to tell
you what a pleasure it's been for me
to share this time with
my collaborators here,
and sharing memories about
The Little Mermaid.