I'll never forget that summer.
I spent a week in the old house
where my mother grew up-
Planning & Screenplay by
Hayao Miyazaki
Produced by Toshio Suzuki
Based on "The Borrowers"
by Mary Norton
Music by Cécile Corbel
Almost there.
Feeling all right?
Yes.
Directed by
Hiromasa Yonebayashi
THE SECRET WORLD
OF ARRIETTY
How many times I have told Haru, not to block the drive-way?
- I'll be back in a sec.
- Okay.
Haru! You're blocking
the driveway again.
Sho?
Where are you?
Don't touch!
These aren't for you.
- Arrietty!
- Yes?
You've been outside again!
And you might want to clean up
this room, young lady.
This like my own li'l garden.
If you'd like to ask me,
it looks like a great big mess.
Oh! Look! Is that a bay leaf?
Oh, Ah, I guess this means
your birthday has come a little bit early.
Enough for a whole year.
But the bay tree's so far away.
What if a human bean saw you?...
Please be Carefull
I'm always careful.
The world is full
of dangerous creatures.
Your great uncle...
...was eaten by a toad. I know.
Oh! Don't this flowers just smell lovely?
So, they do.
With a bit of sugar,
I could make some juice out of this.
- Wait till tonight. I'll borrow some for you.
- You was...
It'll be my first borrowing!
I've been practising night and day.
Father's home.
Hello father!
- Father, I wanted to ask you about my...
- I've seen the boy in the house.
- What?
I saw him too.
- No! Arrietty...
- Oh! There's no way!He Couldn't have seen me.
I was safely hidden behind the bay leaf.
Father,are we going still borrowing this evening?
I won't hear of it.
It's too dangerous.
But he isn't even a boy!
It will be fine.
Huh father, I've been looking
for it, this is so long.
Children can be more terrifying than grownups.
It'll be fine!
Young boys, need to go to bed early.
Oh, Thank you, Father!
But Pod...
This boy seems to be ill.
So you need no worry.
But Still...
It'll be alright Mother.
I'll be extra careful.
Our Arrietty's going to be 14 soon.
She's going to have to learn it get by the world
When we are not here to help her.
Sometimes I feel like
we're the last Borrowers left in the world.
... And if is anything you need,
just ask Haru to help you.
All right.
Haru, I'm depending on you.
Yes, madam.
Let's put out the screen.
Keep the bugs out.
Shouldn't you wear something a bit darker?
No! this will be alright!
Try and remember to borrow
some tissue paper.
And even a cube of sugar, perhaps?
We could have it to sweeten juice
or we serve it for the tea later.
But, only if you can.
We'll be back home, soon.
- Please be careful.
- Of Course!
Arrietty!
Bye!
Excuse Me
- Arrietty! would you Hold these for me please?
- Yes Father!
Arrietty hold on tight!
Arrietty!
Ready?
Huh father it's all so big!
The world of human beings.
The sugar is in that pot.
Just wait here.
Father! you are great!
Now, let's get that tissue.
Father, look.
Then let that be Your first borrowing.
Be careful, it's sharp.
Yes!
Father, borrowing is such fun!
Look! down there.
Rats! Steer clear of them.
They're trouble for us!
I am not afraid.
If they would come
I can defend with this!
Sometimes it's best not to
go looking for danger.
What is this place?
Human beings made it,
to house all of their dolls.
This would be perfect for us!
I'm sure Mother would love
that dresser over there.
These things aren't for borrowing.
Anything goes missing,
they'd know right away.
So don't tell your mother.
Oh...
Don't need to be afraid of me.
Hey! I saw you!
Out in the garden today.
My mother, she told me about you.
She saw little people here
when she was young.
Was it you, she saw?
Was it?
I'm so sorry, Father.
The boy saw me,
outside in the garden today.
I should've been a bit more careful.
I hope he didn't frighten you.
I think it's best, you don't tell mother.
it will only worry her.
All right.
You don't always have to run.
Take the time to watch them first, then decide.
We're back.
Safe and sound.
Something wrong?
Things didn't go well this time.
This light gave out.
So we have to make our way back early.
Oh dear.
It meant we couldn't get your sugar.
Not to worry.
At least you're home safe and sound.
Arrietty, you found something.
Show your mother your very first borrowing.
What a pretty pin.
Time for bed.
Well, Good night then.
She looks completely worn out.
Shall I make us some tea?
Sho!
Come in the house.
You'll catch cold out there.
What! A cube of sugar?
So, why was it?
It was left by the grating.
It's probably the same one
I dropped last night.
What?
What do you mean,
you dropped it?
Don't touch it Arrietty.
Is that understood?
It's a trap.
They're going to track us down and then they will catch us!
Aren't they?
We'll just have to stop
borrowing for a while.
Maybe they already know
where we are.
Pod, we'll have to move!
Oh! This is such a lovely house.
Now we'll have to start again.
Oh!
Well, Should we see how things go?
Eat, soup's getting cold.
Ah! Why did it have to be the sugar?
Thank you, Arrietty.
I wanted to hang the clothes out
while the sun's up.
It's a pleasure.
I love doing laundry.
- I'm going to take a little nap. See You later.
- All right.
"You forgot something"
So, You came back to me.
Hey please! don't go.
You have to leave us alone.
I just wanted to tell you that.
I want, to talk to you.
Human beings are dangerous.
If we're found, we have to move away.
My parents told me so.
So You have your family then?
I envy you.
You don't you have one?
I suppose I do.
But I've never seen my father.
My Mother's always working
and barely has any time for me.
Is that so?
I would really like to know your name.
You can call me Sho.
Do you even have one? Oh do you?
Of course I have a name!
It's Arrietty.
Arrietty. . .Arrietty...
That's so very pretty name.
Would it be posible for me to see you then?
Even if it's just for a moment?
Oh just a little peek. Oh please?
What's going on here?
Ah! it's a crow!
You can't come in here!
Get Out!
What got into that bird?
I've never seen that behave like that before.
Perhaps it's time for their nesting season.
I need to replace this screen.
Where do we keep them?
Master Sho, it's high time.
You should to,.. you should take
some of your medicine now.
Thank you, Haru.
I.. I really feel fine. Thanks.
Hmmm.... The nesting season, eh?
Have yourself
a lovely long rest.
Father!
- I told you to stay away.
- I'm sorry.
I thought I should take care
of myself.
Father he really didn't see me.
Your actions put your family in danger.
I won't say it again.
Understood?
Yes.
I think it's time to start looking.
For a new home.
Oh Pod...
"You forgot something"
Hello! Got a package for you.
Thanks a lot for the drink.
It's so hot today.
Do you know of any good
pest control companies around here?
Oh let's have a look!
Here's one. "Squeaky Clean Services. Pest Control"
Squeaky Clean Services?
I'll write it down.
You having problems with mice?
Maybe it's mice,
Maybe it's something more interesting.
Between you and me, it's little people.
I've seen them myself. Hmmm ...
I hear, a crow tried to fly
into your room?
I hope it didn't scare you.
I'm fine aunt Sadako.
Haru chased it away.
I've never seen anything like...
A huge grey beast of the crow...
Excitement is the worst possible thing
in the world for his heart.
Haru! Sho came here for some peace and quiet.
If anything were to happen
before the operation...
Of course madam.
Gracious! I realize Sho's mother's work
is terribly important to her.
But to go abroad on business
and leave a sick child behind?
It's never easy for a young boy
to be without his mother.
You shouldn't worry about it. I don't mind.
I suppose the divorce was inevitable but why
she can't be here when her only child needs her so?
But why can't she be here,
when he needs her so?
Aunt Sadako, who made
that little wooden house in my room?
Looks amazing.
Ah, You mean the dolls' house?
It belongs to your mother.
When she was a small child.
She had to leave it here
years ago when she moved away.
It was Mom's?
My father had it made
specially to order...
...As a place for all the
little people to live in.
- Litle ...
- Father always said he wants so
little people in our home.
He waited for years.
In the hope of seeing them again
He always said that the house
was a present for them.
I'm afraid they never did
show themselves again.
Not in my father's lifetime,
and regrettably, not in mine.
Master Sho, I don't suppose you saw
any little people in your room?
Ummm...Unfortunately...not.
The dolls' house has been
passed down from my father.
I'm sure your mother would be
very happy for you to have it now.
Do.. do you mean that?
Yes.
Have you looked inside?
It's really quite beautiful!
- Haru, would you be so kind
to turn off the lights?
- Madam.
This is the living room.
All the furnitures were hand-made
by a real furniture maker.
Beautiful!
Don't you think?
Here's the library on the first floor.
There's even a study.
Wait untill tou see the next room.
That's my personal favourite.
- Haru, yould you be so kind?
- My Certainly!
I think it opens this way.
Wonderfull!
It is perfectly detailed and
just like the real thing.
even the oven works.
You could use it for baking.
Ah! it's Beautiful.
It is a pity Father's dream
never came true.
And it's been so long...
Maybe the little people
are gone now.
Mother, these same pictures
have been here for years.
Can't we change them?
I truly love those pictures.
I wish that one day
I'd get to see the real ocean.
Anyway, there's no point
changing now.
Father's a bit late.
I hope he didn't get caught
in that downpour.
- It's father!
- Sounds like he's at the back door.
Father! Are you okay?
I've twisted my leg.
Luckily Spiller here, helped me.
Pod?
Oh no! you're hurt!
Hurry! bring him in!
Does it hurt?
No, it's not broken.
I'll be fine in no time.
Come in.
I'll get you some cold water.
Here's a towel, dry yourself.
You?
I knew it!
It's not just the three of us after all.
I got to go.
Please don't. Stay with us.
Have some tea.
- I can attend to your father.
And you get Spiller a cup of tea.
- Of Course!
Oh! Thank you, Spiller.
Father's so lucky you came along.
We're so in debt to you.
Spiller, have you seen
other Borrowers?
You see, we thought we might be the only one
that were left in the whole world.
I think this many.
Ah! Then Cousin Lupy must be alright!
Is that a bow you have?
Can I look?
How you use this for borrowing?
Give that back Arrietty. It's not a toy.
Give.
Got to go.
But... but... We just about to eat something.
Would you like to join us?
You eat this? Hmmm...
Whoa! cricket's leg!
Want some? It's so good.
No thank you!
Get well.
I thank you again.
I'll see him out.
Did you go looking
for a new home then?
After I tripped and fell in the woods.
Couldn't move untill Spiller found me.
You were lucky.
Spiller lives in the land on the otherside of river really well.
He's told me, he knows about few places
where we could look to build a new home.
That's good, I suppose.
I'm not looking forward sleeping rough
I wonder if we find anything
as nice as this though.
I'm glad there are more like us.
It's make me feel better.
Oh Spiller! Do you never have
been with your family?
Family? No, just me.
All right. Please come. Visit us again.
- My mother makes really amazing stew.
- Okay
Haru?
Arrietty, your stitches
need to be neater.
You have to start over.
What what is this big bag for?
why we'll need it?
I think I go and see how father is.
Father, may I come in?
How's your leg?
Ah, I'll be walking very soon.
Father?
Are we going to move away?
The human beings have seen us.
We have no choice but to move.
I don't think that every
human being is dangerous.
Arrietty...
Long before you were born, there were
two other families living in this house.
One of them went missing.
They just disappeared.
The other one moved away.
They were seen by human beings.
No matter what happens,
this family must survive.
Father.
Oh My...What happened?
Earthquake!
Mother!
It won't open.
The frame's buckled.
Uh...not the wall!
Homily!
I always dreamed
of having a kitchen like this.
Gather only the things we need.
We won't be able to carry all that.
And Homily, take nothing
from the doll house. Please.
I'll go ahead and
make sure it's safe.
- Stay here with your mother.
- Yes.
You finally came back.
So, what do you think
of the new kitchen?
Our house is in really a big mess.
But it doesn't matter.
I came to say goodbye today.
Can I look at you?
Beautiful!
We are going to move away from here.
We have been seen by human beings.
Borrowers aren't meant to be seen.
- Oh... Borrowers...?
- We borrow things from human beings.
We take things we need.
and they won't miss.
Soap, cookies, sugar,
Electricity and gas, too.
Even my great-grandfather
was a Borrower.
- And no body seen them? Never?
- Probably.
I think this is all my fault.
Ah! Niya!... Niya! don't be like that.
Be nice to her.
Arrietty, are there other little people like you
living hidden away in the house?
No, it's just my father,
mother and I.
What about elsewhere?
I'm sure there's more.
But I've only met one so far.
Oh.
So, one day you might be
the only one left.
Every year you get less and less.
That would mean you're a doomed species.
That's not true!
There's lots more of us.
Spiller said so!
Spiller?
He's one of us.
And Spiller says there are
many more of us out there.
Do you have any idea, how many people
there are living in the world?
6.7 billion.
Six point seven billion...?
And how many of you?
I don't know.
There's probably
just a few of you left.
Before my mother told me,
I didn't know borrowers even existed.
There are so many rare species,
thay have already died out.
I've only read about them
in my school books, though.
So many beautiful creatures...
... have ended up dying out
as the environment changes.
It's... It's sad, but may be that's what
the fate has stored for the borrowers.
Fate, you say?
You're the ones who changed things.
and we are the ones who have to move away.
Fathe said that we must survive.
By own means.
So we're moving away,
even though it's dangerous.
We'll make do, we always have.
You don't know anything about us!
But we will survive this.
And we will not just simply die out.
I'm sorry. You're right of course.
- In fact I'm the one
who's going to die out.
- What?
It's my heart.
They're going to operate on it
next week, but it's hopeless.
Your heart...?
I've been sick since I was a little child.
I could never play with other kids.
When I saw you, I wanted to
protect you, but I failed.
I can't even do that.
I hope that you have forgive me.
You are in this really that bad?
What on the earth
is this doing in here?
Oh! the kitchen
from the dolls' house!
I found you!
What is it?
My mother! I heard her voice.
This really is a great kitchen.
And you're not the only
one little here, I bet.
I have to go.
Help! Let me out! Help me!
The ceiling's been moved.
- Hello, Paste Control.
- Hello? Squeaky Clean Services?
- Yeah that's us.
- Can you make an urgent house call?
- Yeah sure.
We have something small
in the house, but not mice.
- No! mice?
- I don't want them killed.
You need trapping services ?
Yes. I want you to trap them.
Sho! Sho!
Arrietty!
My mother's gone!
Someone took the roof off.
I think a human being got her!
Mother...
I'll help you to find her.
Someone's locked the door.
Let's try the room next door.
- It won't budge.
- Wait!
Here's a way in.
Amazing!
No, that's not it.
Farther down you will see a dirt track.
You turn in there.
- Before the bridge?
- No, no, after it!
Haru's opened this.
Then Haru must've taken
mother someplace.
Are you alright?
Oh dear... dear... What's taking them so long?
Mother! Where are you?
But I locked the...
Locked?
Can I have some hot milk please?
Yes! Of course! Of course!
Just a moment.
Thanks, so much.
So hungry.
Can I have any cookies?
Mother!
- Mother?
- Arrietty!
Here! here I am!
I'm here mother!
Arrietty!
Oh! at last!
They finally found the right road.
Uh!... Another human being!
Mother! It's okay.
Pardon madam, we'd like to take a look
around the house first, if It's so worthwhile.
Take your time.
Now who could this be?
- Haru? Haru!
- Madam!
What are they doing here?
My madam!
The little people here!
Little people?
Yes!
Little people who steal.
It's true! really!
They steal things from
all over the house.
That's why so much
was going missing.
Haru, what's got into you?
All these I might thought.
it was my imagination.
Well, it wasn't.
You certainly didn't need
to call in paste control.
We better hurry.
The house is full of them!
You'll believe me
when you see this.
This is their nest.
Nest?
It looks like a pile
of old junk to me.
Huh? What? What happened?
I swear I saw it. I swear!
Haru, I'm sending
paste controls away.
No, wait just a minute.
The dolls' house!
Master Sho? May we come in?
Of course!
Hard to believe.
They've even stolen the little kitchen.
You'll see, it's gone.
Not gone!
This kitchen always looks so nice.
Please, please, wait madam.
I've caught one in a jar.
That's strange! I wonder what's steepling Haru.
Hmm?
What wonderful fresh herbs.
Ah! Someone has been making tea!
It's just as my father said.
There are little people living here.
Yes, there are.
So Haru really did see them.
Though she accused them of stealing.
- They're not stealing at all!
They're Borrowers.
- Sorry?
I mean, I wish I could see them.
I'm sure, they're here somewhere.
I think so too.
Madam! Oh Excuse me, madam!
Is there any place you'd like us to start?
Oh, Are you all right?
It got out.
I had it right in here!
It's not my imagination.
There are little people!
Next time I swear I'll get them!
How far is it to where
we're meeting Spiller?
It's just the end of this woods.
Then we head down the river.
I'm so exhausted.
I really don't think I can make it that far.
Let's move.
I can't do it...
Better eat something now.
We'll likely to be walking through till sunrise.
I'm sorry.
We had to leave our lovely house
beacuse of my stupid selfishness.
That's in the past.
We'll make another lovely home,
with the three of us together.
I'm going outside for some air.
Don't stray too far.
It's Niya!
Niya... Niya...
Just a little further.
Spiller!
That's everything.
Now let's get moving.
Okay.
Mother, you allright?
Arrietty!
Sho!
Arrietty...
We're just about to leave.
I'm glad I got here in time.
Niya showed me the way.
Thank you. Look after yourself.
I... I brought you this.
I'd very happy, if you could accept it this time.
Oh! Thank you.
I must go now.
When's your operation?
In two days.
I'll be okay.
It's you, who gave me the courage to live.
It will bring you luck.
Thanks.
Thank You for having protected me.
Arrietty...
You take care of yourself.
Goodbye.
Arrietty, you're in my heart now and for always.
I'll never forget you, ever.
I'm fourteen years old, I am pretty.
I'm a teeny tiny girl, a little lady.
I live under the kitchen floor.
Right here, not so far from you
Sometimes I feel happy, sometimes I feel blue
In my dreams oh I wish I could
Feel my hair blowing in the wind
See the sky in the summer rain
Pick a flower from the garden for you
Beyond the lane there's another world
Butterflies floating in the air
Is there someone out there for me?
And so life goes on day after day
With knick-knacks on the floor, nooks and crannies
I live in a tiny world, I live in a tiny world.
But out there someone waits for me
I wish I had someone to watch over me
In my dreams oh I wish I could
Feel my hair blowing in the wind
See the sky in the summer rain
Pick a flower from the garden for you
Now I know there's another world
Butterflies floating in the air
There is someone out there for me
Feel my hair blowing in the wind
See the sky in the summer rain
Pick a flower from the garden for you
Now I know there's another world
Butterflies floating in the air
There is someone out there for me
A Studio Ghibli Film
THE END