-Yeah?
-Porco Rosso!
The Mamma Aiutos are on the move!
The Mamma Aiutos?
I don't work cheap, you know.
They're after a boat out of Venice
carrying a mine payroll.
Is that all?
No. There's a girls school tour aboard.
-That'll cost you.
-We'll pay Section 14-3 rates.
And 14-4, too.
Heave to!
Heave to or we sink you!
Wow! Pirates!
Not just pirates! Air pirates!
Time for an overhaul.
-Are you bad guys?
-Yep.
-So we're hostages?
-Are you air pirates?
-What a smart little girl!
-A skull!
-And very well-drawn!
-Come on! We're in a hurry!
-There's 15. Do we take them all?
It's not nice to break up the group!
Too late!
They took the girls and the money!
Bring them back for us!
They went that way!
No! They didn't go that way!
I know what those cheapskates
are up to.
They'll change course for the nearest
island as soon as they're out of sight.
They can't afford to waste gas.
Oops.
Come on!
I don't have much time.
Gotcha!
Just a tour plane
going round the islands.
Hey, it's a pig! A Pig!
Hey, piggy! He's so cute!
Look over here!
Hang around here and
the pirates'll get you!
Cool!
Will you all shut up?
-We're flying!
-Let me see!
Hey! Cut that out! Quiet!
Be quiet, will you?
Do something!
You're the one who said
to bring them all!
Just for a second.
I'm not supposed to let you do this.
It's so beautiful! Look!
-A red plane!
-Where? Where?
-Did you see it?
-Yeah.
That's as far as you go!
Here it comes!
-It's Porco Rosso!
-I can't see!
Oh, no!
-It stopped!
-We'll crash!
We've got another engine!
What are you doing? Fire! Fire!
That red plane's tough!
-You missed!
-Move!
A message from the pig.
-"You're beat. Do as I say."
-Shut up!
He's coming! Get down!
Where did he go?
He's hiding!
We crashed! We're going to sink!
No, we won't! This is a seaplane!
We're sinking!
Hey! Stop that! Halt! You're hostages!
Don't worry.
We're all on the swim team.
-That's not what I mean!
-Another message!
"You can have half the money.
Give me the rest and the kids."
Or I'll kill all Of you.
...is what he says.
-Half the money!
-Shut up! Come on, you swine!
It's you and me!
Take that!
It's busted!
We surrender! We surrender!
Don't kill us!
Bye-bye!
-Goodbye!
-He left us enough for repairs.
Don't be such a sap!
Be quiet, will you?
Don't pull on that! You'll break it!
Stay away from the propeller!
You've got to pee? Just do it there.
Another triumph for Porco Rosso
So the Mamma Aiutos
can't come tonight.
And that filthy pig
bounty hunter is a hero!
But this young kid's
an American, isn't he?
The air pirates of the Adriatic
can't ask an American for help!
His grandmother was a quarter Italian.
Anyway, we've got to do something
about Porco!
But 10% is outrageous!
Beautiful!
He's here.
With his snout in the air, as always!
Mr. Porco Rosso?
I'm from The Neptune.
Well done, sir! I guess
we won't see the Mamma Aiutos
for a while. I hear that bounties
might be a little bit higher this year.
Hey, you! Put me down!
Listen quietly to the music.
She's quite a woman.
Even American pilots know
Madame Gina at the Hotel Adriano.
Air pirates and bounty hunters alike
leave their quarrels outside.
So that's the famous Curtiss
parked outside?
The Rattlesnake.
Bringer of fame and fortune.
You beat Italians two years running
for the Schneider Trophy.
It's not just fast.
It's good in a dogfight, too.
But I hear tell of a "Porco Rosso"
who's pretty famous, too.
Be careful working with the pirates,
kid.
They're poor, they're cheap,
and they're smelly
because they don't bathe.
That's true.
Who are you calling dirty, pig?
Quite a distinguished gathering!
You boys must be planning something.
Correct.
Always glad to see you,
but no war games here, okay?
We know, Gina. We don't work
within 50 kilometers of here.
We're even polite to the pig!
That's my boys.
Be seeing you.
Wow! You're on fire!
Tell me what happened!
Next time we're alone.
That American's funny.
He took one look and said, "Marry me!"
So I told him, "I've married three pilots.
"One died in the war, one in the
Atlantic, and the third in Asia."
They found him?
I got a call today.
They found his remains in Bengal.
It's been three years.
I've got no more tears left.
The good ones all get killed.
To comrades.
Thanks, Marco.
You're always here for me.
You're the only one left
from the old days.
One thing I don't like about this place.
That picture.
Don't touch it.
It's the only one of you
when you were human.
The spell that changed you,
how can we break it?
That American jerk is a good pilot.
Must be nice to make that much money.
This month's payment.
That pays off the loan on your plane.
How about making a contribution
to the people with a Patriot Bond?
I'm not a person.
Hello, Porco Rosso! It's done!
Give me 60 bullets.
It's pretty crowded outside.
Yeah? Maybe the government's
going to change again.
They'll pass a law against you guys.
Laws don't apply to Digs-
That's for sure. Or moles like me.
Just regular bullets?
Not high-explosives or armor-piercing?
Listen, kid, we're not fighting
a war out there.
See you.
Thank you!
Hey, boss, how is war
different from bounty hunting?
War profiteers are villains.
Penniless bounty hunters
are just stupid.
We're air pirates!
We don't take out bank loans!
What else can we do?
These repairs were expensive!
Federation planes!
Why do we have to fly
with a bunch of losers like this?
It's all the pig's fault!
Can't those Mamma Aiutos
even afford paint?
That is shabby!
It looks like everyone's here.
Hey, is the American here yet?
He's up in the sun!
Right where he should be!
"Sighted target.
The Mediterranean Queen."
We're taking a ship that big?
That's why we all got together!
"Having engine trouble. Go first.
We will cover you."
"That's a dirty trick! We follow the plan!"
"Then we share repair costs!"
"You gutless wonder! We pay
our own repairs, just like always!"
"Do you want to be bombed?"
-"Engine trouble! Engine trouble!"
-"We settled all this before!"
"What a miser!"
"Split the cost or I'm out."
All of you, shut up!
Attention all passengers.
We are under attack by air pirates.
There is no need for alarm.
We carry two advanced fighter aircraft.
We will now introduce our pilots.
Number one.
The Black Stallion, Signor Valleta!
Number two. The Wolf of the Tiber,
Flying Officer Visconti!
-They've got muscle!
-That wasn't in the deal!
What a mess!
Get away from me! Curtiss!
Right! Let's go!
That's not good.
Guess I have to go to Milan.
...both pilots were shot down,
but parachuted to safety.
The Pirate Federation looted
the vessel and left this message.
You're next! Come and get us, pig!
We repeat.
"You're next. Come and get us, pig!"
Way to go, you turkeys!
Sorry. I'm on vacation.
White sheets, beautiful women.
Just get me to Milan, engine.
I don't like that weather.
I'll just have to go below the clouds.
Come on! You can do it!
That's right, engine! Good boy!
Pig!
It's one against one!
Not right now!
I'll tell everyone you ran and hid!
Catch you later, Yank!
Oh, damn! I'm in the open.
Gotcha!
No, you didn't! My engine quit!
Yes! Now I'll be famous, too!
I can't go back empty-handed, though.
They won't believe me without proof.
There!
That stupid red color. No mistake!
A souvenir for my mama in Alabama!
Hurry, please.
Madame!
Madame Gina! There's a phone call.
He's safe. He's alive.
Use the phone at the front desk.
Marco? Are you all right?
I was just leaving to look for you.
Good!
I've lost weight.
Two nights on a deserted island.
I'm taking the plane to Milan
to get it fixed.
If that American comes in,
tell him I'll be seeing him again.
Hey! I'm not a messenger!
I worry about you, and you treat me like
part of the furniture!
Someday you're going to be a pork
roast. I don't want to go to your funeral.
A pig's gotta fly.
Idiot!
Is Porco Rosso dead or alive?
I figured you'd be in tonight.
-I'm back.
-Messed it up again, huh?
-Why not just get a new plane?
-No, I like this one.
I know how you feel.
Look out. I'll back her in.
Who's the little cutie?
My granddaughter,
back from the States.
Keep coming, keep coming.
What a beautiful plane, Grandpa!
It's got great lines!
There's no one now
who can do work like that.
No resemblance.
-She's really your granddaughter?
-Hands off.
-Fio, lock up.
-Okay.
My opponent is Curtiss.
I need another 15 knots.
Curtiss?
I haven't heard that name for a while.
-Well?
-Where did you get a Folgore?
Don't ask.
The Italian that Curtiss beat in 1927
for the Schneider Trophy
had this engine.
But it wasn't the engine's fault.
The mechanic was a fool.
This is exciting!
Don't fine-tune it too much.
It's not a race.
Tell me about it!
You're explaining Buddhism to Buddha.
Are you going to take all I have?
These days money's not
worth the paper it's printed on.
Empty your pockets.
That's for the propeller, the paint...
That's for my hotel and my meals!
Stay here.
I'll give you room and board cheap.
-Where are your sons? Are they good?
-They're all away working.
-So who'll do the design?
-Fio.
Fio? That little girl?
She's young, but she's got
something my sons don't.
We've been together a long time,
but I think I'll try somewhere else.
Wait!
Are you worried because I'm a girl?
Or because I'm young?
-Both, miss.
-I can understand that.
Tell me, what's the main thing
that goes to make a good pilot?
-Experience?
-No. Inspiration.
I'm glad you didn't say experience.
Grandpa says you were very young
when you first soloed
and that you were good even then.
It was in 1910 when I was 17.
Seventeen? I'm 17 now!
Let me try. I can't help being a girl,
but we've got the old drawings.
If it's no good, you don't have to pay.
Okay, Grandpa?
She's kin. She'll do fine.
I took apart my first engine
when I was 12.
Sleep on this. We'll fix you a bed
tomorrow. Breakfast's at 7:00.
Good night.
You're still short, but we're old friends.
Pay the rest later.
-Good morning. Did you sleep well?
-Did you work all night?
This is just rough.
We'll leave this part as it is,
but use a different wing section.
That should give us five knots.
The old drawings were a surprise.
The wings were single-structure.
Whoever did this
really understood wood.
-I'm impressed.
-They only made one of these.
It was too dangerous to fly.
I found it in a warehouse.
I thought so. The way the wings are set,
-I'm surprised it even takes off.
-Landings and take-offs are tricky.
They're better at high speed.
Tilt the wings back half a degree for me.
Leave the rest the same.
So you'll let me do it? Thank you!
You won't be sorry.
But there's one condition, miss.
Don't work all night.
You don't do good work on no sleep.
It's bad for your looks, too.
All right.
Actually, I was so nervous last night
I couldn't sleep.
To tell you the truth,
I was afraid you wouldn't let me do it.
I'm so happy! I'll make some coffee.
I sure hope she's not going
to build it alone, too.
My niece Monica will do the drawings,
my great-nephew's wife the finishing.
My cousin's daughters. Sophia,
Laura, Constance and Valentina.
Fio's sister Giliola. Sandra's her cousin.
Marietta, you've gotten so pretty!
My sons' wives Maria, Tina, Anna,
and her sister Miletta.
Porcelino!
Grandma!
The angels haven't come for you yet?
You've grown up into a fine man!
You all work here, too?
To buy things
for our great-grandchildren!
There's not one man here!
-They're all family?
-Yeah. There's no work here.
The men are all gone away.
The depression...
Don't worry. The women are
tough and they work hard.
It's not pancakes we're making here.
Our Lord who art in heaven.
We thank thee for giving our
struggling company work and bread.
Forgive my sin of using women's hands
to build a warplane.
Amen.
Let's eat up and get to work!
That sounds good!
This engine was a good choice.
How do you like them RPMs?
Watch out or you'll blow the shed away!
Curtiss doesn't stand a chance.
Yeah, it's a good idea.
So can I do it?
Well, this is going to cost
a lot more money.
Look how far we are over budget
already, and our customer...
Porco...
Don't look at me like that!
Do whatever you like.
Great! I'll tell the workshop
and we'll get to work!
Porco, I love you!
I can wait three months.
-Maybe I'll become a pirate.
-She's a good kid, huh?
Hands off.
That's the furthest thing from my mind.
-So you're a Squadron Leader now?
-What did you come back for?
-I go where I want.
-The authorities won't like it.
-Are you being tailed?
-I shook them off.
There are warrants out on you for
treason, illegal entry,
decadence, pornography
and being a lazy pig.
It's not funny!
They want to seize your plane, too.
-This is a lousy film.
-Come back to the Air Force, Marco.
-I could still get you in.
-Better a pig than a fascist.
Freelance daredevils are finished.
To fly now you need a government
or an airline to pay you.
I only fly on what I earn myself.
Wherever you fly, you're still a pig.
Thanks, Ferrarin. Say hello to the guys.
This is a good film.
Be careful. They won't bother
with a court of law.
See you, buddy.
Want a ride?
Thanks a lot.
I borrowed this to take the plane
to the lake for tests tomorrow.
No time for that. I've got to fly.
Don't be stupid!
I'm not delivering an untested plane!
It takes a whole day to take it apart
and get it to the lake.
There's no time. Take a careful
look out the back window.
The Fascist Secret Police.
They followed you.
-Me? Why?
-'Cause I shook them off.
And you're fixing my plane.
Hey, are you really a spy?
Me a spy?
Spies are a lot more serious than me.
But you were a war hero.
Why follow you if you've done nothing?
I agree!
Wrong way.
I guess you did do something.
Time to get busy.
It's ready to fly.
There's two men out back and
three out front. This is so exciting!
Settle down, Grandma!
-I'll see you.
-Take care.
What are you doing?
Making myself a place.
Give me five minutes.
What are you talking about?
Don't be stupid!
-Don't shout!
-Listen, Fio.
You're a respectable woman.
Plus you're not married!
Hold this.
Thanks. I had to rush to make this.
A perfect fit! Hold that, will you?
Look, I'm a bounty hunter.
I don't run tourist flights!
I want to get my first job right.
I can make adjustments as we go.
I'm taking off from the canal.
I might not even get airborne!
All the more reason to take me.
You'll need a mechanic against Curtiss.
I'm a male, and
we'll be all alone on a deserted island.
Great! I love camping out.
That's not the point!
Take her along! If you don't
beat Curtiss, we don't get paid.
If you don't pay, we go broke.
You're her grandfather!
I'll give you a break on her salary,
and I'll throw in this voice tube.
-There'll be a price on her head, too.
-No. I'll be your hostage.
We'll tell the police you forced us
to help you. That'll be our excuse.
So please, take me with you.
I'll make myself useful.
Take out the right machine gun.
I don't care how small your bottom is,
it won't fit between them.
Great!
My hips are bigger than they look.
Wait a minute.
We'll leave now, before Grandma
wants to come, too.
Hey, that's an idea!
Grandma, quick!
Please don't buy me anything!
Contact!
Open up!
Let go!
Kidnapper! Pay us our money!
-How's the rudder, Porco?
-Very rough! Like you!
Harder to handle than ever!
Stop and I'll fix it.
No time! I've got to get her up!
This water's like glue!
Ship ahoy!
Here we go!
Come on, baby!
The flaps are in the water!
Use your tabs!
-Tabs?
-They're new!
Quick!
That's right! Now you're behaving!
Beautiful. The world is so beautiful.
-Are they after us?
-He's not attacking.
But that's an Air Force plane.
Ferrarin, I bet.
-You know him?
-The Air Force is waiting for us.
He'll show us a way through.
He says to go low and out to sea.
-Thanks, buddy!
-Thank you!
He saw you and told me,
"Pearls before swine."
Beautiful! A single rose
blooming in a secret garden.
Very rude. This is a private garden.
I just had to show this to you.
From Hollywood?
"In the matter of your starring
in the script you have sent..."
"Serious consideration"
and "please reply ASAP."
I call it Flowers of the Adriatic.
Nice name.
You like it? Then it's settled.
Gina, come to Hollywood with me.
Being a hired gun for air pirates
is a mere step to fame and fortune.
The next step is Hollywood star.
And then?
President!
I'm serious!
I'll make you the First Lady, Gina!
Gina!
-You're stupid. I like that in a man.
-Really?
But I can't. I'm gambling right now
that someone will visit me here,
and I'll tell him I love him.
But the fool only comes
to the club, at night.
He never comes out in daylight.
That jerk's come back!
Idiot!
He just kept on going. I lost my bet.
You mean you're betting on that jerk?
Can't I?
Life here is more complicated
than where you're from.
You can fall in love again and again,
but...
You go to Hollywood alone, kid.
"Kid"?
I bumped my head
when you did that roll!
Just saying hello to a friend.
Gina of the Hotel Adriano?
The woman in white on the terrace?
Grandpa told me.
All the pilots in the Adriatic
are in love with her.
He's got a big mouth!
What's she like?
Are you in love with her, too?
I'm putting down.
Shut up or you'll bite your tongue.
Hey, wait!
A girl riding a fighter plane!
-Where's Porco?
-Talking to my dad about something.
It's not just the caretaker government.
It's the royalists, too.
They want to link up
with the Pirates' Federation.
There's no money
in chasing pirates anymore.
-There.
-Thanks.
All this talk about a depression!
You ought to sell your services
somewhere, too.
A good pilot can make good money.
-Got any smokes?
-Curtiss'll go back to the States soon.
We're the ones
who should go to America.
"Farewell to the days of
fun and freedom in the Adriatic."
-Is that Byron?
-No, me. See you.
Porco, it's terrible!
Their fuel's three times
what it is back in Italy!
Give us a break!
We don't water our fuel here!
Man, girls are stupid!
-Talk to her, will you?
-Pay him, Fio.
Then stuff that bigger-than-it-looks
backside in with the machine gun.
-Off to the hideout!
-I'm putting the fuel on your bill!
They're fair.
We help each other when we need it.
It's pretty around here,
but no one's got much money.
There's the island.
It's beautiful!
What a great hideout!
My leg's gone to sleep.
-Look at all you silly idiots.
-Hey, boss! We got him!
Watch who you're stepping on! Move!
-We've been waiting, pig.
-We knew you were coming.
We've got a score to settle.
He's got a girl with him!
She's pretty!
Shut up! So what?
-Half the world is women!
-That's not just any girl!
She's Piccolo's chief design engineer.
-A cute little thing like her?
-Are you sure?
My plane's a lot better than it was.
She's young but she's good.
Really, Porco?
I never lie about planes.
Be nice to her.
She's here to make sure I pay the bill.
You're in debt, too? Serves you right!
Bust that plane up so bad
all he's got left is the loan on it!
You're going to take an ax to the plane
I built?
A plane as beautiful as that?
It's a long story, miss.
So you are!
-Well, you know...
-And you call yourselves pilots?
Move! Where are my shoes?
I was raised on stories
about seaplane pilots.
My grandpa always said
there's no finer people.
Their hearts are washed clean
by both sea and sky.
So they're braver than sailors
and prouder than regular pilots.
That's right. That's a seaplane pilot!
The most precious thing to them
isn't money or women, it's honor.
-Yeah! That's right.
-Good point, miss!
Hurray for seaplane pilots!
Oh, brother!
All right. We won't take our axes
and bust up the plane you built.
But honor won't let us just walk away,
either!
Mince the pig!
Yeah! Make hamburger out of him!
Don't be so pig-headed!
You don't understand!
Haven't you any shame?
You need an American to come
and save you?
Your mothers would weep!
And tell you to take a bath!
Porco's come back to go
one-on-one with Curtiss
for the honor of the seaplane
pilots of the Adriatic!
A man without honor or scruples
is nothing! Fight fair!
I always said we shouldn't hire Curtiss.
Stop trying to weasel out of things!
-What do we do, boss?
-She makes sense.
We could lose face here.
-Should we talk to Curtiss again?
-Get him to fight again?
-The contract's expired.
-This is embarrassing!
It's Curtiss!
I heard you!
I don't run, and I don't hide!
What idiot put a path up there?
Hold this for me.
So you want a return match?
But I already won once.
I'm no one's hired gun anymore.
So what do you want?
Beautiful!
Will you marry me if I win?
I'm serious.
All right.
But if Porco wins, you pay his bills.
-Wait, Fio!
-You keep out of it!
-Speak now or hold your peace, miss.
-It's up to him.
-This is expensive!
-It's cheap!
Yes or no?
I'll gladly fight for the woman I love!
Right! Listen, all of you!
I like this girl's spunk!
The Mamma Aiutos
will promote this fight!
Along with the Pirates' Federation!
See you later, Miss Fio!
You morons!
Don't forget to show up, pig!
Shut up and get out of here!
See you!
Look what you've gone
and gotten me into!
Don't be angry. I know it was stupid.
Fio, I've got to thank you, anyway.
You got me a chance.
Thanks.
I guess fate meant for us to be a team.
So we're partners?
-My chances are only 50-50.
-I believe in you.
"Believe." I hate that word, but
it sounds different coming from you.
What's the matter?
You're not feeling well?
Fio?
I'm fine.
My heart started beating so fast I
couldn't breathe. I was really scared.
My knees are all wobbly.
Hey!
I'm going swimming!
Porco, we screwed up!
-How?
-We should have padded the bill!
We blew it!
You're right!
-Porco...
-What? Can't you sleep?
I could've sworn... Or was I dreaming?
Go back to sleep.
Tomorrow's an early day.
Porco, why did you turn into a pig?
Well, you know...
My father was in the same unit
as a Flight-Lieutenant Marco Paggot.
I used to love the story of how
he jumped off a cliff in a storm
to rescue an enemy pilot.
Porco, shall I kiss you?
You know how the princess
turned the frog back into a prince.
Don't be stupid. Save your kisses
for when you need them.
Maybe I'm not the one.
You're a good girl.
You make me think
that all humanity's not a waste.
Now be a good girl and go to sleep.
Tell me a story, and I will.
A story? Let me see.
It was the last summer of the war.
We were on our usual patrol
over the Adriatic, heading for Istria.
Berlini was beside me.
An old friend,
who'd gotten married two days before.
I was best man at his wedding.
But we couldn't get leave,
so we'd come straight back to base.
Planes were going down like flies,
ours and theirs.
I had three on my tail.
I didn't have time for anyone else.
Then mine was the only one
of our planes left.
The enemy kept coming.
I was running away like crazy.
My hands and feet were numb,
I couldn't see. I thought I was dead.
Suddenly everything all went
white in front of me.
-White?
-Yeah, like I was in pure light.
But a light so strange it took a
while to realize I was in cloud.
I was so tired I didn't have
enough strength to fly.
But the plane just kept flying by itself.
A cloud prairie?
Yeah, and dead quiet.
The sky was so beautiful.
With that weird line of clouds
stretching up out of sight.
Berlini! You're okay?
Berlini! Wait! Where are you going?
Berlini! Stop! What about Gina?
I'll go instead!
When I came to, I was flying all alone
right down on the water.
God was telling you, "Not yet."
I felt like he was telling me
just to keep on flying alone forever.
No, Porco! You're good!
The good ones are the dead ones.
It might have been hell I saw.
End of story. Go to sleep.
That junkyard sold me rusty bullets!
I'm glad you came back alive. I like you.
Good night!
Place your bets here!
If you're real men,
put your money where your mouths are!
You'd think it was a carnival!
-They're all air pirates?
-The scum of the Mediterranean.
Gangsters, pirates, smugglers,
spies, plain-clothes cops,
a few respectable citizens.
This is going to make me
even more famous!
Ten minutes to start!
The showdown between Porco Rosso
and Donald Curtiss is about to begin!
There's no rules.
The first one to run is a coward forever!
Shut up! We came here
for a dogfight, not speeches!
Shut up!
Open your mouth and we shoot you!
A 10-ton bomb would be better.
This fight decides the fate
of our beloved Miss Fio Piccolo
who needs no introduction!
Know what I mean?
A big hand for Fio! Applaud!
Let's get this over with!
Quiet! There are formalities to observe!
Both sides will place their wagers!
-Miss.
-Thank you.
Put it down!
No complaints? All right,
shake hands and come out flying!
Forget it. I'm a hygienic pig.
-That's not very friendly.
-We'll go straight to the church!
Don't worry. My mother says
you can get used to anything.
-May we have a picture?
-We all took a bath!
-Smile, everyone!
-Smile!
Black wins if it's over in three minutes!
Maybe we could get them
to do this every month!
Five seconds to start.
That is so cool!
Five seconds, four,
three, two, one, zero!
Curtiss has the height!
It's all Curtiss so far!
Give me!
Come on, Porco! Get above him!
He's a better target up high.
He's harder to hit on the deck.
Don't worry! I've got lots of bullets!
-A barrel roll! The pig's on his tail!
-A barrel roll?
That trick made him
the Ace of the Adriatic!
Curses!
Now!
-He didn't shoot!
-Are his guns jammed?
He's not going to shoot
until the very last.
The pig's not a killer.
The American's still got plenty of ammo!
Now! Shoot!
He didn't! What did I tell you?
If he shoots now, he'll hit the American.
He's going to wait till he can put
two or three shots into the engine.
The damn fool thinks this isn't war!
Porco!
What's wrong with you? Shoot!
Or are your guns jammed? Too bad!
They're coming this way!
Come on! Fight like a pig!
Not this way! No!
He ditched the pig!
Go fight somewhere else!
Look at those vapor trails!
This you only see once in a lifetime!
This is so moving!
If she doesn't hurry, she'll miss it!
-She won't come out of her room.
-Are we going or not?
I want to see it!
F to Gina of my heart, warn pig
to stop fooling around.
The Air Force is coming.
"F"? That's Ferrarin.
Time to go!
-They're both really tough!
-They're just getting warmed up!
Go, Porco!
You stupid Pig!
You think you're going to have Fio?
Now the pig's got his tail!
The finale!
It's jammed!
The finish!
What the... Jammed!
What an idiot. You're out of ammo!
It's bent! Fio's big butt!
There aren't any ties in this game!
This isn't a cowboy film!
What are you going to hit with that?
You jerk!
What good's that going to do?
Hi-ho, Silver!
You rotten pig!
Missed me!
-Chicken!
-You ducked!
-This is for love?
-Shut up, pig!
-Something's wrong.
-They're coming down!
-They're back!
-Wait! The prizes stay here!
Useless! Guys, come back!
You gluttonous pig!
Cowboy!
Put 'em up!
Go punch a cow!
Come on, Porco!
Get up, Pig!
That's dirty!
-Uppercut! Block!
-Yes! Yes!
Yes! The Federation can set up
as bookmakers!
Bring a bell!
Can't you go faster?
No. The engine'll burn up.
Pilots are all crazy!
Fio! Did you see that punch?
I'll finish you in the next round!
-Next round you go to sleep!
-Stay in there!
You're going to be brain-dead!
Come on, Don Juan!
You're the Don Juan here!
Chasing every girl you see!
What about you?
Who's it going to be, Fio or Gina?
What?
Stop hogging them!
Gina.
"Miss Gina" to you!
Gina's in love with you!
She sits in that garden
and waits
for you to come!
-Porco!
-The bell!
Start the count! Look at him!
The Air Force isn't here yet.
Try to psyche me out, will you?
I don't get you!
It's the truth!
You won't get Fio!
That's Gina!
There's trouble!
First one to stand wins!
Coming through!
No, Gina!
Marco! Can you hear me?
Are you going to make
another woman unhappy?
Porco!
Thank you, Porco!
It was nothing.
Okay, the party's over.
The Italian Air Force is coming.
Get out of here, everyone.
Come to the club.
Drinks are on the house!
We're out of here!
It's over.
Boss! Hurry!
There are formalities to observe!
I hate the pig, but I like you.
Build some good planes. Bye!
Thanks. Take a bath sometime!
Thanks, Mr. Curtiss!
Next time it won't be a bet.
I'll court you for real.
Sure. But I've made up my mind.
-You ride in Gina's plane.
-No!
I ride in your plane!
We're partners, aren't we?
Gina, take this girl
back to the regular world.
You always do this. It's not fair.
Sorry. Away you go.
Take her up.
Here comes the Air Force.
Help me lead them away.
Hey! Your face! Wait!
-Show me your face!
-Your plane's over there!
Just one look!
Porco never showed up again,
even after the Air Force did its sweep
and I went back to Milan.
But Gina and I became good friends.
And we still are, through all the war
and turmoil there's been since then.
Now I run Piccolo Co.,
but I still spend every summer
at the Hotel Adriano.
Gina is more beautiful every year,
and there are lots of old faces.
Yes. Mr. Curtiss still isn't President,
but he writes us
saying he misses the good old days
of that Adriatic summer.
Whether Gina ever won her bet or not
is our secret.
The End