GOOD LUCK, CHIHIRO
WE'LL MEET AGAIN
Chihiro. Chihiro!
We're almost there.
This really is the middle of nowhere.
I'll have to shop in the next town.
It'll be great, once we get used to it.
Look, there's the school.
That's your new school, Chihiro.
It doesn't look so bad.
I liked my old school...
Mommy... My flowers died.
No wonder, the way you clung to them.
A little water when we get there
and they'll perk right up.
My very first bouquet
is farewell flowers, how sad.
What about that rose
you got for your birthday.
One rose isn't a bouquet.
You dropped your card.
I'm opening the window.
C'mon now, behave yourself.
It's a big day for all of us.
SPIRITED AWAY
Hey... Did I take the wrong turn?
I don't get it.
That must be it, look.
It must be that blue one over there.
That's it.
I must've missed the exit.
I bet this road'll get us there.
This is always how you get us lost.
Just a little farther, OK.
What are those little houses?
They're shrines. People pray to them.
Daddy, are we lost?
We're fine, we've got four-wheel drive.
Sit down, Chihiro.
You're going to kill us.
A tunnel.
What's this strange building?
Must be the entrance.
Honey...
Let's go back, honey.
Chihiro.
No...
It's just plaster.
This building's pretty new.
The wind's going in.
What is it?
Let's have a look. There's a way through.
It's creepy, Daddy, let's go back.
No need to be scared.
Just a little farther, OK?
The moving van'll get there before us.
So, let 'em, they've got the keys.
Let the movers move us.
I know, but...
No! I won't go.
Daddy, let's go back.
Nothing to be scared of.
I won't go.
Chihiro, you wait in the car.
Mommy.
Wait.
Watch your step.
You'll make me trip, Chihiro,
clinging like that.
Where are we?
Say, do you hear that?
It's a train.
Maybe we're near the station.
Let's go and find out.
What are those houses doing here?
I knew it.
This must be an abandoned theme park.
They built so many in the early '90s,
but they all went down with the economy.
This must be one of 'em.
What! No.
Let's go back, Daddy.
C'mon.
Mommy, that building's moaning.
It's just the wind.
What a lovely spot.
We should've brought our lunch with us.
They were making a river.
Hey, you smell that?
See, it smells great.
You're right.
Maybe they're still open.
Hurry up, Chihiro.
Wait for me.
This way.
Can you believe it,
they're all restaurants.
Where is everybody?
Over there.
Hey.
In here.
How amazing!
Hello, anybody here?
Come in, Chihiro, it looks delicious.
Hello!
Oh, don't worry.
We can pay them when they get back.
You're right. That one looks great...
I wonder what this is called.
Delicious! Chihiro, taste it.
I don't want to.
Let's go! They're gonna be mad at us.
Don't worry, you've got Daddy here.
I've got credit cards and cash.
Take some, Chihiro, it's so tender.
Mustard.
Thank you.
Mommy! Daddy!
OIL
Weird...
BATHHOUSE
There's a train.
You're not allowed here. Go back.
Wha--
It's almost night!
Leave before it gets dark.
BATHHOUSE
They're lighting the lamps. Go.
I'll distract them.
Get back across the river.
OIL
What's his problem?
Daddy.
Daddy, let's go home.
Let's go, Daddy.
Daddy! Mommy!
Mommy!
It's water.
This can't be...
I'm dreaming, dreaming.
Wake up!
Wake... up...
It's just a dream, a dream.
Go away, disappear.
Disappear.
I can see through.
It's a dream, it's got to be.
Don't be afraid, I'm a friend.
No, no, no.
Open your mouth and eat this.
Unless you eat something from this world,
you'll vanish.
No!
Don't worry.
It won't turn you into a pig.
Chew it and swallow.
Good girl, you're fine.
See for yourself.
I'm back again...
You see? Now come.
What about my mom and dad? They
didn't really turn into pigs, did they?
You can't see them now, but you will.
Quiet.
It's looking for you.
There's no time, let's run.
I... I can't stand! Oh, no.
My legs don't work.
Calm, now. Take a deep breath.
In the name of the wind and the water
within thee... Unbind her.
Get up.
NO ENTRY
OIL
Hold your breath
while we're on the bridge.
Even a tiny breath
will break the spell
and the attendants will see you.
I'm scared.
Be calm.
Welcome. Always nice to see you.
Welcome.
I'm back from my task.
Welcome back, sir.
A deep breath...
And hold...
Welcome back! We missed you!
Hang on, we're almost...
Master Haku.
Where have you...
Wha... A human.
Run.
What...
Master Haku!
Chase after it. A human intruder.
I smell humans! The stench of humans.
They know you're here.
I'm sorry, I took a breath.
No, Chihiro, you did very well.
Listen and I'll tell you what to do.
Stay here, and they'll find you.
I'll distract them.
In the meantime, you escape.
No, don't go! Stay with me, please.
You have no choice,
if you want to survive here.
And save your parents, too.
So they did turn into pigs...
I wasn't dreaming...
Be still...
When things quiet down,
go out by the back gate.
Take the stairs, all the way down.
Until you reach the boiler room,
where they stoke the fires.
Kamaji's there, so look for him.
Ask him for work.
Kamaji?
Even if he refuses, insist.
If you don't work,
Yubaba will turn you into an animal.
Yubaba.
You'll see.
She's the sorceress who rules our world.
Kamaji will turn you away,
trick you into you leaving,
but keep on asking him for work.
It'll be hard work,
but it will give you a chance.
Then even Yubaba can't harm you.
OK.
Master Haku.
I have to go.
Remember, Chihiro. I'm your friend.
How do you know my name?
I've known you since you were small.
My name is Haku.
Here I am!
Master Haku, Yubaba wants you.
I know. It's about my task.
Um...
Excuse me.
Um, are you Kamaji?
Um, Haku sent me here.
Please let me work here.
Darn, all at once...
Get to work, you little runts.
I'm... Kamaji.
Slave to the boilers that heat the baths.
Step on it, boys.
Um, please let me work here.
I've got all the help I need.
The place is full of soot.
Plenty of replacements.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Please wait.
Outta the way.
Um... What should I do with this?
Do I just leave it?
Finish what you start.
Hey, you runts! Wanna turn back into soot?
And you, watch it.
You can't just take someone's job.
If they don't work, the spell wears off.
Got no work for you here. Look elsewhere.
You sootballs got a problem?
Get to work! To work.
Chow time.
What? You guys at it again.
Cut it out.
Where's your bowl?
I keep telling you to leave it out.
Meal time! Take a break!
A human! You're in trouble.
They're having a fit about it upstairs.
That's my granddaughter.
Granddaughter?
Says she wants to work,
but I've got all the help I need.
Would you take her to Yubaba?
The girl can handle her, I'm sure.
Not a chance! And risk my life?
Take this, then. A roasted newt.
Real quality.
If you want to work,
you'll have to make a deal with Yubaba.
Might as well try your luck.
Fine! You there, follow me.
Can't you even manage
a "Yes ma'am," or "Thank you"?
Yes... yes ma'am.
You sure are slow. Hurry.
Yes ma'am.
What do you need shoes for! Or socks!
Did you even thank Kamaji?
He's looking out for you.
Thank you very much, sir.
Good luck.
Yubaba lives way up at the top,
in the back.
Get over here.
You wanna lose your nose?
We're almost there.
Right.
Here we are.
Wel... welcome.
This elevator is not in service, sir.
Please use another.
DOWN ONLY
-He's following us...
-Quit gawking.
UP
Here we are.
Your room is on the right.
Lin.
Yes.
What's that smell?
It's human. You reek of human.
Is that so?
I smell it, I do.
Smells mighty tasty, too.
You're hiding something.
Tell me the truth, now.
This smell.
Roasted... Gimme.
Not a chance. It's for the other girls.
I'm begging you. I'll settle for a leg.
Anyone going up, pull down on the lever.
SECOND SKY
SKY
OIL
Not going to knock?
What a pathetic little girl.
Come closer...
I said closer.
Ow...
You're making a racket. Keep it down.
Um...
Please let me work here.
Stop babbling.
You're just a useless weakling.
Besides, this is no place for humans.
It's a bath house,
where eight million spirits
can rest their weary bones.
Your parents had some nerve.
Gobbling up our guests' food like pigs!
Just desserts, I'd say.
And you'll never see...
your world again either.
You'd make a lovely piglet.
Or maybe a lump of coal.
I see you're trembling.
Actually,
I'm impressed you made it this far.
Someone must've helped you.
I must thank your friend.
Just who was it, my dear? You can tell me.
Please let me work here.
Not that again!
I want to work here!
Shut up!
Why should I hire you?
Anyone can see
you're a lazy, spoiled, crybaby.
Stupid to boot.
I've nothing for you.
Forget it.
I've got all the bums I need around here.
Or maybe you'd like the worst,
nastiest job I've got,
until you breathe your very last breath?
Stop that! What's wrong...
I'll be right there.
That's a good baby, now.
What? You still here! Get out.
I want to work here.
Don't shout.
I'll be right there...
That's a good baby, there, there.
Please let me work!
OK, OK, just pipe down.
There, there, now.
Your contract.
Sign your name.
I'll put you to work.
But one peep out of you about anything,
and I'll turn you right into a piglet.
Um, I sign my name here?
That's right.
Quit dilly-dallying and do it.
Unbelievable.
That ridiculous oath I took.
To give a job to whoever asks.
-Signed it?
-Yes.
-You're Chihiro, huh?
What an extravagant name.
CHIHIRO
SEN
From now on, you'll be Sen.
You got that? You're Sen.
Answer me, Sen.
Yes...
Did you call?
This child's starting work as of now.
Look after her.
Yes.
Your name?
What?
Chi... Oh, I'm Sen.
Follow me, then, Sen.
Haku... Um...
No idle chatter.
Call me Master Haku.
Even on Yubaba's orders...
We can't allow humans.
Her contract's signed.
What...
Thank you, everyone.
-Don't send her to us.
-Can't bear that human stink.
Three days of eating our food
and her smell will vanish.
If she's still useless then,
fry her, boil her,
do with her as you will.
Back to work! Where's Lin?
Don't dump her on me.
You wanted help?
That's right, Lin's just perfect.
-Go, Sen.
-Yes, Sir.
What a pain. You're gonna pay for this.
Off you go.
C'mon.
So you pulled it off, huh?
You're so thick, I was worried.
Keep your wits, now.
If you need something, ask me, OK?
What's wrong?
I'm dizzy.
So this is our room.
A little food and some sleep
and you'll be fine.
You wash your own apron! Pants.
You're so puny.
Too big...
Um, Lin...
What?
Are there two Hakus here?
Two?
Of him? I sure hope not.
Still too big.
He's Yubaba's henchman. Watch out for him.
Where the...
Here it is.
What's wrong? Are you OK?
What's all the fuss, Lin?
New girl. Says she feels faint.
Meet me at the bridge.
I'll show you your mother and father.
My shoes...
Thank you.
BATHHOUSE
Follow me.
Daddy, Mommy, it's me.
It's Sen.
Mommy, Daddy.
Are they sick or hurt?
No, they ate too much. Sleeping it off.
They don't even remember being human.
Daddy, Mommy, I promise I'll save you.
Don't get too fat, or they'll eat you.
Hide these.
I thought they were gone.
You'll need them to get home.
This was a farewell card...
Chi-hi-ro.
Chihiro... That's my name.
Yubaba rules others
by stealing their names.
You're Sen here,
but keep your real name a secret.
She almost got mine.
I'd nearly turned into Sen.
If she steals your name,
you'll never find your way home.
I no longer remember mine.
Your real name?
But it's strange. I remembered yours.
Go ahead, eat, you must be hungry.
I don't want to.
I put a spell on it
to give you back your strength, eat it.
You've had a hard time. Eat some more.
OIL
Can you find your way back?
Yes, Haku, thank you. I'll work very hard.
Good.
Where were you? I was worried.
I'm sorry.
Outta my way.
Is that the best you can do?
You and Sen get the big tub as of today.
What! But that's Frog work.
Orders from the top.
Better give it your all.
Aren't you... getting wet?
Hurry up, Sen!
Coming!
I'll leave this open.
-On the big tub, Lin?
-Lay off me.
Jerks! They haven't scrubbed this in ages.
This bath is reserved
for our filthiest guests.
It's caked with sludge.
Lin, Sen, first customers are here.
Right away...
Shoot, clearly harassment.
This tub needs an herbal soak.
Get a tag from the foreman.
A tag?
-An herbal soak tag.
-Right.
What's a foreman, Lin?
Something's coming. I wonder what.
Some useless scum,
under cover of rainfall...
I can't waste that on you.
Why good morning!
Feeling refreshed?
For Kasuga sama.
One deluxe sulfur soak.
No point in standing there. Back to work.
Scrub with your hands.
Good morning!
Your hands, I say.
But... Um... It has to be an herbal soak.
You sure are dense.
Oh... A fragrant bath coming up.
Relax and enjoy...
Hello, foreman here. Yes, ma'am...
Thank you so much.
That's not...
Hey, you, wait.
-What's the trouble?
-Why, nothing at all...
We have an intruder.
Is it human?
You figure it out. Haku's out today.
Wow, you got a really good one.
This goes to Kamaji.
Water'll be right up,
it's not too busy now.
Yank on this for hot water.
You're such a klutz.
Look at that color!
That's the dried worm salts.
With water this murky,
who's gonna see the sludge?
Yank it again when it's full. It'll stop.
Go ahead, let go.
I'll get our breakfast.
Sure.
Ouch.
Um... The bath's not ready yet.
But, there are so many...
Wha... They're for me?
But... I don't need this many.
No, just one.
Madam.
It's a Stink Spirit?
An Extra Large Stinker at that.
Headed straight for the bridge!
Please turn back!
Please withdraw!
The bath is closed for the night.
Please withdraw, please.
Peeeee-ewy...
Something's fishy.
Didn't seem like a Stink Spirit, to me...
Well, now that it's here,
better go greet it.
Just try to get rid of it,
as fast as you can.
Please retire to your rooms!
So terribly sorry.
Please hurry.
Lin and Sen, Yubaba's calling.
Yes sir.
Listen, this is your first job.
You take this customer to the big tub.
Um...
One peep out of you and you're coal.
Got that?
It has arrived.
Don't insult the customer.
Welggum to our bazzs...
Oh... Money...
Sen, hurry, take it.
Yes ma'am.
Zhow him de bazz.
Pl... Pleazze.
Sen!
Awful...
Our food...
Open the windows! All of 'em.
What? Just a minute.
Truly filthy.
This is no laughing matter.
Let's see what she does.
Ah, she intends to re-fill the tub.
Oh, no, soiling the walls
with those filthy hands.
Did you give Sen new tags?
Never, what a waste!
Oh no! All that precious herbal formula!
Sen! Sen, where are you?
Lin!
You OK?
I asked Kamaji to give us
all the water he's got!
He's sending the best herbal soak ever.
Thank you. He's got a thorn stuck in him.
A thorn?
It's in so deep, it won't come out.
Thorn!? She said thorn?
Rally the help downstairs.
Step on it.
Sen and Lin.
That's no Stink Spirit in there.
Grab this rope.
Yes ma'am.
-Hold on tight!
-Yes ma'am.
Hustle now,
and get the women to help them.
I tied it.
Everyone, all of you! All together now.
Heave!
And heave!
A bicycle.
As I suspected! Now, pull!
And heave.
Sen, you OK?
Well done...
Gold! It's gold!
Hands off! That's company property!
Be still. Our guest is still with us.
Sen, you're in our guest's way.
Get out and open the door.
Open the main gates! He's leaving!
Sen! You did great! You made us a bundle!
That River Spirit's famous.
You can all learn from Sen.
Sake's on the house, tonight.
Now! Time to hand over
all that gold you picked up.
Want some? I swiped it.
Thank you.
Man, oh, man.
I didn't see Haku.
Not Haku again.
He just disappears sometimes.
They say Yubaba makes him do bad stuff.
Really...
-Lights out, Lin
-Right.
There's a town. Looks like the ocean...
What did you expect after all that rain?
Some day, I swear I'll get to that town.
I'm gonna get out of here.
What's wrong?
Gold.
Who are you? You're no customer.
You're not allowed in there.
Hey! It's gold, gold! It's for me.
You can make gold.
Gimme!
Who goes there?
It's way past bedtime.
Hey boss, I'm hungry.
Starving.
That voice...
There, I'll pay you now.
I'm a customer, I want a bath!
Wake everyone up.
Mommy, Daddy,
the River Spirit gave me this cake.
I'm sure if you eat it,
you'll turn back into people.
Dad, Mom, where are you?
Dad!
Bad dream.
Lin...
Where is everybody?
Wow... it really did turn into an ocean!
I can see where Mom and Dad are from here.
Kamaji's already lit the fires?
Did I sleep that long?
The customer's waiting. Hurry it up!
Serve everything you've got,
even leftovers.
Sen!
Lin!
I was just going to wake you up. Look.
Real gold! He gave it to me.
This guest's a real high roller.
Please, sir, try this.
Taste the very best.
Throw us some gold.
Your blessings.
I'm starving, bring it all.
That guest...
Come, Sen, Yubaba's still asleep.
Now's your chance!
I'm going to see Kamaji.
I wouldn't go right now.
He's in a foul mood
'cause they woke him up.
Let's go back for more, Lin.
What if I don't recognize my parents?
I hope Dad hasn't gotten too fat.
The dragon I saw before!
It's coming this way.
What are they? Not birds!
Fight back, Haku! This way!
Haku?
Haku!
Oh... It's just paper...
Haku? That is you, right?
Are you hurt? Those paper birds are gone.
You're safe, now.
He's going to Yubaba...
Oh, no! He'll die.
The richest man himself has come
To grace us with his presence
Welcome.
Time to beg for tips
Time to start begging
Now beg
-Please, sir!
-Over here.
Gold springs from his palms.
Toss some this way, sir.
What are you doing?
I'm going upstairs.
No, you don't. What's this?
It's blood!
Move, move. Let our guest through.
Thank you for helping me before.
Don't just stand there...
I don't want any. Don't need any.
I'm busy, please excuse me.
Quiet! Quiet down.
Back, get back.
Please forgive her manners.
After all, the girl is only human
and new here...
Wipe that smile off your face.
I saw that look.
Why, I would never...
He ate them!
Yubaba!
We're in a fine mess, now.
Actually, he's a No Face.
That's right, a No Face.
Your greed attracted
quite a guest, all right.
Don't do anything stupid
until I get down there.
Look, the carpet's a mess.
Get Haku out of here.
He's no use to me now.
Sleeping outside of your crib again.
Oh, I'm sorry,
you were sleeping like such a good baby.
Baba still has work to do.
Go back to sleep now. Good baby.
Ouch, let go!
Oh, thank you for helping me.
But I'm in a hurry. Please let me go.
You came here to make me sick.
Bad germs outside, bad.
I'm a human.
Maybe you never saw one before.
You'll get sick out there.
Stay here and play with me.
Are you sick?
I'm in here 'cause I'll get sick outside.
It's staying in here
that'll make you sick.
You see, somebody I really care about
got hurt very badly.
So I've got to go right now.
Please let go of my arm.
If you go, I'll start crying.
If I cry, Baba will come and kill you.
I'll break your little arm.
That hurts!
Please, I'll come play with you later.
No, I wanna play now.
That's blood! Get it! It's blood.
Haku!
Stop, go away! Scat, scat.
Haku! It is you, right?
Hang on.
Be quiet! Haku!
Shoo, go away.
Oh, no.
I'm not afraid of blood.
I'll cry if you don't play.
Please be a good boy and wait.
If you don't play with me, I'll cry...
Please, wait.
What a racket! Simmer down.
You're a little butterball, aren't you...
Guess I'm still a little transparent.
Baba.
Oh, dear, can't you even tell me
from your own mother?
There,
that gives you a little more freedom.
Let's see now...
What shall we turn you into?
This is our little secret.
You tell anyone, I'll rip your mouth out.
Who are you?
Yubaba's twin sister.
Thanks to you, I've had a good look
at this place, enjoyed myself.
Now hand over the dragon.
What do you want with Haku?
He's badly hurt.
That dragon's a thief, my sister's lackey.
Stole a precious seal from my house.
Haku would never! He's so kind.
All dragons are kind. Kind and stupid.
Eager to learn my sister's magical ways.
This boy here will do anything
that greedy woman wants.
Move away.
It's too late for him anyway.
The seal was protected by a charm...
Any who try to steal it must die.
No, you can't.
What's gotten into them?
Hey there, cut it out!
Go back to your room.
Oh, dear, seems I was careless.
Haku! Oh, no!
Haku.
What on earth is this? Hey! Just wait!
Does it hurt?
This is serious.
Haku, don't give up!
Oh, no, he's going to die!
There's something inside him
that's killing him.
Inside him?
It's a good spell. Nothing I can do.
Haku, the River Spirit gave me this.
Eat it, maybe it'll help.
Haku, open your mouth.
Please, Haku, eat it.
See, it's safe.
Is it an herbal cake?
Open. That's a good boy...
That's it.
Swallow.
He spit it out! That's it!
The seal!
It got away! There! Over there.
Gross, gross, Sen! Totally gross.
Clean.
Haku took this
from Yubaba's sister, Kamaji.
From Zeniba? A witch's seal.
Precious loot, I'd say.
Oh... I knew it was Haku!
Look, Kamaji, it's Haku!
Haku!
Kamaji! He's not breathing!
Yes he is, but he's still very ill
from the spell...
That should calm him some.
Haku turned up one day,
just like you.
He said he wanted to learn magic.
I didn't approve...
of him becoming
a sorcerer's apprentice...
I warned him,
but he wouldn't listen.
Said he had nowhere left to go.
He signed up to be Yubaba's apprentice.
As time went by,
he turned increasingly pale,
and his eyes took on a sharp gleam.
Kamaji, I'm going to give this back
to Yubaba's sister.
Give it back, apologize,
and ask her to help Haku.
Tell me where she lives.
Go to Zeniba's?
She's one scary sorceress.
Please.
Haku helped me. Now I want to help him.
You can get there all right...
But getting back...
Wait here.
Let's see now...
It's around here, I think...
Everyone, I need my shoes
and my clothes, please.
Sen! I've been looking for you everywhere.
Lin.
That's Haku. What happened here?
Who are these guys?
My new friends.
Yubaba's tearing the place apart
looking for you.
The big tipper turned out
to be a horrible monster, No Face.
Yubaba says you led him here.
Maybe I did.
You serious?
I just thought he was a customer...
He's already swallowed
three of our people.
Found it! Here it is, Sen.
We're busy, gramps.
You can use this.
TRAIN TICKETS
Train tickets.
Where'd you get them?
I've had them for 40 years.
Now listen, it's the sixth stop,
called Swamp Bottom.
Swamp Bottom.
That's right, it's the sixth stop.
The sixth stop.
Make sure you get it right.
There used to be a return train,
but these days it's a one-way ride.
Still interested.
Yup. I'll walk back, along the tracks.
But what about Yubaba?
I'll go to her now.
I promise I'll be back, Haku.
You can't die.
What's going on here?
Don't you see? It's called... love...
It just keeps getting bigger.
Don't let it swallow me.
Here she comes.
Thank goodness, Sen.
Yubaba can't control him.
There's no need to get upset.
I'm sure Sen will turn up.
Where's Sen! I want Sen.
Go, hurry.
Yubaba, it's Sen.
Where were you?
Sen has come, dear guest.
We'll be right with you.
What took you so long!
This is a complete disaster.
Suck up to him and squeeze
all his gold out of him.
What's that filthy rat?
Don't you recognize him?
Of course not, how disgusting.
Now, in you go.
Call if you need us.
Is she all right in there by herself?
Want to take her place?
Try this, it's yummy.
Want some gold?
I'm not giving it to anybody else.
Come over here, Sen.
What is it you want? You can tell me.
Where did you come from?
There's someplace I have to go right away.
You should go back where you came from.
You can't help me with what I want.
Where's your home?
Don't you have a mom and dad?
I don't wanna...
I'm lonely...
Can't you get back home?
I want Sen.
Take the gold.
-Are you going to eat me?
-Take it.
Take it.
If you're going to eat me,
have this first.
I was saving it for my parents,
but you can have it.
Sen.
Girl! What did you feed me?
Out of my way!
Not on my premises!
Over here!
Here!
You'll pay for this.
Sen, over here!
There he is. Over here!
Don't call him over.
He's only bad in the bath house.
He needs to get out of there.
But take him where?
I don't know...
You don't know... He's following us.
From here, you walk.
You'll find the station.
Thank you.
You better come back.
I know I called you a klutz!
I take it back!
No Face, if you so much as touch
that girl, you'll pay for it.
There it is.
Train's coming, here we go.
I'm riding to Swamp Bottom.
You want to come, too?
Him too, please.
Come here.
Behave yourself, OK?
Kamaji.
Oh, Haku... You're awake.
Where's Sen?
What happened? Please tell me.
Don't you remember anything?
Just little pieces.
Chihiro kept calling my name
in the darkness.
I followed her voice
and woke up lying here...
Chihiro, huh...
Her real name's Chihiro.
Can't beat the power of love...
This gold hardly covers the damage.
That fool, Sen.
She just cost me a fortune.
But, Sen did save us, after all.
Silence!
She started it all,
and now she's run away.
Even abandoned her own parents!
They must be fine fat pigs by now.
Turn them into bacon or ham.
Please wait.
Master Haku.
What, you still alive?
You still can't see
that you've lost something precious.
Don't get fresh with me.
Since when do you talk that way?
Baby...
Baby!
It's just sand.
Where are you, baby?
Come out, please.
You!
Tell me!
Where did you hide my baby?
He's with Zeniba.
Zeniba?
I get it, that evil witch.
So she thinks she's beaten me.
So, what's your plan?
I'll bring baby back.
But in exchange, return Sen
and her parents to the human world.
And what becomes of you?
Let's say I tear you to pieces
after sending them back!
I think this is the right stop...
Let's go.
You can ride on my shoulder.
Come in.
Excuse us.
Well, hurry up and come in, then.
C'mon.
So you all made it.
Um...
Have a seat.
I'll make you some tea.
Zeniba, Haku stole this from you.
I brought it back.
Do you know what this is?
No, but I know it's very precious.
I'm here to apologize for Haku. I'm sorry.
-You felt fine while you held it?
-What?
What's this? The spell is gone.
I'm sorry. I stepped on that strange bug
that was on the seal and squashed it.
Squashed it?
You know,
my sister snuck that bug into the dragon,
so she could control her apprentice.
Squashed it...
You sit too.
You're No Face, aren't you? You sit, too.
Oh, um, please turn
them back into themselves.
Why my dears, the spell's long broken.
You can turn yourselves back.
My sister and I are two halves of a whole,
but we really don't get along.
You've seen what bad taste she has.
Sorceress twins
are just a recipe for trouble.
I'd like to help you, dear,
but there's nothing I can do.
It's one of our rules here.
You've got to take care of your parents
and that dragon boyfriend of yours,
on your own.
But, um, can't you even give me a hint?
I feel like Haku and I met
a long time ago.
In that case, it's easy.
Nothing that happens, is ever forgotten,
even if you can't remember it.
It's already late.
Why don't you stay the night?
You boys give me a hand.
Keep at it.
That's right, you're terrific.
You're a big help...
A magic one won't do the trick.
Pull it through there... And do it again.
I really have to go home, Granny.
Haku could die
while I'm just sitting here...
They might eat my mom and dad.
Just wait a little longer.
There we are.
Use it to tie back your hair.
It's so pretty.
It'll protect you.
I made it from the thread they spun.
Thank you.
What good timing.
We've got another guest, let him in.
Sure.
Haku!
Thank goodness.
Aren't you hurt? You sure you're OK?
Good timing, I'd say.
Look, Granny, Haku's alive.
Haku, I no longer blame you
for what you did.
Just be sure you protect the girl.
OK, boys, time to go home.
Come back soon.
You, stick around and be my helper.
Granny!
Thank you, I'm going now.
I'm sure you can manage everything.
My real name is Chihiro.
Chihiro... What a nice name.
-Take good care of it, it's yours.
-I will!
-Off you go.
-Yes.
Thank you, granny. Good bye.
Listen, Haku.
I don't remember it, but my mom told me...
Once, when I was little,
I fell into a river.
She said they'd drained it
and built things on top.
But I've just remembered.
The river was called...
Its name was the Kohaku River.
Your real name is Kohaku.
Chihiro, thank you.
My real name is Nigihayami Kohaku Nushi.
Nigihayami?
Nigihayami Kohaku Nushi.
What a name!
Sounds like a guardian spirit.
I also remember
how you fell into me as a child.
You were chasing your shoe.
Yes, you carried me
to shallow water, Kohaku.
I'm so grateful...
They're back!
You brought Baby back with you, right?
Baba.
You're not hurt?
What a terrible time you had.
Baby, you're standing all by yourself?
When...
Yubaba, you promised.
Please return Chihiro's family
to the human world.
Not so fast.
This world has rules, you know.
Shut up!
Baba, don't be so mean. Just do it.
Baby had such a good time.
But, a rule's a rule.
Otherwise I can't break the spell.
If you make Sen cry,
I won't like you anymore, Baba.
Why that's--
Granny.
Granny?
I'm coming to you.
Haku told me all about the rule.
At least you've got guts.
Here's your contract. Come over here.
I won't be a minute, Baby.
Don't worry.
See if you can guess
which of them are yours.
You only get one guess.
Get it right, and you're all free.
Granny, this is no good.
My parents aren't here.
Not here? That's your answer?
Yes.
Bingo!
Thatta girl! Right on!
Thank you, everyone.
Go! You win. Just get out of here.
Thank you for everything.
Good bye.
Thank you.
Come and see us.
-Haku...
-Let's go.
-Where are Mom and Dad?
-They've gone on ahead.
There's no water.
I can't go any farther.
Go back the way you came, Chihiro.
But don't ever look back.
Not until you're out of the tunnel.
What about you, Haku?
I'll speak to Yubaba.
Quit my apprenticeship.
I'm fine, now that I have my name back.
I'll go back to my world, too.
-Can we meet again?
-I'm sure.
-Promise?
-Promise.
Now go, and don't look back.
Chihiro.
Where have you been? Hurry up.
Mom! Dad!
You can't just run off like that.
Away we go.
Mom, are you sure you're OK?
What?
I'm sure the moving van's there by now.
Hurry along, Chihiro.
Watch your step.
You'll make me trip, Chihiro,
clinging like that.
The end of the tunnel.
Hey...
What is it?
Will you look at that...
It's all dusty inside, too.
-Some kind of joke?
-You think?
I told you not to stop here.
OK, all clear.
We're off, Chihiro.
Hurry up, Chihiro.
THE END